DAVID MALAN: All right, this
is CS50 and this is lecture 10.
Welcome to those parents among you.
Today, for those tuning in online,
is freshmen family weekend.
We have quite a few
guests with us and we
thought we would begin today in
fact by perhaps putting everyone
at ease since I know this is
perhaps the first time in a while
that you've been back to college.
Maybe this is your first
class for the fall semester.
And so we thought we'd
share with you by proxy
what you might be feeling
by way of a short film
that CS50's video team put together
with a little friend of ours
just a few semesters ago.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
- Hi.
- Hello
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: All right, well,
welcome to Harvard and CS50.
So if you'd like to actually
return in just a few weeks time,
your children or siblings or
friends or here in the room
will be exhibiting their CS50 final
projects in just a few weeks' time.
This is the so-called
CS50 fair, which is
meant to be a campus wide exhibition
of students' final projects.
And it's worth noting that, as
the students in the class know,
68% of the students in CS50 this
year had no prior CS experience.
And so what you and they will
see on display at the CS fair
in a few weeks' time in December
is all of their accomplishments.
And in fact, the goal
of this event really
is to delight in what everyone
has achieved and glancing
at each other's screens and phones
to see with great surprise what
each of our students has pulled off.
So you are invited back if you
would like for that as well.
Now CS50 of course is
characterized as a class
for those less comfortable
and those more comfortable
and those somewhere in between.
And I daresay some of our
guests today are perhaps
at one end of that
spectrum or the other.
And so rest assured that
what we'll dive into today,
the world of databases and SQL
with applications to data science
and beyond, is new to most
everyone in the room as well.
So you are in good company,
and I daresay 68% or more
of percent of the parents in the room
are perhaps feeling exactly as you are.
So if we can now turn our attention
back to some things lower level,
those students among you will recall
that we focused in recent days
on Python, this other higher
level language by which you
can solve problems a bit more readily
than you can using, say, something
lower level like C. Now you might
have noticed I'm ready if you dived
into problem set 6 as I'm sure
you have, the debug 50 only
supports C and not Python.
So you have relatively fewer tools
at your disposal for debugging.
But do realize that within
the CS50 library for Python
is a function like this
called eprint, which
you might recall if you've
used eprintf with C.
This is a Python version of the same.
And so if you need help
debugging your programs,
it suffices to write
a program in Python.
And anywhere you want to
see diagnostic output,
simply call this eprint function.
And it will print the file name
and the line number for which you
have written that line of code.
But let's turn our attention
now to things more web-oriented
and perhaps something with
which you're familiar Facebook
and the login screen thereof.
So there's so many websites out there
today where when you visit them,
you're prompted to log
in-- something like this.
But you're not prompted to log in every
time you click a link on facebook.com.
You're not prompted to log in
every minute or every two minutes
because indeed, the websites,
if they required as much,
they would degrade into
something downright unusable.
So instead, these websites remember
that you're logged in somehow.
So you log in once per
day, per week, per year.
It varies by website.
And then somehow the website remembers
that you are Maria or you are Brian
and you have already
logged into this website.
Now how might that work?
How does Facebook or any site
like it, Gmail and beyond,
remember that you are logged in once
you are logged in even though you only
type your username and password once?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, so they store
information on the server.
And indeed, that's exactly right.
On the server, as we're now starting
to see with Python and today with SQL,
you have the ability to store
information on a server.
We saw very simply about a week
ago the ability to store data
in, like, CSV files, just
text files on the server.
That's not going to be
very high performing,
so we're going to do
better than that today.
But you can also store data
in variables inside a flask
while it's running as we saw as well.
But we'll need some more
sophistication than that.
But yes, we can certainly remember
that Maria or Brian have logged in.
But how do we remember from
which computer or browser
Maria or Brian have logged in?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Via the IP
address-- so could work.
You could just recall that
from those virtual envelopes
which I no longer have today.
We've been writing the to address in the
from address, the IP address, on those
envelopes.
So you could certainly remember, oh,
I saw Brian from 1.2.3.4 and Maria
from 4.5.6.7 or whenever
the numbers actually are.
But that's a problem in, like,
households and frankly even
on campuses these days because of
NAT, Network Address Translation,
that technique whereby a bunch of
us probably in this room right now
on our laptops or phones are sharing
the same IP address, at least so
far as the outside world is concerned.
So we could confuse things.
And that would be bad because that means
if Brian sort of logs into Facebook
and Maria logs into
Facebook, suddenly Brian
might actually see Maria's
profile page or the like.
So what else might they be doing?
What's that?
AUDIENCE: Cookie?
DAVID MALAN: Cookie, so-- eh,
correct answer, but what in the world
does that mean?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Don't know--
OK.
So, perfect-- so you're
in the right place.
And most everyone in this room
probably, if you use the web frequently,
have generally heard about cookies and
probably that they're dangerous or bad
or some way or you've
probably googled how
to clear your cookies if
you've indeed heard they're
a bad thing or something like that.
And indeed, cookies are the
answer to this question.
But how does that actually work?
Well, if you've been to like
an amusement park or a club
or someplace where you typically have a
ticketed access gate, sometimes if you
want to come in go to and from the
parking lot or out to the street
or wherever, they might stamp your
hand using like a little red stamp
or invisible stamp or the like.
And then you just show it to the
bouncer or the person at the checker
that you had been there before
because you have this hand
stamp via the remembering you.
So web servers and browsers
are kind of the same.
When you visit Facebook or Gmail
or wherever for the first time
and moreover log in, they
essentially put like a digital hand
stamp on your browser called a cookie.
And that handstand
happens to be implemented
not obviously as ink but like
as a big random number that
is given just to you.
And it's stored either
in your computer's RAM
or on your computer's
hard drive longer term.
And your browser,
because it speaks HTTP,
that protocol we've
been talking about, it
has been designed to show
its hand, so to speak.
Every time you revisit Facebook,
every time you click an email,
every time you send a message, anytime
you browse around on that same website,
the browser is, without
you realizing it, reminding
the server of that hand stamp.
So how might it be doing it?
Where can a browser sort of tuck
away information like this such
that it's always in that envelope?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: It can put it like into a list
like you did before with the invites
or something like that.
DAVID MALAN: The invites, the invites--
oh, so that would be lower
lev-- so, OK, I remember now.
So that would be not
quite there because we
want to make sure that this
has nothing to do fundamentally
with our application.
This has to do with HTTP.
So this was invented years ago before
there was like a list of registrants
for [INAUDIBLE].
So we can't put it there.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: A concept of
a cache-- not here, no, no.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] header.
DAVID MALAN: The
header-- so the header is
where we have access to metadata, sort
of lower level technical information
that most of us never see
unless you poke around Chrome
or actually sniff your own
internet traffic and see.
But we do have the ability, within
these HTB headers, to send, so to speak,
this virtual hand stamp.
So let's recall what
these headers look like.
So the headers that get sent
in this virtual envelope
when you request Facebook's
home page, for instance,
might look like this-- get slash,
which means get me the home page,
using version 1.1.
The host I'm visiting,
just as a reminder,
is facebook.com or www.facebook.com.
And then below that
is maybe more headers.
We've generally waived our hands at
it because they're not as interesting
but there might be some
more information there too.
Well, when Facebook replies,
especially after you've
logged in, it turns out one of
the headers we haven't looked
at in addition to these which
we have seen, the response,
the 200 OK from the server,
is that Facebook and servers
like it are probably sending
this header as well, literally
Set-Cookie colon and then a name
and then a value or key and a value.
The name here, for instance, I'm
going to start calling session,
as is the term of art.
And then the value to the
right can actually be anything.
So value might be 123,
456, or any unique value
that's sort of randomly generated by
the server to remember who you are.
And so session equals value is like this
is your hand and this is your value.
That is now the cookie that's
been planted on the computer.
And what your browser thereafter is
supposed to do is not send set cookie.
That only comes from server to browser.
But whenever you on Facebook
request another page,
click a friend's profile
page or the like,
your virtual envelope will
contain not these familiar headers
but also cookie session equals value.
And so that is the presentation
of that same key value pair.
So if Facebook now to your
point earlier remembers
that user 123456 has logged in and
that user happens to be named Maria
and we can store that
information on the server,
every time Facebook sees
this same hand stamp
or sees this same session equals value,
it'll be like, oh, that must be Maria.
And so I'll show Maria her
messages and her profile page
and all that comes with it in a website.
So let's take a step back because
the mechanism is as relatively
simple as this, even though
it's certainly arcane
and you have to kind of know what
you're doing to leverage this.
But is there a threat here?
Like, why might cookies be
dangerous and why do people
tell us occasionally to delete them?
AUDIENCE: If some one gains
access to [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, if someone
gains access to your cookies,
you could masquerade as
someone else like Maria.
And so in the sort of
equivalent at a club or a part
would be if you kind of do this with
someone else's hand and try to say,
hey, we're both here even though one
is now backwards, that would be kind
of a duplication of the session value.
So you probably want to make
sure these are encrypted.
And what's the easiest way to
ensure that the traffic between you
and a server is encrypted?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Not hashing necessarily.
AUDIENCE: SSL.
DAVID MALAN: SSL or the
HTTPS prefixed URLs.
And thankfully-- and the story
has changed over the years.
Thankfully, web servers
are getting better
at supporting HTTPS because
then all of this stuff,
even though the browser can see
it and the server can see it,
it's at least encrypted
or scrambled to anyone
who's eavesdropping and trying to
see what's going on between the two.
But there have been
bugs along these lines.
In fact, it was just a
few years ago in CS50
where just days or hours
prior, a security researcher
had presented at a conference
some very easy to use
software via which you could
hijack other people's sessions,
or session highjacking
being the term of art here.
And what he had implemented was this
plug-in for Firefox, another browser.
And that would allow you, when
you ran this guy's plug-in,
to just sniff all of the wireless
traffic in the same room.
And it would show you, so user friendly,
a list of all of the session cookies
that were kind of going back and
forth through the air, so to speak,
that were not encrypted.
And this was, I don't know,
four or five years ago.
When HTTPS existed, it's
just not, a lot of websites
were actually really using it.
So a lot of really popular
websites weren't using it.
And so the demonstration in
class, which thankfully we
can't do anymore because most
websites have been more secured,
it was as easy as
clicking a button for me
to log into that here Rose's Facebook
account because she was using Facebook
during lecture and unbeknownst
to her, so now was I.
And it was simply a matter of
capturing this kind of value.
Moreover, if the session cookies
are stored, as they're called,
on your computer's hard drive,
there's just more remnants
of where you have been on the web.
Not just that little drop down menu,
but elsewhere on your file system
might be reminders for better or for
worse of where you have actually been.
So for these and other
reasons do you sometimes
want to clear these or at
least be mindful of them.
And frankly, from a
development perspective,
one of the reasons why we keep
encouraging you students to use
incognito mode occasionally
for development purposes
is to essentially clear
all of your cookies.
Incognito mode gets rid
of all of your cookies
temporarily so that you can
interact with the server
in a more predictable way.
And for software developers,
that's just useful
not to be confused by
older stale cookies.
Any questions then about cookies?
All right, so who cares?
Like, that's all fine and good.
Now we can be a little more
paranoid when using the web.
But what can we actually do
with this now that's actionable?
Well, if I go ahead into CS50 IDE,
let me go ahead and open up an example
that you can also look at later
on via the course's web site.
And this is a little web-based
store that I whipped up.
It's super common these days
to, like, buy things on the web.
And of course when you're buying
things on the web, hopefully
the website is remembering
what you are interested in.
If you go to amazon.com and click
Add to Cart, where does that go?
Well, let's think about it.
Amazon is somehow remembering,
after I logged in, who I am.
And we can assume that they're
doing that via cookies already.
So they're putting some
handstamp on my hand
and my browser is reminding
Amazon on every page click
that I am me who logged in previously.
So what do you think a server is doing
any time you add something to your cart
or quantity two of your car or
something else in your cart?
Where Where's that information
being stored as well?
Say again?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Also-- so in
the header, it suffices just
to put that cookie because
you proposed actually
earlier that we can store stuff in
a server, whether it's a CSV file
or in RAM or today in a database.
If you can store anything
you want on the server,
it suffices just to
remember via this cookie
that the person has logged in before
and uniquely identify him or her
thereafter by that cookie's value--
123456 or whatever it is.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: But there's a list
associated with your cookie?
DAVID MALAN: There's a list
associated with my cookie.
That is actually the perfect
segue to, yes, exactly.
And let's take a look at
what that actually means.
So this is a web based application.
To those of you in the audience
who weren't here last week
or the week prior or
the whole semester, this
is a programming language called Python.
It's the language we've now
started using over the past week.
And this is using what's called a
framework, freely available software
that other people wrote, called Flask
that makes it easier to implement web
based applications or websites.
And what we're doing in CS50, now
recall, is not making static websites.
We're not talking about
web design, per se,
which tends to be the art of
creating static content, very
beautiful informational websites, but
web programming, whereby we're actually
using logic to generate web
applications or web sites dynamically.
And so Python lets us do this.
So this, recall from last
week, is the magical line
that says give me a Flash
based web application.
And with this comes certain
features, like the ability to say,
hey Flask, define a route for slash.
That means anytime the user
visits slash, the default page
on a web site, return what
file, just to be clear?
Index.html.
And then we looked last week
at where those index.html are
and that they are
templates and so forth.
But this simply means render index.html.
So recall that I can run
this web app as follows.
If I go into the store
directory and type flaskrun,
I have now turned on a web
server, so to speak, in the cloud,
and it's literally telling
me what URL to visit.
So I'm going to go ahead and
click on this and click Open.
And we see a super simple store.
Let me zoom in.
It's really ugly-- haven't used any CSS.
This is indeed not web design.
This is all functional today.
And you'll see, even though the
projector is a little cloudy,
that there's three text fields there.
There's a number for
Foo, a number for Bar,
and a number for Bas,
which if I'm familiar
are just go-to words in
computer science when
you need to talk about something
that doesn't need a specific name.
It's like x, y, and z in math.
So right now, here's a store a la
Amazon.com that sells three things--
Foo, Bar, and Baz.
And I can buy any
number of these things.
But what we haven't
had yet is the ability
really to allow a user to
interact with a web form
and then store that information
and change that information.
We kind of scratched the surface last
time with the CSV file for [INAUDIBLE]..
But here now we have the ability to
actually store something in a database.
So let me go back to the IDE for a
moment and focus on exactly that.
So first of all, here is
how this program works.
I'm going to go ahead and buy myself
one Foo, two Bars and three Bazes,
whatever those are.
I'm going to go ahead
and click Purchase.
And now I see my shopping cart.
And just to be clear, if I hover
over the URL, I am now at slash cart
preceded by the long URL,
which is where I began.
So notice what's neat here.
I can reload and it's still the same.
I can reload, still the same.
I can even close the tab, open a new
one, go back to it, and it's still me.
Now let's see what's actually going on
underneath the hood in terms of code.
Well, to C/cart is
actually super simple.
Just render cart.html.
But cart.html, which I
wrote before this morning,
didn't know in advance
presumably that I was
going to buy one Foo, two
Bars, and three Bazes.
So it's probably not hardcoded.
So there's this other
feature of templates
in a web application
like this one whereby
in addition to telling the
computer show me cart.html,
recall that you can pass in values.
And I think we did this once last time.
So cart is just the name I've given
to this concept, like a shopping cart.
And I'm going to pass it
something called a session.
And a session is the term
of art that describes
whatever it is the server is
remembering on that user's
behalf per his or her cookie.
So the user's browser has
the hand stamp, the cookie--
123456.
The server actually
stores the session, which
is just going to be a box
filled with values, something
that has been put into that box before.
And so what I have now
in my cart.html is this.
Let me go into templates,
open up cart.html.
And this is going to
look especially cryptic.
But for those who've
seen it before, recall
that this just means descend
from or inherit from layout.html.
That's where, where, like, of the
standard HTML is-- head and body
and all that.
Then this says, hey, server.
Here comes the body of my website.
And there's relatively little in there.
Here's my big bold title--
cart.
And that's why a moment ago, we
saw exactly that, big bold cart.
And then over here,
notice that I'm using
Jinja, that templating language--
very lightweight, very Python-like,
and you'll get more
used to it over time.
Notice that we have here a for
loop saying for each item in cart,
go ahead and do this colon
that, which looks super cryptic.
But does anyone recall perhaps
from [INAUDIBLE] last time,
like, what does this syntax mean with
the two curly braces on left and right?
AUDIENCE: Variables.
DAVID MALAN: Variables-- just
plug in these values here.
And now as an aside, it turns out
that these curly braces are actually
escaping our data, so
to speak, in a way so
that if the user types in
kind of dangerous characters
at his or her keyboard, this prevents
that from becoming a problem,
but more on that some other time.
And so this is just going to say
item colon cart bracket item.
And this might be new syntax to some.
Where have we seen
square brackets before?
What does that mean in C?
AUDIENCE: Arrays?
DAVID MALAN: Arrays.
So in Python, we still have
arrays, but they're called lists.
But we have another feature
too, and you wouldn't know this
just by glancing at the syntax.
But when you see square
brackets next to a word
like cart inside of
which is not a number,
but it's going to turn out a word.
This word is literally going
to be Foo or Bar or Baz.
This is a way of using a hash table
or a dictionary or a dict in Python,
as it's called, whereby if the cart is
what's been passed into this template
and inside of the cart are a bunch
of items like Foo and Bar and Baz,
you can get the number of Foos by doing
cart brackets Foo, which would look,
if I hardcoded it, like this.
You can get the number
of Bars by doing this.
And you can get the number
of Bazes by doing that.
And yet if I just plug in
item, which is a variable,
I'm going to get out,
within this loop, the Foos,
then the Bars, then the
Bazes, and so forth.
So what is the end result?
Let's go back to the browser.
When I hit reload here, the
reason we're seeing Foo colon 1,
Bar colon 2, Baz colon three,
is because of that template.
And if I reload again
and again and again,
I'm seeing the same thing because my
browser is probably doing something.
So let me do that.
Let we go to inspect.
Let me go to Network.
And just for good measure, and you
should get into this habit too,
click preserve log.
Because this way, if you change
pages, the log doesn't go away.
You can still poke around
what you're seeing.
And again, this is my Network tab.
So I want to look at what Chrome
is doing to talk to this web app.
I'm going to go ahead now and I'm going
to hold Shift and then click reload.
Or if you click and hold--
you've probably never noticed this.
But if you click and hold on
your own reload button in Chrome,
you can do a normal reload, which
is what all of us do all the time,
or a hard reload or an empty cache
and hard reload, which is just
a way of saying get rid
of all of my cookies,
all remnants, and just forcibly
reload everything, which
is great for software development so
we know what state we're always in.
But you can also do
that by holding Shift--
whoops-- and clicking reload.
So let's do that.
Reload-- and here we go.
That made one request because there's
no images or CSS or fancy stuff
to send more requests.
This is going to be a little
overwhelming at first glance.
The IED itself uses
cookies for other purposes.
So you are seeing
bunches of cookies that
have nothing to do with
this application-- has
to do with the programming environment.
But what we can focus on is this here.
Notice that any time I get
a response from the server,
it's indeed sending me set
cookie and then some value.
Now this is a longer value
than 123456, but it's
the same thing-- a big random number.
So what's happening is
that is the server's way
of telling my browser you
are user 123456 or whatever
that big long number was.
And my browser is now supposed to
present that again and again and again.
So lastly, what is actually going on
when we continue shopping and let's
say buy 10 of these and 10 of these
and 10 of these and click Purchase?
Notice that if I look at the form,
this is going to slash update.
And it's via Post.
And so if I now go back to
the code to see what happens--
let me go back into
application.py, focus on update.
This now is how I'm updating the
contents of my server side cart.
I am saying for each
item in the form that
was submitted, the requests form,
go ahead and update session bracket
item, which is going to be Foo or
Bar or Baz because that is what
was in the form, and store there this--
request.form.get.
So get me the value of that item,
whether it's 10 and 10 and 10 or 1
and 2 and 3, whatever the numbers
are that the human typed in.
And why do you think
we put this word int?
Why might that be necessary?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's simple as that.
It's kind of a casting in C.
What the user typed in was text.
It might look like numbers, like 1, 0.
Certainly looks like 10.
But it's not a number.
That's a string that
looks like a number.
So using int converts it to an actual
number so we can do math on it.
So long story short, what is
it that made this possible?
We've not used this before, but you
will have seen this perhaps in P set six
or rather P set seven's distribution
code, which is now on the web site.
There's a few lines of code
that just enable sessions.
With those few lines, are we
able to tell Flask, hey Flask,
start sending cookies
and expecting cookies
back so that the programmer can
use what is called a session, which
I've additionally imported up here?
So I've just added some
additional functionality.
And if you've ever wondered
where all this data is going,
let me go ahead and stop the server,
clear my terminal and type LS.
A moment ago, the only
two things in this folder
were application.pi and templates.
Now there's apparently a
directory called Flask session.
So if you've ever wondered where Amazon
stores the contents of your shopping
cart or where Facebook stores Maria
or Brian once they've logged in,
it's probably in a folder
in a file like this
where these big long strings
represent your cookie value
or, better yet, it's in a database.
And so that's why those are
there-- because I apparently
created four cookies by reloading and
experimenting a few different times.
OK, any questions on
what the potential then
or the usage of cookies
and sessions are?
All right, so let's then
transition to solving
problems a little more powerfully
with these things called databases.
So here is, like, a depiction of
what we've been doing the past week
and we'll do a bit more today and you'll
do with problem set seven as well.
We have been having browsers
and servers talk to one another
using kind of a certain paradigm.
And the paradigm is generally called
MVC, Model View Controller, though we
didn't call it that last week.
And MVC means this--
you are writing code that
is called controller.
This is like the logic,
the intellectual property,
the business logic of your application.
Like, if a user submits form, then
add update contents of shopping cart.
Any of those kinds of
ifs and elses and loops
are in what's called your
controller code, AKA application.pi.
You might also have views, V in MVC,
which specifically are your templates,
the idea being that you separate all
of the interesting, juicy, intellectual
part of your program in the
controller code, the application.pi,
and all of the important
but kind of aesthetic stuff
in your templates directory, AKA views.
This way, among other
things, you, for instance,
can implement all of
the logic of a web site
whereas a friend of yours who is much
better at design certainly than me
can do all of the aesthetic
stuff, all of the views,
in the templates directory, and you
can collaborate a lot more effectively.
But there's one more letter in MVC.
It's Model View Controller.
And what we'll focus now
on today is the M in MVC.
Model is just a generic
way of talking about data--
like where does the actual data go.
So the mental model to have
moving forward as you write code,
even though the lines are
not going to be always as
clear as this picture
suggests, is any time
you're writing code in application.pi
that's probably controller code.
Like, that's the intellectual
workflow of your application.
Anytime you're doing
HTML or CSS or Jinja,
that's the view of your application,
the aesthetics, the presentation
of information.
And any time you're reading and
writing data, long term or short term.
That's the model.
And sometimes the lines
will be very blurry
and it could all be in the same file.
But those three types of operations
are the mental model to begin to adopt.
So let's get there.
You'll recall that in week zero,
we introduced this guy, Scratch,
and the graphical programming language
with which you began the semester.
A week later, we introduced C, which
had the same ideas and capabilities
for the most part but using a keyboard
only instead of graphics and a GUI.
Then we transitioned a week ago
to Python, a couple of weeks
ago now to Python, which is
very similar in spirit to see.
But as you may recall with
great delight or frustration,
you can get so much
more work done quickly--
for instance, P set five--
using the right language.
And so here too we
begin to use a new tool
for the job called SQL, or
Structured Query Language,
or S-Q-L. This is yet another language,
but it's much smaller than Python and C
as we shall see today.
But it is a language
that you typically use
when you want to talk to a database.
So based on your
familiarity already, what
is a database even if you've
never actually used or programmed
with one before?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Place
where your store data.
So a database is a place where you store
data- a base where you store data even
perhaps.
And so that's true.
And what does that actually mean?
Well, a database, like a web server,
is actually a piece of software.
We might think of it is
this, like, physical entity,
but a database is technically
a database program
that is listening for connections just
like a web server or an email server.
And any time it gets requests,
it serves up a response.
So we have the same client server
relationship that we do with the web
itself.
Now the database hopefully is better
and smarter and faster at storing data
than certainly little old me.
And it's hopefully better
than something like CSV files.
Like, recall we used CSV to store the
registrants for [INAUDIBLE] last week.
I think it was me and Rob
and Maria all at once.
Then what was good about that?
What problem did we solve by
introducing CSVs with that example?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: You didn't have
to go through my inbox, right?
One of the other versions
of the registration program
were to just email the proctor
in charge of [INAUDIBLE],, which
is fine because he or she can just
use labels and keep track of it there.
But that's not a database.
You're Just kind of abusing
Gmail as a database.
So why not put in a Text
file instead like a CSV?
Because what kinds of
programs can open CSVs?
Yeah, like Excel and Numbers and
similar spreadsheet programs.
You can import it into
Google Spreadsheets as well.
So that was a plus of using CSVs.
But what's perhaps a minus
even though we didn't really
experience the minus so much?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Harder to what?
DAVID MALAN: It is harder to do stuff
with it because at the end of the day,
it's just a stupid text
file, and we humans
have agreed to put commas in
between values we care about.
But that's it.
Like, there's no features.
You open up that file, you're just going
to see ASCII text and commas with them.
You get no, like,
features, no functionality.
And do you have another thought?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: It's inefficient why?
DAVID MALAN: It's harder to find things.
Certainly not in the case of,
like, me and Rob and Maria.
But as soon as you start having hundreds
of students registered or thousands
of customers in your database or
hundreds of thousands, like, in CSV,
the best they can do is
linear time for everything.
You have to search the
entire file top to bottom.
So wouldn't it be better if we
can borrow ideas from week zero,
integrate them into the context
of this problem, databases,
and actually query for data, ask for
it, change it, delete it, and edit it
much more readily than simple
little text files allow?
So what should you be thinking about
when you think about a database?
Well, there's different types.
And today, we're going to focus on what
are called relational databases, which
is a fancy way of saying
tables of columns and rows.
So this is a screenshot
of Google Spreadsheets
with which you're likely familiar.
The projector seems to be hiding
the fact that there are actually
rows and columns here.
And instead, we're just
seeing a big white box.
But there are indeed rows
and columns inside of here
as you can see on the screen.
And if I use a [INAUDIBLE]
this is a screenshot.
So I can't even enable rows and columns.
So here, we have our columns and rows.
So why is this useful?
Well, if you've ever store data for your
student group, or for your customers
or for other applications
around the house,
you've probably been in the habit of
storing things in rows and columns.
And what does each column typically
represent in a spreadsheet?
What kinds of things might it represent?
And here's an actual version
of Google Spreadsheets.
And let me actually highlight this and
turn on, just because, darker lines.
So there's our rows and columns.
So when you're using a spreadsheet,
maybe from personal experience,
like, what do you put in the columns?
I'm sorry?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Categories of what?
Give me a concrete example.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] the name of the
student and lab that they're in and--
DAVID MALAN: Oh, what
a delightful example.
So yes, we can say, like, the student's
name and the student's dorm and maybe
their email or if we
collected their phone number
and bunches of other things.
And you know, just to be sort
of tidy, we might boldface it,
and you can use features like this,
which just kind of lock that row there.
But these are just GUI features.
These are not sort of
intellectually that interesting.
But what do I typically
put in each row thereafter?
The first row is kind of
special usually, which
is why you can kind of lock it off.
What do you put in the rows?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: I'm sorry?
AUDIENCE: Elements [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, the actual data--
so, students' names.
So if, like, David
registered from Matthews,
you would put his information in there.
And then, like, if Rob registered
from Thayer put his in--
oh, that's not--
Rob's from Thayer, not Rob from Bowden.
And then Maria, who--
damn it, I asked her this the other day.
Where does she live?
[INAUDIBLE] Matthews, just like me,
which is why I should remember it.
OK, so here's-- we now might have
multiple rows in this database,
each of which represents an entity would
be the fancy way of describing where
an entity is like a real world thing or
a physical object or whatever it is you
care about.
So this is how we might form at this.
And of course literally, we might
format things using Excel or Numbers
or Google Spreadsheet's, like,
format column, which kind of
presents the data in a different way.
Maybe it centers it to the left
or-- the lines to the left or right.
Maybe it removes leading zeros.
Maybe it adds dollar signs, percentages.
You can kind of present the
information in different ways.
But for the most part, at the moment,
it's just text that I've typed in.
But if I want to actually find someone
in this spreadsheet, what can I do?
Well, I can do Command-F
and then type in Rob.
And there we go.
We found Rob.
But what did the spreadsheet do?
Pretty much looked from top to
bottom looking for R-O-B and as,
soon as it found it,
highlighted that row.
And if I had thousands of
rows or tens of thousands
of rows in the spreadsheet,
Rob might be all the way
at the bottom at which
point it could take longer
to actually find all instances of Rob.
And in fact, programs
like Excel and Numbers
and even Google Spreadsheet
eventually just start to break down.
In fact, I experienced
this in grad school
myself I was doing some research
where I wanted people to analyze data
and it was just convenient to be
able to double click on my CSV files,
open them in Excel, and look at
or search for some of the rows
that I cared about.
But it turns out that because of the
long running simulations I was doing,
I had, like, over 65,000 rows of
data, and Excel just wouldn't do it.
I would double click
and, sorry, this file
is too big because someone at
Microsoft, in prior versions of Excel,
had decided, first and
foremost, surely no one
needs more than 65,000
rows in this product.
But specifically, they used a number
of bits to represent the row number.
If you recall, we tend to deal in powers
of 2 or multiples of 8 specifically--
so 8 and 16 and 32 and so forth.
Well, 16 bits, 2 to the 16th, is 65,536.
And indeed, I must have
had 65,537 rows or more.
So Excel just kind of
wouldn't cooperate,
and I would have to use an actual
database like Microsoft Access
or Oracle or, as we'll see
today, something like SQLite.
So as soon as you kind of hit
some ceiling with the tool
whereby it's slow to search or the
program just can't open all of the data
or you can't kind of edit information
or delete information any better
than linearly, it's probably
time for an actual database.
And one such database is
called, indeed, SQLite.
So SQL, Structured Query Language,
is the language we're about to see.
SQLite is like a very
free and very lightweight
implementation of this database.
And it's a lightweight
in the sense that you
don't need special software licenses.
You don't really need to install it.
All you have to do is store
data in binary format.
So up until now in
CS50, we've pretty much
stored almost everything in ASCI or
text format except for P set 4's images.
Well, today we're back to storing
things in binary format, zeros and ones.
But again, we are well past the point
of caring what those zeros and ones
look like, the patterns there of.
So SQLite is going to handle
all of that complexity for us,
and it's going to store in
one big binary file containing
zeros and ones the same kind
of information as David and Rob
and Maria and others but
much more efficiently
because one of the things
you get from a database
is the result of a lot of
smart people's effort trying
to figure out how can we, on behalf of
the world, store data more efficiently?
How can we provide users around the
world with searching and deletion
and editing capabilities more
efficiently than he or she could
implement themselves?
So again, in the spirit
of CS50, we sort of
are standing on the shoulders
of people who've come before us.
Now what is this going
to mean in real terms?
We're going to use at
least one of two tools.
There's a tool called PHP
lighted min, happens to be
written in another language called PHP.
But that's incidental.
We're going to use it as a
graphical tool with which we
can interact with the database program.
But there turns out there is also a
terminal window version of a management
tool called SQLite or
technically SQLite 3,
which is just a text based way of
interacting with the database as well.
But that's just how we're going
to see the database visually
in my terminal window or in my browser.
At the end of the day, we're going
to talk to our database using
actual Python code.
But before we get there,
let's seed ourselves
with some of the basic
building blocks that we'll have
at our disposal with this language.
So unlike C and Python,
where we're generally focused
on the logical controls, conditions
and loops and functions and so forth--
some of those do exist in SQL.
But we're actually going to focus
really on just the operations, so
to speak-- the verbs that SQL supports.
So it's a little different mental
model to have than C and Python.
Specifically, perhaps the
most common operations
we're going to use when storing data
in not a spreadsheet like Google
but rather a binary file like a
SQLite file is these five operations.
We can create tables.
We can create-- we can insert rows.
We can select rows from the table.
We can update rows in the table and
we can delete rows from the table.
So these are kind of like
what you would expect
you would get from a database program.
It's just these happen to
be the terms of art as well.
Like, these are the verbs we use.
And it's conventional
to capitalize them,
but they don't strictly need to be.
So let's look at a few examples now.
If I wanted to, in an
actual database program,
create kind of the
equivalent of this idea--
rows and columns and
things called tables--
here's how I might do that.
So in my administrative program, which
we'll see in a moment, or in code,
I might do lines like
this, one at a time.
We'll review.
So in yellow now is CREATE TABLE.
So if you want to create the binary
equivalent, the computer equivalent
of like a Google spreadsheet
for [INAUDIBLE] registrants,
you would literally do CREATE
TABLE quote unquote registrants
where that's the name of the table
or the sheet you want to deal with.
And then this didn't fit on one line.
So I wrapped it.
But this is technically
one long command.
Then in parentheses, you specify a,
separated list of all of the columns
that you want to have
in that table, but--
and this is fancier
than Excel and Numbers
and Google Spreadsheets-- you
specify a few other details as well.
For instance, if my leftmost or
first column is going to be called ID
and my second is going to
be called Name and my third
is going to be called Dorm--
so similar to what you
proposed earlier but
we're not going to worry about
email and phone number and the like.
And I have added, for good measure,
a unique identifier, an integer
to identify each freshmen
registering for sports.
There's a few other details
I'm clearly providing.
Like, what type of information
is a name going to be clearly?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Text, and
indeed, SQLite has a data type
called not string but literally text.
Similarly, as dorm going to be text.
But ID is going to be
a little different.
It could be text.
But we get better efficiency
if we just use numbers
to uniquely identify humans, right?
Because even in my name, D-A-V-I-D,
how many bytes is that minimally?
How many bytes?
D-A-V-I-D. Five-- yes, five
bytes total for D-A-V-I-D.
But if we instead represent me in a
computer using a number like the number
one or two or even the number 2
billion if we have a lot of users,
how many bytes does it
take to store that number?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Well, even fewer.
If I just rep-- if my Harvard ID
number is just a single number,
like one or two or 2
billion, how many bits
do you need to represent
an int like that?
Typically, we've used four.
You could use eight if
you want a bigger integer,
but generally speaking, it's going to
be fewer than the number of characters
you're actually carrying about.
And so that's why I
might use an integer.
We'll come back to what primary
key means in just a moment.
But long story short, that
line, those lines in yellow
if executed in a database
program are going
to create the equivalent
of a spreadsheet containing
three columns that I care about.
Thereafter, if I want to insert
someone like myself into that table.
This is how you use the
SQL language to do so.
You literally execute
insert into registrant,
which is the name of the
table, then a, separated list
in parentheses of the columns
for which you have values
that you're about to provide.
And this allows you to change
the order if you really want,
but I'm just keeping it clean
and going left to right.
Then you literally write values.
And then in parentheses again, you list
a comma separated list of the values
that you want to plug
into those columns.
And again, it's up to you to make
sure that if you say ID first,
you put a number first.
Name second, you put the
name second, and so forth.
That's where we're in control.
Meanwhile, if we want to search
for everyone who has registered for
[INAUDIBLE],, we're going
to see syntax like this.
You're going to say to the database
select star everyone from the database,
specifically from the
table called registrants.
And that's going to
return to you literally
every row somehow in code
from the table Meanwhile.
if I want to change my name because
I wasn't sort of following directions
and they technically wanted
my full name for sports, well,
here I can do update
registrants, the table,
set the name column
equal to David Mailand,
but this last part is pretty key.
If I don't put where ID equals
1, what intuitively do you think
might happen in the database?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: All the names go to David
Mailand, which is probably incorrect.
And some of the C course's
head teaching fellows
will remember years
ago-- we actually had
a teaching fellow named
Michael [? Tingly ?]
whose nickname was Tingles.
And we accidentally executed
a SQL query omitting
this condition, this predicate.
Where we should have said where ID
equals Michael [? Tingly's ?] ID
number, instead we left this off.
And thereafter, we had like 700 Michael
[? Tingles ?] registered in the class
until we restored from backup.
So it can happen to you as it did to us.
Finally, if you wanted
to delete someone,
same principles, just different
verbs-- delete from the table
that you want to delete
from where you are
specifying an actual ID in this case.
And actually just for good
measure, though it doesn't strictly
matter, let me be consistent and
just capitalize that Where as well.
The reason for the
capitalization, just to be clear,
is that it kind of helps
the human eye to distinguish
what is, like, SQL syntax from
words that we humans have invented
for own spreadsheet.
And notice a few
characteristics as well.
I have standardized on all
lowercase for my column names
ID, name, and dorm, which is
common, but not strictly required.
The table as well is all lowercase.
But what is absent from all of these
field names is I'm not using spaces.
I'm not using funky characters
like exclamation points,
like "registrants!",
or anything like that.
I'm just kind of keeping it
clean with very simple characters
and that's good for portability.
It's very commonly the case.
And you might have seen or
experienced this in the IDE.
Any time you start using
spaces or funky characters,
computers sometimes get confused
because they're not expecting them.
So the best practice with
things like database design
is just avoid those issues
altogether and keep things simple.
Use underscores instead of spaces if
you really want to put something--
a gap between two things.
Now meanwhile, there are
different data types.
There's not terribly
many, and the only ones
we have to care about for the coming
days are these here, one of which
is kind of strangely named.
But SQLite, the database we're using
henceforth, supports text as we've
seen, integers as we've seen, or
AKA int-- some of these things
have aliases or nicknames
Null is going to be kind of the
opposite of having any value.
You can actually specify,
no, there's no value here.
Real is going to be what, perhaps?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, like a real
number, like a floating point value,
as we called it in C and in Python.
And then BLOB is binary large object.
So if you actually want to store 0's
and 1's in some form in your database,
you store it as a BLOB,
which isn't super common
because there are better ways to
store binary data like, in files.
But it is possible as well.
And it's worth noting that there's
kind of sort, of some other types,
but they're not sort
of officially there.
SQLite is nice because
it's pretty flexible.
There are a lot of database
programs out there.
You've probably heard of some of
them like the ones I rattled off--
Microsoft Access, Oracle,
MySQL, Postgres SQL, and others.
SQLite is just an alternative
that's pretty flexible.
And so if you try to load data from
like another database like Oracle
into SQLite, it will actually
tolerate unofficial types
like date times, which look like
years and time-- or dates and times
literally-- numeric, which
is when you're not sure
if it's going to be a floating
point number or an integer,
the database can figure it out
for you and some others as well.
So don't be confused when
reading up on SQLite.
If you see some things that
aren't wholly consistent,
it's just consistent with
that kind of flexibility.
And in fact, here's an exhaustive
chart of all the things from left
that map to the right.
So in the right are all of SQLite's
official data types, these five here.
And you might see on the
internet in SQL tutorials
and like bunches of other types here.
The most popular might be, like,
bigint, which is a 64-bit integer,
which is really big, varchar, which
is a variable number of charts--
either fewer or more,
depending on the data--
and lots of other things as well.
So just realize they're out
there, but the five on the right
are the ones we really care about.
SQL also has some built-in functions.
You can do this in Python
code too as we'll see.
But date and time and datetime allow
you to get, like, the current time.
So if a user registers
for your website and you
want to record when
he or she registered,
you can call functions
like this and the database
will just figure it out for you.
You don't have to check
the computer's own clock.
But most importantly, there's going
to be some of these decisions.
But before we forge ahead with too much
more, let me pause for any questions.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
when you [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Ah, good question.
Typically, no.
But if you want to be
really precise, yes.
So I was really precise and I actually
read the documentation this morning
to make sure I got all
of those quotes right.
The rule of thumb if you're curious--
though for the most part, this won't
matter and it shouldn't hang up--
is that any time you are referring
to the name of an identifier,
as it's called, like a
column name or a table name,
you use double quotes with SQLite.
Anytime you're referring
to a literal string
that the human has typed in
somewhere like with David Mailand
and like with Matthews,
you use single quotes.
So if it's kind of user input, single.
If it's a name in your database,
then it's double coated,
but it doesn't typically matter.
So don't fret two much.
So let's consider then
for just a moment where we
started this particular conversation.
We were trying to create a database
or spreadsheet for [INAUDIBLE] IM's,
but we kind of stopped
short of the juicy part.
Like, I typed in some
names and some dorms.
But I could have started
typing email, which
would have hopefully some standard
format-- something at something dot
whatever.
And then phone number is
kind of interesting, right?
Like, how should I store a number?
Like, if I just want people
calling Harvard's main number,
is that, like, 459-- what is it 5,000?
Well should I store it like this--
10 digits and two hyphens?
Should I instead store it without the
hyphens just to kind of save space?
Should I, need to be consistent
with international folks,
store the country code as well, which
now Google is confusing for math?
So that's what Harvard's phone number
is when you add the numbers together
apparently.
How do you store the information?
Or better still, what should
you expect the users to type in?
When you visit a website and you
are asked for your phone number
to buy something or create an
account, like, in what format
are you typically prompted for
your number at least in the US?
AUDIENCE: Area code, [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, you're often prompted
[INAUDIBLE] like an example like this.
And then you have to
type it in and hit Enter.
And then it's stored, like that.
What else have you seen--
probably the other formats too?
So which way should you do it?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yes, yes, all of these
ways are perfectly reasonable,
and any website that forces you to type
your data into one format is stupid.
Like, it is poorly designed.
And this is one of my greatest--
well, it's not my greatest pet peeves.
But like, one of my pet peeves is
when a web site just completely
technologically unnecessarily puts the
burden of the human to format the data.
Like, I should certainly be able
to type my information in like this
or with the plus one or
without the parentheses
or with an additional hyphen or
the like because you know what you
the programmer who made
the website can do?
You can just use some
kind of pattern matching
in the spirit even of P set six,
throw away all of the punctuation,
and then store just the
digits if you want or go in
and forcibly add the
hyphens where you want them
or the parentheses where you want them.
The burden does not
need to be on the human.
And there's actually compelling
UX, or User Experience,
reasons for this beyond me
going off kind of on a rant.
Like, if you can't copy and
paste something into a field,
that is a bad user experience.
And if you've ever tried to
just copy one field into another
and the website is disabling that
for you, it's not the best practice.
Worse yet are websites that don't let
you paste your passwords into the forms
because if you store your passwords,
as is good practice, in like a password
manager, encrypted somehow, it's
better to have a really long password
and then paste it into the form than
memorize a really short password
that someone else could guess.
So in short, as we move
forward with web programming,
don't necessarily take as canon, like,
what you see out there, but consider
for your own users, like, what
would be the best way to do this
and how can I, knowing programming,
accommodate different styles
and expectations as well?
But at the end of the
day, there's an issue here
because is this phone number now a
number, or is it a string or text?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So OK, so I
heard a few strings or text.
So that's good because
SQLite supports text.
So I could specify, when I convert the
spreadsheet into SQL commands and a SQL
database, I could use text.
And so that's probably a good thing.
What about zip codes, right?
Zip codes, at least if we do the
first five digits in the US--
like 02138 to.
Is that a number or is that text?
AUDIENCE: Text.
DAVID MALAN: Text?
Why?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: I'm sorry?
Say again?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah,
it's more of a category
than it is a quantity, certainly.
Like I don't have zero, one,
two, three, eight of things.
That is actually just meant
to be a unique symbol.
And in fact, as a side effect of the
spreadsheet trying to be helpful, here
is an actual bug, or
reason to store it as text.
I typed in 02138, which is
Cambridge, Massachusetts,
one of its largest zip codes.
And unfortunately, Google
just decided, you don't really
need that leading zero, do
you, and it got rid of it.
And so this is because, at least in
Google Spreadsheets, my data here,
if I go under Format, it's
being stored automatically.
Google, for better or for
worse-- often for worse--
is inferring that, if it looks like a
number, it is a number, therefore let's
throw away the leading zeros,
which humans don't need.
But if I change it to plain text and
now do 02138, now it kind of sticks.
And another sort of
true story, years ago,
I used to use Microsoft
Outlook for my email.
And then eventually,
I switched to Gmail.
And before I did that, I
wanted to copy my contacts,
like my address book
from Outlook into Gmail.
And so Outlook actually
has a feature where
you can export a big CSV,
literally, from Outlook.
And that contains columns of, like,
all your friends' names and numbers
and addresses and zip codes.
And I foolishly didn't
realize that I probably
shouldn't open the file
first in Excel to look at it,
probably instinctively hit Command
S or Control S just to save it,
because that's like a habit.
As soon as I did that,
Excel presumptuously
did a Google just did, and
dropped all those leading zeros.
And to this day, like
10 years later, I'm
still finding friends whose addresses
are Cambridge, Massachusetts
2138 for that very reason.
So data formats matter.
And we actually have a number of
decisions to make, and moreover,
if we want this database to be
highly performing-- that is, quick--
we actually have a few
other design decisions.
And so let's take our five-minute
break here, and when we come back,
we'll actually wrestle with how can
you store the data most efficiently so
that your web applications
are super fast.
So we are back.
And let's see what problems now arise
besides the most immediate, which
was the phone number.
So let's consider that these aren't
necessarily students registering
for [INAUDIBLE],, and so
therefore they don't just
have dorms and so forth,
but maybe these are actually
like customers in a database,
Amazon customers or the like.
And so people are indeed going
to have names, we'll say.
And people are going to
have addresses, address.
And people will have phone
numbers still, email, and maybe
some other identifiers, as well.
So when it comes to
storing actual data here--
and just for clarity, these will
be my column headings now, so
special first column--
so what's my name here
going to be, David Malan?
Should it be David?
Like, how do you actually think
about something as trivial as this,
and what are some of the
upsides and downsides?
Like, which should it be?
AUDIENCE: David Malan.
DAVID MALAN: David Malan, OK.
So David Malan is what we store.
OK?
But now, later on, I
realize I'd really like
to send customized
emails to my customers,
and it feels kind of lame and informal
if I say dear David Malan, where
clearly it's not very intimate.
I'd like it to say, dear David comma.
So how do you address that?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, so maybe we should
store first and last names separated.
So to do that, maybe I'll just
kind of redo this, and actually
call this First, and
then call this Last.
And so now, I can keep
my two columns separated.
Other thoughts?
That's pretty good.
Or--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Sorry?
DAVID MALAN: Oh, so we have
like the greeting, as well,
which you might be asked by a
dropdown or a text box, too.
So maybe we need that, as well.
So technically, I should probably
move this over like this.
And this will be like the
greeting, and maybe this
will be Mr. or some
number of other symbols.
So we might have to
deal with that, as well.
What about address?
Let's move on to that, because
honestly, with most of these questions,
there's not necessarily a best answer.
There might be some best
practices, but even then you're
going to hit corner cases.
For instance now, anytime I do want
the user's first name and last name,
I'm gonna have to concatenate
them together, which is fine.
It's not a big deal in Python.
It was a bigger deal in C.
So there's these tradeoffs.
Like, I just have to now do
that, or write more code later.
What about the address?
So it might be 33 Oxford Street, the CS
building in Cambridge, Massachusetts,
02138 USA.
Let me even make more
room for all of this.
Good?
Bad?
Why?
Let's go here.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Sorry?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] separate the
data [INAUDIBLE] zip code [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Well you say need to
separate the data into street and city
and country and zip
code and state, but why?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] right now
to sort people by [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Yeah,
that's a great example.
So if everything has just kind
of been this long string, which
we humans and the postmaster
general in the US can understand,
and computers can parse, it's not that
easy to just glean what we care about
from that whole long string.
Like, we're gonna have to
use some kind of heuristics,
we're gonna have to look for all
numbers to get the zip codes.
And I can, as you say, not sort
everyone who's in Massachusetts,
or everyone who's in 02138, because
like it's not a separate field.
And so even mechanically
in Google Spreadsheets,
I can't sort by anything
other than 33 Oxford Street.
And I probably don't
really care to sort people
by their street addresses, which
really have no notion of ordering
that's interesting.
So we probably want to split this up.
So maybe this is actually Street,
and maybe this is actually--
let me shrink this to make
a little more room now--
maybe this is City, maybe this
is State, maybe this is Zip,
maybe this is now Country.
And then over here, we have
Email and Phone and so forth.
And so now, I could do 33 Oxford Street.
And then I could do Cambridge, Mass,
02138, USA, malan@harvard.edu, 6174495.
See, this is why you shouldn't allow
user input in different formats.
495, 5000 and so forth.
OK, so suppose we do that.
But you know, Rob has an office
in the CS building, as well.
And so he's actually Mr. Rob Bowden.
So now he and I are both there.
And oops, we didn't fix this, so
technically let's go back here.
02138.
And now it's like rob@cs.harvard.edu.
And maybe we share the
same office number.
And there are certainly, like, dozens
of other people in the CS building,
if not a couple of hundred.
So this is actually
yielding another problem.
At least if I keep typing, I'm going
to dislike this for some other reason.
What's also bad about this?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] the office room.
DAVID MALAN: The office room, yeah.
So we didn't specify the
room in the building.
So we're missing data all together.
What else really rears
its head over time?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: It's very redundant.
DAVID MALAN: What is redundant?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
wasted space [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Which information
is redundant, then?
AUDIENCE: The street [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, there's a lot of--
I mean, literally I copied and
pasted, which in coding in general
should kind of be a bad
sign or a bad habit,
certainly if you do it
more than just once.
And so Cambridge is identical,
Massachusetts is identical,
zip code is identical.
And even though this is
gonna be a small white lie,
it's probably the case that every zip
code actually maps to a unique city.
So I don't-- if I know 02138, do I
really need to store Cambridge, Mass,
Cambridge, Mass, Cambridge,
Mass for everyone?
No, it's probably all the same.
So I should be able to
delete some of this data.
And this kind of messiness is a
problem that databases can now solve.
You could do this in Excel and in
Google Spreadsheets and so forth.
You can quote unquote normalize your
data by factoring out commonalities.
But to do so, the most
common way, then, is
to start assigning unique
identifiers to things.
So for instance, if I want to go in
here-- let me give myself a new column,
call it ID.
And I'm just going to be user one,
Rob will be user two, and then three
and four and so forth.
We're just gonna use an int to
keep it simple and efficient,
because now it's only like
32 bits, or maybe 64 bits,
no matter how long the humans' names
and street names and so forth are.
Let me just fix the border so
that everything looks uniform.
So now I've done this.
And you know what, if
you've never noticed,
like Excel and Numbers
and Google support
multiple sheets in a spreadsheet.
So just for good measure, let me
actually rename this to Customers.
And you know what?
I'm gonna go ahead in
Google Spreadsheets,
give myself another one called Cities.
And then here, I'm gonna
do something like this.
I'm gonna store over here maybe
a let's say city and state.
And actually, you know
what, because cities I'm
gonna claim for the moment are
uniquely identified by their zip codes,
let's just put zip code there.
And then in this spreadsheet, let's do--
preemptively this time-- plain text--
02138 shall be Cambridge, Massachusetts.
And now, back in my
customers database, which
of these columns, A through I or
so, do I actually not need anymore?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I don't need this.
I don't need this.
I probably still need zip.
So let me just go ahead
and delete these and start
to assuage your concern, which
was this redundancy of data.
Now, I can do a little better, but now
at least I'm storing zip code only.
And actually, this is
getting a little lazy.
Let me get rid of country, as well,
and just put this in here, as well,
for generalizing zip code
to be postal code now, say.
And this shall be USA.
So now my Customers table
has a lot less redundancy.
So clear upside is that it
just takes up less space,
and less space means less money,
and just more room for other things.
So that's surely good.
But it probably means too it's
easier to update the data, right?
If someone-- if Cambridge
for whatever reason
changes its name back to Newtown,
as it apparently once was,
we just change it in one place, not for
every resident in the Customers table,
and so forth.
So this is just a good principle, right?
Anytime in coding we've done something
again and again, or in CSS even,
like we've tried to factor it out.
In HTML, we factored it out
with templates or with functions
or with other techniques.
So this normalization process
feels like a good thing.
But you know what?
02138, we can do a little
better, because that's a string.
We could just store this as a number.
So you know what I'm actually gonna do?
I'm gonna also have in this
spreadsheet a column called
ID whose value for this city is gonna
be one, and then for subsequent cities
it's just gonna an arbitrary number
that's just increasing and unique.
And so now what I can actually do here
is I don't strictly need to store even
02138 dash whatever whatever,
I can just store the ID.
And I'm gonna go ahead and call that
zip ID, just to make super clear to me
that now this is just a number.
And so by starting to assign arbitrary
but consistent unique integers to all
of our data, you can kind of
relate them back to one another
by looking up one value in the other.
So for instance, if you're
looking at this table as a human
and you see that, oh, David
and Rob live in zip ID 1,
you do have to ask a follow-up question,
which is, well, what is zip ID 1?
You can only answer that by looking
at the Cities table, checking it,
and being like, oh, Rob and David
both live in Cambridge, Massachusetts,
02138, USA.
So it's added a step, but
it's also massively shrunk
the amount of data we need, assuming
there's more people in the world
than just the two of
us, and there's millions
of users or thousands of users,
or just otherwise context
where you have lots and lots of data.
And in fact, as an example of this, what
we put together on the course's website
is a Google spreadsheet that
has a whole bunch of sheets.
This is based on a freely
available open source
database that looks like
real data, but it's mostly
taken from one guy's iTunes account and
then made up names and company names
and so forth.
And you'll see that this is actually
a database for like a digital music
store, a la iTunes or Google
Play or Spotify or whatever.
And so there's different entities
in the world of digital music.
You have album names,
you have artist names,
you have customers who might buy those
albums and listen to those artists.
You have employees at the
company who is selling the music.
You have genres for those songs.
Because this is actually a very
slippery slope whereby, over time,
you're gonna have lots
and lots of data that
ideally would be in multiple places
at once, but that's just bad design.
Keeping it factored out is ideal.
So if we glance at this album
title, or rather album tab,
here are all of the albums that
this digital music store sells.
Here are the unique
IDs, album ID, that have
been assigned to those albums,
arbitrarily but for permanently.
And then here are the artists
who published those albums.
So the only way to
know the artist's name
is-- at least in Google,
I'm gonna actually have
to scroll over to my
Artists tab and, OK,
here are the artists and their numbers.
Meanwhile, all of these albums later--
or songs are associated with genres.
So here's all the genres and the IDs
associated therewith, and so forth.
So you're welcome to poke
around this kind of data later.
Here's even data involving birth
dates, so dates and times and so forth.
Here are invoices, like the
addresses and the cities
of people who bought this music,
supposedly, in the sample database.
But honestly, this is very,
very, very quickly becoming
really really annoying, right?
Because if you the human just
so much want to know, OK,
who produced Restless and Wild, artist
two, who the heck was artist two?
This is not good for humans.
But this is good for computers.
We just need a language with which to
reconstruct what we want and query for
and change what we want.
And that is the kind of thing
that SQL is going to do for us.
So let me change to another
tab here in CS50 IDE.
Let me find the right tab here.
So if I go back to CS50 IDE, let me
introduce a tool called phpLiteAdmin.
Name doesn't really matter, but this
is a tool that comes with the IDE--
and we downloaded it for free off the
web and just installed it for you--
that allows us to do this.
I have among today's distribution
code a file called lecture.db.
.db just means it's a database.
It could be another
file extension, as well,
but this is one of the standard ones.
And notice that-- let me close the
console-- if I double-click this,
this is going to open a special
tab in the IDE called phpLiteAdmin.
What I am now seeing is
the content of lecture.db.
Lecture.db is a binary
file, zeros and ones,
that represents a SQLite database
that I made before class.
So I essentially downloaded all this
data, I made a few changes to it,
and then saved it in a
file called lecture.db.
phpLiteAdmin, this GUI
here in the tab, is just
a way of visualizing for us
humans what's in this database.
And you can see there's a bunch of
tables, I think 11 different tables,
that I named identically
to the Google spreadsheet.
So this is the SQLite equivalent
of the Google spreadsheet.
But notice just from the links alone--
not that this is a very good design--
the overwhelming amount of
functionality that I now get.
I have the ability apparently already
to browse the data, search the data,
insert, export the data,
empty the data, and so forth
that we just get from a database.
And we'll see how to do
that in just a moment.
If I go ahead and click
on Album, I'm gonna
see the same data as before
within this graphical tool,
but again I just have
some handy functionality.
I have the ability to edit each
of these albums, delete them.
But I can also see the artist ID.
Now, this isn't all that useful,
but let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and go to the SQL tab.
And this is where this
tool is actually handy.
phpLiteAdmin is not something
you put on your resume.
This is just like a tool we will
use to help visualize what's inside
of our database, and to try
out queries before we actually
write them into code.
I recall from before that one of the
operations that SQL supports is Select.
So let me try that,
select star from album.
And these are the key words from SQL.
This is the name of my table.
I could quote it, but it's
not strictly necessary to,
so I'm not gonna bother here.
And if I go ahead now
and zoom out-- whoops--
and click Go, this is
going to select for me
all of the albums in the album table.
Now, this is not all that interesting,
because just a moment ago I
just clicked on the word album and
I showed you all of the albums.
But suppose I don't
care about the album ID.
I don't care about the
artist ID at the moment.
Well, let me go to SQL tab again
and do select star from album.
But instead of star, which
was the wildcard, what might
I want to select instead?
Just the name of the album?
So let me do that, select--
oh sorry, it was called
title, title from album.
Click Go.
And now I get back a set of rows,
a result set, as it's called,
of just the titles.
Now again, I'm not programming,
I'm not using this data.
But this is the language, the way I
can express myself in the SQL language
to get back only the data I care about.
And you know what?
Let me go ahead and do this now.
And this is where it gets more powerful.
If I go back to selecting all
the data, there's the artist ID.
How do I get the artist ID?
Well let me go to Artist, and
there's that same data, artist ID
and all of the names.
But here's where SQL gets powerful.
I can now take one table,
one of whose columns
is these numbers, take another
table, one of whose columns
is these numbers, as well, and
I can kind of join them cleverly
by lining up the numbers
that are identical in both.
The syntax is a little funky
at first, but let's try this.
Select star from album join artist.
I want to join the two.
But now I have to tell the
database what two columns to join.
It just looks like numbers, but
I have to tell the database which
columns should line up.
So artist on album dot artist
ID equals artist dot artist ID.
So this is just a predicate
or a condition at the end,
but you can kind of read it intuitively.
Select everything from the result
of joining album and artist,
provided you join them
on album dot artist
ID, which is the artist ID column
in the album table on the artist ID
column in the artist table.
So that's kind of doing
this digital equivalent.
And so now if I go ahead
and click Go, amazing.
Like, now I get back all
of the data reconstructed
in a way that's useful, because
now every row contains the album
ID and the artist ID, but
more importantly the title
of the song and the name of the artist.
And I now have the ability to query for
the data I want without inefficiently
storing all of this together.
And I can actually store a join
on yet more tables in here, too.
You'll notice that playlist, for
instance, is one of the tables in here,
because this digital music store
supports the ability to make playlists.
And here we have playlist IDs
which map to playlist names.
But how do you associate
songs with a playlist?
Well, if a playlist just
has a name and an ID,
you need some way of associating songs
with a playlist by way of these IDs.
So we actually need kind of a many
to many relationship, so to speak.
And that's what a
database person would say.
If you want multiple
people, playlists, to all
be able to have different songs
but maybe overlapping songs,
so that you can't dedicate
one song to one person,
you want a many to many relationship.
And so if we look at Playlist
Track, notice this column is crazy.
This column-- or rather this table--
has just playlist ID, track
ID, whereby track ID maps
to one of the rows in the track table,
playlist ID maps to one of the rows
in the playlist table.
And by using this table and
joining with multiple tables,
we can map playlist, which is
just names of playlists and IDs,
to tracks, which is names
of songs on certain albums.
And with the right join
commands, I can actually
reconstruct all of the data I
care about, and then in one breath
get all of the data back
and let the database figure
out how to find all of those
people and all of those songs
and all of those playlists efficiently.
A CSV, you would have to read
every darn file top to bottom
and then figure it all out yourself.
But there are some key
design decisions to be made.
I mentioned earlier not just these
data types that SQL supports,
but also the constraints pictured here.
So these are a few new terms
that we now need as ingredients
to designing a good database.
And we've seen one of
these before, Primary Key.
It turns out that, anytime
in one of these tables
we have defined for ourselves an
arbitrary but a unique number,
generally in the left-hand column,
just by convention, called ID or called
Artist ID or Album ID,
whatever you call it,
that we've declared
typically as a primary key.
This is a way of telling the database,
when you design the database,
give me a table with an ID column
that is meant to be the primary key.
That is, database, I promise to you
that this column will always be unique.
Therefore, database,
use this in the future.
Anytime you want to do
something efficient,
rely on that column as
uniquely identifying rows.
Don't use albums or
artist names and titles,
which can be longer and non-unique.
Instead, use that, as well.
But there's other fields that you
might want to flag as being unique,
but not your primary key, the
number that uniquely identifies.
Like in the world of customers, which
field that we played with a moment ago
might you arguably want to make unique?
And this was our own little
database here of customers.
Which are the candidates
for unique values here?
In back?
No, here.
AUDIENCE: Phone.
DAVID MALAN: No.
Phone, phone could be unique, certainly
in the world of mobile phones.
But some people still have landlines.
That might get a little messy.
So maybe, maybe not.
What else?
AUDIENCE: Names?
DAVID MALAN: Names, maybe.
But if you Google
yourself, odds are there's
many people in the world
with your same name.
And you don't want to have one of you
only buying things from the store.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: What's that?
DAVID MALAN: Email probably more likely.
Now, we can probably think
of some family members
even who are maybe sharing
an email address at home,
which complicates even that scenario.
But maybe.
If you do at least want to mandate
that email addresses be the same--
I'd probably go with
email over name, which
is gonna collide with multiple people--
then maybe we could specify yes,
email address for our customers
must be unique, because maybe
they're using it to log in.
Right?
If you're using email as
a login name, it better
be unique so that there can't be
two people with different passwords
but the same username or email address.
But an email address is kind of long.
Malan@harvard.edu, rob@cs.harvard.
Like, that's more bytes than an integer.
So long story short, it
might make good sense
to uniquely identify your
users at the end of the day
with just an ID, a numeric
ID, the primary key.
But one of the features you get from a
database is you can tell the database,
hey database, make this
other column also unique,
and make sure that I or my colleagues
can never accidentally insert data
into the database that is duplicated.
The database will defend
against that for you.
You don't need ifs and
else ifs in your own code,
you can let the database
do that for you.
Index, meanwhile, is really powerful.
You can specify by the
keyword index, hey database,
this column is important to me.
I am going to want to do
searches on this column.
I am gonna want to look
up people by this column.
Therefore, please go ahead
and index it by using
your sort of secret sauce using fancy
data structures and solid algorithms
to actually find data efficiently.
And here again is where we're
standing on the shoulders of others.
Other computer scientists have figured
out really good algorithms and data
structures, usually
involving trees, which
we did discuss a few weeks back,
that allow you to find data generally
in logarithmic time, not linear time.
And so simply by using
this keyword index,
we'll see you can tell the database
use those years of knowledge
to actually find data for
little old me more quickly.
Not null.
You can specify don't let
null end up in this column.
I must have a user's name.
I must have their phone number.
It cannot be blank.
Foreign key is even more fancy,
but we've seen it already, in fact.
When we looked in just these examples
here, rather for the songs database,
notice that in Album we
had two types of IDs.
We had album ID in the Album
table associated with titles,
and then each of these albums
was associated with an artist ID.
And we've got two
keywords here to apply.
I claim that this is the
primary key for this table
because it just uniquely
identifies the albums.
Why is that the primary?
Well, the table itself, the
spreadsheet is called Album.
This is the unique ID that's primarily
responsible for identifying rows.
That key over there is not primary,
because there can only be one,
so it's called a foreign key.
But it's foreign in what sense?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Say it again?
DAVID MALAN: To the album.
It's related to the album
in that it's the artist,
but it's foreign in what way?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: It's in a different
file in a different table.
So it is a primary key
in another table, which
is what makes it foreign if we
mention it in this table, right?
Strictly speaking, this column
doesn't need to be here.
I could just go ahead
and forget about all
of the values in this
highlighted column.
But once I add it, that allows me to
link it primarily to another table,
because in this context it's
just called foreign keys.
So that's it for the vocabulary there.
So what does this actually all mean?
Let me go ahead now
into phpLiteAdmin, which
is again just our web-based
tool for manipulating data.
And let me go ahead
actually and do this.
Let me go ahead and close
this version of phpLiteAdmin.
Let me go back over to my file browser.
And let me open up a terminal
window for just a moment.
And I'm actually gonna
go ahead and do this.
If I want to create a new file in
Linux, the operating system we're using,
you can actually do this pretty
easily by just touching the file,
even if it doesn't exist.
So touch customers.db, and now
notice at left customers.db exists.
It's just an empty file.
I can now, wonderfully, double-click
that and begin interacting with it
as though it's a database.
There's no zeros and ones in it
yet until I start manipulating it,
and that's why it says
no tables in database.
It's just an empty file.
So let's create an actual table in
this database akin to what I was doing
in Excel, or in Google Spreadsheets.
So here is where in
this user interface I
can create a new table
on database Customers.
So let me go ahead and call this my
Users table, because they-- well,
we're just gonna call it--
yeah, Users is good.
And number of fields, let's
just do four this time.
And now I'm gonna go ahead and click Go.
And this is again what
you get from phpLiteAdmin.
It's just a nice,
user-friendly interface
for, like, answering questions.
So what columns do I want in this table?
Well, the first one is going
to be the customer's name,
or maybe it should be first name, so
like first underscore name or F Name
or whatever you want to call it.
I'll just call it First.
What should the data type be?
AUDIENCE: Text.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, text.
And then last name should be text.
And actually, I'm
getting ahead of myself.
I don't want to uniquely
identify users by their names.
What did we decide?
AUDIENCE: ID.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, ID.
So just to be kind of tidy,
I'm gonna put it first.
It doesn't strictly matter,
but it's just kind of the norm.
So I could call this
ID, as would be a norm.
You could call it user ID,
which might be another norm,
so long as you're consistent
is what's important.
This should be not text but integer.
And notice these other features.
I can tell the database
this is my primary key.
And now no other field
should be primary.
I can tell the database, you know what,
you deal with auto incrementing this.
I don't want to keep track
of who is what number.
The database can assign
an auto-incremented ID,
so one becomes two
becomes three over time.
Not null is a given, because if it's
a primary key it can't be blank.
And then this is irrelevant here,
but you can give default values.
So for instance, if,
for whatever reason,
people want to remain anonymous
in their name, we could say,
well, the default name for
everyone in my database
will be Bob, or something like that.
But that is kind of silly, as well.
We probably want to say that there is
no default value, but rather first name
and last name must not be null so that
the users must cooperate and provide us
with a value.
As for the last one here, I don't
know, we'll just use email for now.
We'll make that text.
And it turns out you can't
specify in the database
that an email address must
have something at something.
We're gonna have to do that
if we ever want in code.
But I can at least make it not null.
Now notice what happens.
Even though this is a GUI,
graphical user interface,
when I click Create now, I'm told
this-- table Users has been created.
But what's nice about phpLiteAdmin,
which is largely why we use it,
is it's a good teaching tool, too.
This is what phpLiteAdmin just
executed in order to create this table.
So it's a way of kind of learning
SQL as you go by just click, click,
clicking in a user-friendly way,
and then seeing immediately feedback
as to what command you could
have just typed manually
in order to create that same table.
And it's wrapping because it's a little
long, and it's not nicely indented.
But here, we have
something very reminiscent
of what I put on the board earlier.
We have an ID field that's an
integer, that's a primary key.
And by the way, it should
also be auto-incremented.
That's a new feature.
But it cannot be null.
Over here, first name is
text, must not be null.
Last is-- should not be an integer.
That's a screw-up.
So I should have made that text,
so that's flawed at the moment.
And then email all the way
over here is text, not null.
So what does this actually mean?
Well, let me show you one other way
before we use this in actual code
as to how else I could be
interacting with this database.
If I open up a terminal and I go
ahead and type this now, SQLite
3, which is the third
version of the program,
I'm gonna make this my alternative
database and hit Enter.
This is not as user-friendly.
Like, I have to know what I type, or it
seems I can type Help to get some help.
And these are all of the commands
that I can type at the command line.
It's not all that user-friendly.
But I do know this.
Once I know SQL, I can just interact
with this with SQL commands.
And I'm gonna go ahead and fix
this in my alternative database.
I did not mean to say integer,
so let me make that text.
I'm gonna put a semicolon at the
end, which is typically needed,
though it's not always needed.
So let me go ahead and hit Enter now.
Nothing seems to happen.
But in SQLite, if I type Schema,
schema is like my database design.
.schema means show me my database.
And any command that starts
with a dot is SQLite specific.
It is not SQL, it's now part of the
language, it's just a local command.
Oh, that's kind of cool.
It just spits back out what
it is my tables look like.
I can see this in another way.
Let me go ahead and close
this for just a moment.
And notice that, in today's
files on the website,
I have lecture.db, which was the music
database that we opened up earlier.
Let me look at that.
SQLite 2, lecture.db.
Let me do .schema.
Oh.
That is all of the data inside of this
database redisplayed to me as text.
So I can kind of back it up
if I want, or do other things.
But let's just skim it
for something interesting.
Let me go to the top.
And here we have, nicely
formatted, these are the commands
that the people who wrote this database
online from whom we downloaded it
essentially made.
Create Table, Album.
The square brackets are optional, but
they just are alternatives to quotes.
One of the fields will be called
Album ID, Title, Artist ID.
We've seen those things before.
One is an integer, one is
text, another is integer.
And then we'd see these features
here, which we didn't see earlier.
And I'm gonna wave my
hand at them for now.
But there is a way to tell the database
that there is indeed a foreign key.
So you can say, in this table, there's
a number that refers to another table,
and you can let the database
make sure that you can never
add an artist ID that doesn't
map to an actual artist.
So you can't just insert
artist number one, two, three
if artist number one, two,
three doesn't even exist.
So again, another feature
you get from the database.
And for PSET 7 we're just gonna
scratch the surface of some of these.
But again, this is one of the reasons
that you sort of graduate from text
files and you graduate from [INAUDIBLE]
and start using [? full-pledged ?]
database software like SQLite
or Oracle or other such tools.
So let me pause to see if there's any
questions before we dive into Python.
All right, so let's now
actually use this in code.
The value of seeing, hopefully,
SQLite 3 and in seeing phpLiteAdmin
is just so that you have tools with
which you can create your databases
and actually see what's
inside of them without having
to write code to do both, which just
makes it very hard and annoying to get
started.
So phpLiteAdmin is what you'll
use for problem set seven.
And we'll end with a
look at that in a bit.
But it's just a way of
administering your database.
It's not actually the
intellectually juicy part.
For that, we're gonna need
some actual Python code.
So for that, let me go ahead
and open up my console again.
Let me get some tabs open here.
And let me go into let's say
Lecture 0 folder from today.
And this is not online
now, but soon will be.
Let me open up application.py
and see what this app is.
Super simple.
This is just copy paste pretty
much from past examples.
And notice that it has one route,
slash, that's gonna render index.html.
And then what is that template?
Well, index.html is one of two files.
My layout is big generic
HTML structure of the page.
Index.html looks like this.
It's a big to-do.
So let's actually do something
with this program as follows.
But first, let's take a stepping stone.
Let me go into New File,
save this as lecture.py.
It's just a local script, nothing
to do with web programming just yet.
And let me go ahead and do this.
First, for those in the room who've
never seen Python before today,
python lecture.py--
that is a program written in Python.
If you're underwhelmed, that's
deliberate at this point.
It's a one-line program.
But now we can do something
so much more powerful.
Let me go ahead and essentially do this.
In pseudo code, query
database for all albums.
Whoops, albums.
For each album in database,
print title of album.
Like, suppose this is now
the program we want to write.
How do I do this?
Well, in Python, I'm gonna
go ahead and do this.
From CS50, import CS50
SQL library, which
will be introduced again in PSET 7.
And it just makes SQL a
little easier to get into.
And for your final projects, you're
welcome to drop use of the library
all together.
It's just training wheels.
And I'm gonna do this.
DB for database, but I could
call that anything I want,
is going to get a SQL database whose
file is of type SQLite colon slash
slash slash just because dot DB.
So long story short, this
one line of code just says,
hey Python, open a SQLite
database called lecture.db
that's in the same directory.
That's all.
So after that, I have a
Python variable called DB.
And this is a variable that allows
me to talk to the database in code.
And this is the missing piece.
So far the only way we've interacted
with lecture.db thus far--
and lecture.db, again,
is the musical database--
is by using phpLiteAdmin, which
is just this administrative GUI,
or SQLite 3, which is the
command line version of the same.
We haven't actually done anything
intellectually interesting by querying
for data in a programmatic way.
I've done it all very manually.
But not now.
Now let me go ahead and do this.
Let me say, go ahead and store
in a variable called Rows.
All of the rows in the table
that are the result of executing,
select star from album.
So I'm writing Python code, but inside
of my Python code I have a string,
and that string has SQL in it.
So what do I now want to
implement this pseudo code?
So that's what I've just done.
That's my comment.
Now I want to iterate over
each album in the database.
How can I do this?
Well, let me go ahead and do that.
So for each album in database,
so for row in rows, old syntax
by now, what do I want to do?
I want to just go ahead
and print out row--
what were the columns in my album table?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it was album ID and?
DAVID MALAN: I think it
was title in the album one.
So I'm gonna do this.
Quote unquote-- I think
it was called title.
We shall see if I'm
remembering correctly.
And now let me just put my
comment over here, as well.
So now we have a pretty short
program that just executes a query,
and it turns out-- oops, I indented
excessively-- this variable Rows
contains what's called a result set.
It is a list, an array, a list of all
of the rows that match that query,
which hopefully is all of them.
Then this is just Python
from a week or two ago
for each of the row in that Rows
list, print out that row's title.
Now what is this exactly?
You can think of this as a
hash table, or a dictionary.
Row is one of the rows.
It has a bunch of columns.
And the syntax in Python for
indexing into those columns
is just square bracket notation.
This is a dict, or a
dictionary object in Python.
OK.
So let's cross my fingers
because I'm not sure
if I named everything correctly here
and do Python of lecture.py, enter.
Whew.
It worked.
So outputted here is every
title from the database.
So let me go ahead and just pick one.
For instance, a soprano inspired.
And just do another proof of concept.
You know what?
I don't want to get all of them.
I want to go ahead and
get where title equals.
And now I will use
quotes to distinguish it.
So how many rows should
this query now return?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Hopefully just one.
So let's see.
Let me go ahead and
rerun it, lecture.py.
And very nice.
And now two things
printed, though, which
we didn't see before because there
was a lot of output, but it was there.
It turns out that the CS50 library, to
help you out, especially with problem
set seven, always prints out this
debugging information that you
can technically disable.
It's not part of your program,
just kind of sent in addition.
This shows you exactly
what query was executed,
which is gonna be helpful because,
when you start using web programming,
as we're about to, as well, you can
then see in your terminal window
what your web app is actually
doing to make sure your
can diagnose any bugs in your code.
But we can be fancier than this.
Remember for problem set six,
or soon see in problem set six,
that if you import sys for a Python
program, this gives us access to what,
among other things?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah,
command line arguments.
So what if I do this, where
title equals something.
I want that to come
from the command line.
So how can I go about doing this?
Well, turns out there's
one other piece of syntax
that you need to know
from the CS50 library.
The Execute method supports what
are called name placeholders, where
you can essentially say this,
colon t, or colon title,
or colon whatever you want.
It's just a placeholder.
And I'm just gonna call it t for title.
And what you can then do is this.
You can specify that
the value of t shall be,
for instance, sys.argv
bracket 1, which will
be the first word that the human
typed in at the command line.
And what is Python gonna do?
It's gonna plug this into colon t.
That's all.
It's just a placeholder.
And just as an aside,
we've seen this before.
Let me delete this for just a moment.
As of like two minutes ago, the
way you might have done this
is like this, with a so-called f string
or format string, just plug it in.
This is dangerous, for reasons
we'll see in just a moment.
So I'm gonna actually do this
instead, the colon approach,
and let the CS50 library actually
scrub or sanitize my data so
that the user can't accidentally trick
me into, like, deleting all of my data.
So now let me go ahead and do this.
Python of lecture.py-- whoops.
Python of lecture.py.
And now let me go ahead and type
in that same title, which was--
what was it, a soprano?
AUDIENCE: Soprano inspired.
DAVID MALAN: A soprano inspired?
Inspired?
And now I'm using quotes.
Why?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's one phrase.
I want it all in argv1.
I don't want it partly
in argv1 and 2 and 3.
It's just gonna be messy.
Enter.
Whew.
It actually worked.
So now I've written
an interactive program
that takes user input at the command
line, plugs it into the SQL string,
and actually allows me to get
the data that I care about.
Now, why did I do this?
As a quick aside, if you do it this
way, which would have been our technique
as of, again, like minutes ago,
before seeing this, this technique--
and actually, now I need to
quote it inside the SQL string,
the library otherwise does that for me--
this is actually very dangerous.
This is violating a
principle that henceforth
you should be very mindful of.
Why might this be dangerous,
just plugging in the command line
argument to that string?
AUDIENCE: I could put malicious quotes,
or I could put, like, [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
You can plug in sort of
code that you didn't intend.
So let me go back down here.
What if a really malicious
user didn't just type
in the beautiful name of
a song, but did something
like haha semicolon delete from album
to try to delete your whole database.
This isn't perfectly right.
This won't actually execute properly.
Haha is not a keyword.
But the semicolon means that's it
for this query, the delete from album
is a valid query that we
saw before, and this is
what's called a SQL injection attack.
And in fact, this is
very common even today,
because one of the features you're
getting from the CS50 library
is sanitization or
scrubbing of the user input.
And the takeaway for today
is that you should never
henceforth trust the user's
input ever, even if it's you.
Get into the habit now of
distrusting even yourself,
lest you somehow inject data into
your database that shouldn't be there.
Let me demonstrate this as follows.
So if you're logging in, for instance,
to a Yale University website,
your login form looks like this.
Or at Harvard University, it looks
like this, Harvard [? key. ?]
Now I'm gonna g sort of reveal
what a password prompt actually
looks like without showing the
bullets, which is the norm,
but in the context of
the web, if a user were
to type in seemingly dangerous
instructions, maybe this could happen.
So suppose that my name is
me@exampleprovider.com or whatever,
and my password is this funky single
quote or quote unquote one equals one.
Like, this is not a complete thought.
But notice it's miss-- it ends a
quote here, and it lacks one here.
So it's kind of like
this partial thought,
because if an adversary
out there on the internet
is trying to hack into a Harvard
or a Yale system or the like,
he or she might think what if someone
at Harvard or Yale wasn't so bright
and did not sanitize users' input,
and just trusted whatever it is.
Maybe I, the malicious
adversary, can try
to finish their thought, so
to speak, in a malicious way.
And what does this mean?
Well, suppose that the code that
someone at Harvard or Yale had written
looks like this.
Give me a user name variable
and a password variable
using syntax that we
started seeing last week,
and you'll see more of
in problem set seven.
This just says get me whatever the
user passed into the web application,
as opposed to from the command line.
And then suppose that the
Harvard or Yale staffer actually
executed select star from users where
username equals this f string syntax.
What's interesting here
is that they are correctly
quoting whatever the string is supposed
to be for both username and password.
But remember what the user was
about to type in a moment ago.
If I kind of close one quote
and then like leave one open,
I can kind of inject
arbitrary statements in here.
And so what a SQL injection
attack might look like is this.
If I type in exactly those values,
me@exampleemailprovider.com,
and that funky password, notice if you
look past the syntactic weirdness what
really this is saying.
Where password equals
quote unquote, which
is kind of silly, if your password
is blank, or if one equals one.
Now, which of those
statements is obviously true?
One equals one.
And this is arbitrary.
I could've said foo
equals foo or anything.
The point is, I sort of finished
one thought with that single quote.
Then, I typed whatever
I wanted because I'm
presuming a little cleverly,
but also kind of guessing,
because the adversary
can't see this code,
I just have a hunch that, if
I construct the right query,
I can trick the database into returning
any user because one always equals one.
So I'm gonna get back a row which is
probably gonna let me into the system.
So what the end result is is very bad,
unless you sanitize the user's input.
So this other approach
with which I started,
actually using these
colon-based conventions, which
is very similar to percent
[? s ?] in C, but it's
just now SQL-specific,
or SQLite-specific,
this now ensures that
when the user types
in even the most malicious-looking
data, CS50's library, or other libraries
out there in the world that
do the exact same thing,
is gonna make sure that any
dangerous characters like apostrophes
are escaped with backslash.
So long story short, you
don't even have to know
or care what a SQL injection
attack is fundamentally
if you just practice good database
sanitization techniques, which
doesn't sound very cool.
But it's very easy to do so by
using, in our case, the CS50 library,
but in the more general case,
actually using a library like it.
And so this is kind of a fun meme
that kind of goes around the internet,
supposedly like some
actual person's car.
This was meant to do what, do you think?
AUDIENCE: Hide the license plate.
DAVID MALAN: Well, not just
hide the license plate.
This is probably one of those
cities where you actually
have cameras overhead that are using
optical character recognition to bill
the right person for their license
plate, or ticket the right person
for their license plate.
So this person, correctly or
incorrectly, was presuming,
hey, maybe, you know,
the city of Cambridge
has some buggy software that's not
sanitizing its inputs like that.
And before we look at
an actual web example,
I would be remiss if I didn't teach
a generation of aspiring programmers
this comic.
[LAUGHTER]
So henceforth, if you ever
hear about Little Bobby Tables,
this is what CS people
are actually referring to.
So let's actually now use
this in a web context.
So I'm gonna go ahead and do this.
I'm gonna go back to the IDE,
close out the command line program
that I was writing a moment ago.
And let's just fill in this to-do.
Let me go ahead and go back
to application.py, which
doesn't do much of anything just yet.
But I'm gonna go ahead
here and do the following.
I am going to initialize my database.
So this gives SQL of SQLite colon slash
slash lecture.db, so just like before.
And then in my index route, I'm
gonna do something like this,
rows gets db.execute, which is the only
method in there that you need to know.
Select star from album.
And that's gonna get me all of them.
And now I'm gonna pass to
this template all of the rows.
And I'm gonna call it albums, and
I'm gonna pass in all the rows.
And this is a way now of handing
all of those rows and those titles
into my template.
If I now go to my template
where I have this to-do,
I can use some Jinja syntax,
which honestly is not
going to sink in until you
start practicing it some more,
but I do know from experience
it's for album in albums.
Now close brace, and
then endfor is gonna
be how we end this in my Jinja template.
And in here, I'm gonna go
ahead and output each time
the album's quote unquote title,
if I didn't get a syntax error.
And so now, let me go ahead
into my terminal window
and do in my source directory
in my lecture example
flask run to start the web server.
Open up the URL.
Whoa.
So that's kind of a mess.
But it kind of looks like
all of the titles, probably.
Let me clean this up.
And here's where HTML now
becomes really useful.
In HTML, what's the tag for, like,
an unordered list, [INAUDIBLE] list?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, UL
for unordered list.
So let me go ahead and make
an unordered list tag there,
but close it after this loop.
Let me go ahead and
nicely indent everything.
And now inside of the loop,
let me go ahead and output
a list item, recall
from a few weeks back.
And now it still looks super cryptic,
but what is the logic saying?
Within the body block of my page, go
ahead and start an unordered list.
Iterate over each of the
albums, and then output
its title inside of a list item.
So if I go back here and
reload, what should I see?
A whole list of those album titles.
Moreover, I can do a little bit better.
Let me go ahead back now here
and do something like this.
Let me go ahead and say q
equals request.args.get q.
And q is, again, what
Google uses for its queries,
but I could call this anything I want.
Let me now go ahead and
pass in the following.
Where title equals colon q, and
then let me pass in q equals q.
This feels a little silly, but
just think about what it's doing.
I want to substitute for
colon q the actual value of q.
And maybe I can be more explicit here.
If I call this query, what I'm really
doing here is passing that in to there.
So now that I've done
that, what can I do?
This is not a very
fancy web application,
but suppose I want to search only for
what was it, the soprano song before,
soprano inspired.
Actually, let me search
for something simpler.
How about just worlds.
A la hello world.
Let me go to my URL.
And remember, if you
understand HTTP, we can
do question mark q slash question
mark q equals worlds, and enter.
And dammit.
Where title equals worlds q--
where title equals worlds.
Why did you not come out?
request.args.
request.
Stand by real quick.
We were doing so well there.
All right, let me just reload.
Oh actually, what a good time--
none.
OK, none is bad.
What am I doing wrong?
Did I screw up?
OK, hang on.
Stand by.
What a good time to introduce eprint
for just a moment from earlier.
Now let me go ahead and reload
the page to trigger the load.
OK, that's bad.
Dammit.
eprint is not defined from CS50.
Oh.
Oh, so close to--
yes!
OK.
[APPLAUSE]
In fairness, I have no
idea what just happened.
But it worked.
So let's now, with
those inspiring words,
give us a sense of
what it is you're going
to be doing with these ingredients.
We focused a lot today on
SQL and on database design,
but the ultimate goal at hand is
going to be to use these ingredients
and use this new language to
query for real information.
So here is what we call CS50
Finance, AKA problem set seven.
And you'll be given a little
bit of distribution code
that essentially gives you a user
interface similar to this that just
allows users to log in and log out.
But it doesn't allow users to register.
It doesn't allow users to buy or
sell stocks yet, as will be the goal.
CS50 Finance is like building
your own e-trade website
where you can buy and sell stocks.
But it's going to
integrate thanks to code
you write with Yahoo Finance, which
happens to provide essentially a very
lightweight API, application programming
interface, whereby if you ask Yahoo
for the current stock price of a
certain stock ticker, they will respond
and actually give you that answer so
you can integrate it into your website.
So what you'll ultimately
be able to do--
and this is simply the staff solution--
is build a website like this one
here, such that I can go ahead now
and log in to CS50 Finance as a
John Harvard with his password.
I can then see that, by
default, all of your customers,
wonderfully, for a special deal, are
going to get 10,000 virtual dollars.
I can go ahead and get a quote
for a stock, like GOOG is G-O-O-G.
Google as of right now
is just over $1,000.
That's great, because I have $10,000.
So I'm gonna go ahead and buy one share
of GOOG by typing in its stock ticker
symbol and one.
And now I actually have one share of
Alphabet AKA Google plus some remaining
cash.
So all of this and more
you will implement.
Happy to stick around for questions.
That is it for today.
And thank you so much for today's
parents and families for coming.
[APPLAUSE]