[MUSIC PLAYING]
[MUSIC - BIRDY, "KEEPING YOUR HEAD UP"]
MUSIC: Times that I've
seen you lose your way
You're not in control
and you won't be told
All i can do to keep you safe
is hold you close hold you close
'Til you can breathe on your own
Hold tight you're slowly
coming back to life
I'll be keeping your head up
I'll be keeping your head up darling
Let go of all your
haunted dreams tonight
I'll be keeping your head up
I'll be keeping your head up darling
Hold tight you're slowly
coming back to life
I'll be keeping your head up
I'll be keeping your head up darling
Let go of all your
haunted dreams tonight
I'll be keeping your head up
And I won't let you down
[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: This is CS50,
week 11, for the final time.
And it is of course, this weekend,
Harvard-Yale, and in full disclosure,
we actually spent yesterday at Yale
wrapping up the course there as well,
but we did think this was perhaps an
opportunity to make a few changes here
for today's lecture.
Now, now to be fair, we suck.
But we thought we'd use
this as an opportunity
to take a closer look at this problem
that was solved by some of our friends
in New Haven just a few years ago
in honor of this weekend's event.
A closer look then at, if
you will, problem solving,
DAVID AULICINO: We're
headed up to Boston,
checking out the stadium for the prank.
A few years ago, I was
at a math conference,
and I was sitting around the table at
dinner with a few other mathematicians.
And one of them went
to Harvard and started
telling the story of this amazing
prank that was against Harvard.
And at that point, I
felt I had to interrupt,
and said well, actually I can
tell you a lot more about that.
OK?
MIKE KAI: OK.
SPEAKER 1: The idea was
perfected in a dorm room.
MIKE KAI: Came up with
the idea, actually,
to prank them with signs
at the football game.
We threw some ideas out there as
far as what the signs would say.
We eventually settled on "We Suck."
DAVID AULICINO: And my immediate
reaction was no, this will never work.
, However, the problem solver
in me started thinking, well,
maybe we can make this work.
SPEAKER 1: The problem?
They had to infiltrate Harvard
stadium without getting caught,
sneak in 1,800 placards, distribute
them to unsuspecting Harvard fans,
and then convince those
fans to prank themselves.
MIKE KAI: That's great.
We thought about basically
every possible thing
that could go wrong and try to
come up with a solution for it.
DAVID AULICINO: And then you
put two reds on top of it.
SPEAKER 1: They made fake
Harvard IDs and fake backstories,
fake placard designs, and
a 28-member fake pep squad.
AUDIENCE: I can see the shirt.
SPEAKER 1: On November 20th,
2004, the fake Harvard students
smuggled the placards into the game.
AUDIENCE: What do you
think of Yale, sir?
AUDIENCE: They suck.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
AUDIENCE: It's not going to say
something like Yale Sucks, is it?
AUDIENCE: It says Go Harvard!
SPEAKER 1: But then, trouble.
AUDIENCE: What houses are you guys in?
That's not a real house.
AUDIENCE: Ho-fo?
AUDIENCE: You guys aren't
from Harvard, are you?
Because I really think
you guys are from Yale.
DAVID AULICINO: I just showed him the
front of this ID, and all of a sudden
he just ran away, and
he felt so embarrassed.
SPEAKER 1: Having escaped
one confrontation,
they couldn't risk another.
It was time.
MIKE KAI: This just
looks like a total mess.
We have absolutely no idea
if this is going to work.
AUDIENCE: Look at them,
they have the paper.
It's gonna happen.
It's actually gonna happen!
I can't [BLEEP] believe this.
SPEAKER 1: What was once
a prank became a legend.
AUDIENCE: We [BLEEP] did it!
MIKE KAI: And immediately, we started
hearing chants from the other side,
"You Suck."
AUDIENCE: You suck!
You suck!
MIKE KAI: And I think it
was at that point in time
that we knew we had pulled it off.
AUDIENCE: One more
time, come on Harvard!
AUDIENCE: There it goes again!
MIKE KAI: I really think it
didn't matter that Harvard won.
Because of the prank, for a lot
of Yale students and alumni,
we definitely won that year.
DAVID MALAN: Best of luck
to both teams this weekend.
We thought that we would
participate in our own CS50 way.
This game was something written in
scratch some years ago now by one
of your predecessors, and
I thought we would go head
to head here with Yale if we
could, with one volunteer who
is willing to come up and
represent Harvard in this game.
Someone?
Anyone?
Not too many people all at once.
No?
Actually, would you with the Harvard
sweatshirt like to play this game?
Could we get you to come on up?
Are you comfortable?
Yeah, all right, come on up.
This could not be more perfect.
What's your name?
DIANA: Diana.
DAVID MALAN: Diana.
Nice to see you.
Come on up, Diana.
So here, as you see, we're
about to hit the space bar,
and the instructions will
appear on the screen,
if you'd like to play my keyboard here.
And the goal is simply
to move the Harvard crest
to the goal again and again without
getting hit by the other team.
DIANA: OK.
DAVID MALAN: Sound good?
And just arrow keys.
Up, down, left, right.
Surprise.
Let's actually open up the game.
That was a slide.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
There we go.
[MUSIC - MC HAMMER, "U CAN'T TOUCH
THIS"]
MUSIC: You can't touch this
Can't touch this
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
You have your fan.
MUSIC: My music hits me so hard
Makes me say oh my lord
Thank you for blessing
me with a mind to rhyme
DAVID MALAN: Two Yales now.
MUSIC: When you know you're down
A super-dope homeboy from the Oaktown
And I'm known as such
And this is a beat uh, you can't touch
I told you homeboy
Can't touch this
DAVID MALAN: Very nice.
Level five.
MUSIC: Look at my eyes man
Can't touch this
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
MUSIC: Fresh new kicks and pants
You got it like that now
you know you wanna dance
DAVID MALAN: Level six.
MUSIC: Out of your seat
And get a fly girl and catch
this beat while it's rolling
Hold on pump a little bit and let
them know it's going on like that
Like that cold on a
mission so fall on back
Let them know that you're too much
And this is a beat uh, they can't touch
DAVID MALAN: Oh!
MUSIC: Told you, can't touch this
DAVID MALAN: Nice, yes, yes.
Level seven.
MUSIC: Can't touch this
Give me a song or rhythm
Making them sweat that's
what I'm giving them now
They know they're
talking about the Hammer
DAVID MALAN: That's level eight.
MUSIC: Singers are sweating,
so pass them a wipe or tape
To learn what's it gonna take
in the 90's to burn the charts
DAVID MALAN: Oh!
MUSIC: Either work hard
or you might as well quit
DAVID MALAN: Oh, still level eight.
MUSIC: You can't touch this
Break it down
DAVID MALAN: Yes.
Level nine, second-to-last level.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
MUSIC: Stop, Hammer time
DAVID MALAN: Death at five.
MUSIC: It is said if you can't groove
to this then you probably are dead
DAVID MALAN: That's OK.
MUSIC: Run your fingers
through your hair
This is it
For a winner
DAVID MALAN: One level
to go after this, yes.
MUSIC: Slide your rump
Just for a minute let's all do the bump
Yeah, can't touch this
DAVID MALAN: OK.
MUSIC: Look, man
Can't touch this
DAVID MALAN: Yes!
She doesn't want to go
run the [INAUDIBLE]..
MUSIC: Break it down
DAVID MALAN: On level nine.
I didn't do better.
Okay, nice.
Yes, oh!
Oh, don't give up yet!
Yes, yes!
Hang in there.
Let's give it another
one or two more deaths?
Hang in there.
MUSIC: Can't touch this
DAVID MALAN: There we go.
Come on, Diana, come on, yeah!
One more, one more.
MUSIC: Stop, Hammer time
Every time you see me
The Hammer's just so hype
I'm dope on the floor
DAVID MALAN: Hang in there.
MUSIC: Now why would I ever
DAVID MALAN: Come on.
MUSIC: Stop doing this
When others making records that
That just don't hit
I've toured around the world
DAVID MALAN: Try a couple more times.
MUSIC: It's Hammer Go Hammer MC Hammer
DAVID MALAN: What's that?
I think you just-- luck.
MUSIC: Can't touch this
DAVID MALAN: One more life?
Two more lives?
MUSIC: You can't touch this
Yeah
Can't touch this
I told you, can't touch this
DAVID MALAN: Yes, oh!
One more, one more, one more.
MUSIC: We outta here
Can't touch this
DAVID MALAN: Yes!
Yes!
All right a big round
of applause for Diana.
Congrats.
Thank you.
All right, so we will post the
link on the course's web site
if you would like to try
your hand at that as well.
Before we forge ahead though, a
big thanks to CS50 50's whole team.
Suffice it to say, with
office hours and sections
and the problem sets and, soon,
the CS50 hackathon and fair,
we truly could not do
it without all of these
faces here, all of the faces behind
you today, and the whole team online.
So if we could, a big round
of applause for CS50's team.
Allow me to call out a
few folks in particular.
One, these are all of the names of
CS50 50 staff, both here and afar,
helping to make this course possible.
CS50 50's production team, of
course, making it possible for you
to tune in across campus
or across the world,
and then, some folks too that might
be more familiar over the course
of the semester.
CS50'S 50's own Doug Lloyd, who not
only has been the longest-serving staff
member for the past 11 years now, he was
also here on Jeopardy some years ago,
and won.
So that was amazing to watch on TV.
CS50's own Rob Bowden,
or that guy in Thayer
from whom you might have
gotten some help over time,
since he is a proctor there.
And of course, perhaps
the most familiar face
of all, CS50's own Zamaila
from the problem sets.
And then of course, today's
performer, playing out, if you will,
problem set three for us, Brian.
A big thanks to him as well.
And then a special final thanks
to someone particularly special.
CS50's own Maria, who has been with the
course now in some way for four years.
Sadly but excitingly, Maria is about
to go off into the real world, working
as an engineer at Facebook,
but she actually took CS50 here
as a first year years ago, and
then is among the longest-serving
members of the course's head's
team in that she's been with us now
in some form for the past three years.
And in fact we went
through some old footage
and, in fairness, one
of her friends actually
found this, an old video from
her freshman year years ago.
This was Maria like, right here,
volunteering some years ago.
So if we enhance this here, a big
round of applause especially for Maria.
She will be missed,
as of course will you.
This is week 11, and so this is
where we promised we would get to.
And indeed, especially on the
heels of a little quiz that you
might have taken or finished
yesterday on what is ultimately,
what does ultimately
matter in this course
is not so much where you end
up relative to your classmates,
but where you end up relative
to yourself today and next week
and beyond, relative to
where you were in week zero.
So we do hope that you have gotten
an extraordinary amount of time
back now from this class,
but also a huge return
just in terms of the concepts
and the practical skills
we hope you can now bring to
your future studies in CS,
or if you exit CS at this
point to your own domains
and can solve problems
all the more effectively.
And in fact, if you're curious
as to how some of your classmates
have labeled themselves over
time, this is where, in week zero,
you all were with the
majority of the class
describing themselves
as less comfortable.
And if you're still feeling
a little bit that way,
rest assured some 12 weeks later, none
of you are among those less comfortable
anymore.
Everyone has been upgraded
as of today to somewhere
in between or more comfortable.
So do realize, that too
has been a stepping stone.
And in fact now, even if you
are currently a first year,
or we've had high school students in
the past or a junior and a rising senior
realize that the opportunities ahead,
not only to study other courses in CS,
but to teach computer science,
TF-ing or CA-ing for CS50.
Hands down, the most effective way
to learn this kind of material,
and perhaps any other
is to actually teach it,
and that's certainly true for me and
for Maria and Brian and Zamaila and Doug
and Rob, and the whole
of CS50's team here.
I mean in fact, some of them
with CS50's production team
wanted to share with you
an invitation to join us
in some form on campus this
coming fall 2018 online.
In the meantime, we're in
any number of other ways.
If we could dim the lights for
this invitation from the staff.
ALAISHA: I'm Alaisha.
DANIEL: My name is Daniel.
ATHENA: I'm Athena Braun.
ALAISHA: I'm a sophomore.
THOMAS: I'm a senior.
BRIAN: I'm a junior studying
computer science and linguistics.
ALAISHA: I'm concentrating on CSO.
ALLISON: CS50 is also just
because it's changed my life.
It made me a computer
science concentrator.
ALAISHA: I am a TF for CS50.
ALLISON: Course assistant.
ATHENA: This is my
second year TF-ing now.
THOMAS: This is my third year
being a teaching fellow for CS50.
ATHENA: Becoming part of CS50
staff helped empower me so much.
ALAISHA: I was a total beginner, never
anticipated programming beyond CS50,
but here I am.
It was just something I
never thought I would do.
I think it's just been really
exciting going from being a beginner
to being comfortable
enough to TF this class.
MARIA: Everything that
has come out of this
has helped me grow so much
as a teacher, as a student.
DANIEL: Also, the culture
and the environment of it
is also pretty unique.
ALLISON: Definitely found a community
of friends within the CS50 staff.
ATHENA: Be prepared to have
students who look up to you
and really appreciate the
work that you're doing,
and just realize that you're
not just a teaching fellow.
You're not just this person
behind the whiteboard.
You're a student who took
this too, and can really
level with other people in your
section and figure out what's going on,
and make it a good experience for them.
DANIEL: I decided that I can
get the best of both worlds.
I can get to teach
about computer science,
and those are two of my passions.
THOMAS: I just really love teaching
computer science to beginners.
CS50 is where all that
beginner energy is,
and that's where I can make a real
impact on the students careers in CS.
BRIAN: It's amazing to see how much
this course can do in just a semester,
and how from September until
December, students learn so much
and gain so much
experience and knowledge.
And watching that and working
with them in that process
has always been really,
really inspiring.
MARIA: It's been so,
so wonderful getting
to see these people grow
just like I did myself.
THOMAS: One of the most
rewarding things I've done here.
That's why I keep coming back.
DANIEL: Going to office
hours and helping people out,
it makes you feel good, and it makes
other people feel good as well.
BRIAN: My name is Brian.
THOMAS: I'm Thomas Lively.
ALLISON: I'm Allison.
MARIA: I'm Maria, and this is CS50.
DAVID MALAN: So in the coming weeks,
please do feel welcome and encouraged.
Even if you were among those less
comfortable and still kind of think
you are, that is
undoubtedly not the case,
because amongst CS50 staff are students
who have just taken the course a year
or two or more prior, you
potentially among them.
And in fact there's other
opportunities to get involved as well.
In addition to the on-campus
class here, we of course
have our friends in New Haven,
but even beyond, the CS50's team
work with communities around the world.
In fact, every red dot on
this map here represents
a high school where there's a high
school teacher and class of students
who were taking CS50 in some
form, where their own teacher
has adopted or adapted the
curriculum, the same tools,
the same software that you all use
here in Cambridge and in New Haven
to actually teach introductory
computer science as well.
In blue, similarly, are
universities around the world
as well where we've been working with
faculty and student groups beyond.
In fact, here some of our friends
in Miami-Dade College in Florida.
Some of our friends here in Chile,
here in London, here in Burma,
here in Ukraine, here in Cairo,
here in Bolivia, here in Nicaragua.
And lastly, here on stage, our
very first cohort, so to speak,
of high school teachers teaching CS50
AP as of a couple of years ago, who then
went back through their school
districts to evangelize computer science
and empower students there to teach it.
And in fact, even though we ourselves
have our own hackathon coming up here
in just a couple of
weeks' time, so has there
been a CS50 hackathon for high schools.
In fact pictured here, was
our very first CS50 hackathon
for AP students, a mix of four public,
four private schools in Manhattan
some months ago, where everyone got
together to work on their own problems
sets, projects and the like.
So again, please feel free to engage
in any number of these ways and more.
So what did we do all
semester, and what will you
do if you continue to apply CS?
It's really all about
problem-solving, and we've certainly
solved quite a few problems, the last of
them last week with problem set eight.
If you're curious as to what your
classmates thought of the problem sets,
here we have blue means love, and purple
means hate, and each of these bars
represents problem set
zero through eight.
So you can kind of get
a sense where the love,
where the like, where the
neutral was, here in yellow.
And maybe there are some spikes
of hatred, maybe over down there.
But perhaps more revealingly
too is the difficulty
with which folks perceive these, and
this admittedly is retrospective.
So of course scratch was
pretty fun, pretty easy,
as was maybe Mario and so forth.
But you can get a sense of
some of the fluctuation.
And apparently, on the
heels of misspellings here,
we suddenly went to a lot of medium
difficulty when you simply had to port,
so to speak, some of your problems
from P-set one now for problem set six.
And in terms of demographically,
how your classmates
are engaging in the class, when
did you start problem sets?
Oh interesting.
So recall that problem sets
are released on Fridays,
and here we have Saturday,
Sunday, Monday, Tuesday.
Oh hello, Wednesday is when
really a plurality of students
seem to begin their problem sets.
Not though perhaps
surprisingly, when it coincides
with office hours and sections
in the earlier days of the week.
And then in terms of when you
watch lectures, because indeed,
both here and in New Haven, most
students, they do engage online.
You can see that, with the lectures
live on Friday, many students watch
apparently shortly after 10:00
a.m. on Fridays, but on demand,
followed by the weekend,
and the most popular being
Monday before sections presumably.
So you too are somewhere
among those inputs.
But what were the problems
that we actually solved,
and what were really
the goals of the class?
It's not to teach C per se.
It's not to introduce JavaScript
or SQL or Python, all of which
are really just tools in a toolkit.
So that when you exit CS50 and go onto
some other class or some other field,
and want to actually solve problems
using data and using computation,
that you actually just have a mental
model with which to approach it,
and less of a fear factor.
So that even if you have absolutely
no idea how to write code in Ruby,
which your lab or your company,
your friends, happen to be using,
well, no big deal.
Much like in P-set
seven and eight, where
Google and Stack Overflow and friends
become your support structure,
realize that among the goals has been
to teach you to teach yourselves.
And undoubtedly, that comes
with some frustration,
in especially those recent
weeks, but the goal really
has been to take off
these training wheels, so
that when you're no longer handed a
spec for P-set zero through eight,
you at least have a sense
of where to go from here.
And indeed the final
project is about taking off
the final of those training wheels.
Now what does problem
solving itself mean?
We described that back
in week zero as this.
You have inputs to that problem,
and at the end of the day
you care about the outputs, and what was
inside of this black box, so to speak.
So algorithms, just
step-by-step instructions
for solving some problem, and
that's where the real insight is,
the real efficiency and
the real opportunity
to get things not only correct, but also
well-designed in addition to something
like well-styled.
And so as you approach
the solutions to problems,
I dare say maybe one of the most
thematic topics of this class,
and perhaps any other introductory
class, is this theme of trade-offs,
whether it's time and space,
or the computer's time
and space versus your time and space and
so forth when solving these problems.
And consider that
there's not necessarily
one right answer to these
kinds of design questions,
but hopefully you'll feel
all the more that you
can hold your own in a conversation
with someone as or even
more technical than you and
convince them of your perspective
and contribute to the solving
of some of these problems.
And among the other topics
that have been sort of manifest
throughout the semester
is this one, abstraction,
which really speaks to this very
general problem-solving tool.
If you've got some problem
ahead of you, whether it's
something software-related
or real-world,
or really anything in between, this
idea of taking something complicated
and breaking it down into
its constituent parts,
so that you only have to
think about up at this level,
and you don't have to worry about
where the zeros and ones come from,
or where the characters on the
screen come from, and so forth.
Like the fact that we've kept layering
and layering and layering means
you could do so much more
with P-set seven and eight.
Even if it didn't feel like
it at the start of the week,
then you could with just C and
certainly with just binary alone.
So realize too, that
sort of bootstrapping
is thematic any time you're
learning some new topic.
And how do you express yourself
when trying to solve these problems?
Of course pseudocode.
And indeed, this should
become habit as well.
Doesn't really matter what
language you write in,
but I am still in the habit of
writing out comments for my programs,
and then therefore I kind of know the
outline, much like an English essay,
and then I kind of fill in the gaps
with the actual code thereafter.
Because the hard part,
and perhaps the fun part,
is really just thinking through
how you might solve something.
And in fact this was, this
feels like an opportune moment
to take a moment to see just
how well this has sunk in,
and how well we might apply some
of these most basic principles that
started in week zero and
then persisted throughout.
But for this, we need a
volunteer to come up on stage
and help me program everyone else.
Yeah, come on up.
All right.
What's your name?
Sorry?
Amy.
Amy, come on up.
Nice to meet you.
Now only Amy is about to
see what's on my screen,
and if the staff could
help me for just a moment.
Let me go ahead and cut to this.
I'll be right back.
We just need to quickly
hand out all this paper.
You can pull out a piece of
paper of your own if you have it,
but if the staff could kind of
divvy these up so that everyone
has a piece of paper.
Ideally, a pencil or pen.
If you don't, we have, pardon me, Amy.
A solution to that problem.
Everyone gets a free CS50
pen today if you'd like.
OK, very popular.
OK, so no one has a
pencil now, apparently.
All right.
So Amy, as you guys get
set up up there, I'm
about to show Amy something on
my screen, a picture to draw.
And you, much like the
programmer that you now are,
are going to program the audience
to actually draw what you see.
And we'll remember, from very early on,
that precision is probably important
here, but at the same
time, you don't want
to get tangled in the weeds
of zeros and ones so to speak.
You want ultimately
everyone in this audience,
ideally, to draw what it is
just you and I are seeing.
All right, so everyone
is unwrapping pens.
And hopefully you have a piece of paper,
though any piece of paper suffices.
I'm going to go ahead and
reveal what Amy is seeing here.
And the goal is, verbally only, to
tell the audience here what to draw.
And give everyone just a moment.
Get your paper in front of you,
pencil in hand or pen in hand.
And feels like we can begin.
AMY: OK, so I'm looking at a cube.
It's kind of like a Rubik's cube, but
I can only see three of the faces.
So there's a, this, oh.
So there is the top of the
Rubik's cube and two sides.
The top looks like a diamond, so you
want to draw the diamond on the top.
And then the two sides
come down from that,
so it looks like you're looking
at a Rubik's cube from the corner.
And it's not actually Rubik's
cube, so don't draw the lines.
It's just like a normal cube.
I don't know how else to describe it.
DAVID MALAN: Exit?
AMY: Exit.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So thank you so much to Amy.
Round of applause, if we could,
for getting us to this point.
Now comes, feel free to
partake back down there.
Now we just need that staff to help
grab some of these pieces of paper.
We'll do pseudo-random samples and
we'll take a look at correctness,
if not artistic design here.
Some folks still going past
the buzzer, but that's OK.
All right, I'm going to go
ahead and cue up my screen here.
In just a moment, we'll actually
reveal how some of these came out.
All right, that's good.
Thank you so much.
All right, so notice in particular
though, that what Amy was doing
was actually leveraging
abstraction, as it turned out.
Right?
She was telling you to draw shapes
that are hopefully familiar,
toys that are hopefully familiar,
and those of course are abstractions.
Because it would get
pretty mundane and pretty
low-level if she had to start
describing what a Rubik's cube is
or what a diamond is.
Hopefully these are
abstractions all of us know,
at least the diamond shape and so forth,
and the cube shape from yesteryear,
so at least we have
that same mental model.
So let's take a look at a few
of the shapes that we have here.
Here, we have one, two,
three attempts to draw,
but that perhaps is reminiscent
of what some of you drew as well.
This one here is super small.
We didn't really speak to scaling,
but that does look like a cube.
Perhaps not necessarily
oriented as she intended.
This one's kind of cute.
But we love them all
equally, whoever's this is.
In fairness, this one's
sort of Inception-like.
Or, oh I see.
Diamond on top of the cube, I get it.
This one's a little
bloated at the bottom.
OK, this one's actually quite beautiful.
Here we have this one here.
Very nice.
And I think she was
describing it this way.
And in fact, if I go back
to what Amy was seeing,
the answer was this one here.
So a big round of applause,
if we could, for Amy.
But now, let's flip things around.
Here we need one more volunteer
to come on up if you could.
OK, come on up.
And what is your name?
Dylan.
Dylan, come on up.
So here, we'll turn the tables a bit.
Thank you so much.
Welcome to keep those pens and the
sheets of paper if you still have them.
Let me go ahead here and
blank the screen again
and give Dylan a piece
of chalk if we could.
And so if you could come
on over here, what we
have here is a canvas on which you can
draw what the audience tells you to do.
And in fact, since the
answer is going to be there,
we're going to push this back after all.
And the only thing you
can't do is look up.
All right, so look straight ahead.
Here's your piece of chalk.
And now, what the audience is going
to see is what you need to draw,
and we'll take it one instruction at
a time to tell Dylan what to draw.
All right, the drawing is--
Who would like to contribute
the first instruction?
And also don't look to your right,
because there are answers everywhere.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: Draw a circle in
the middle of the board.
DAVID MALAN: Draw a circle
in the middle of the board.
AUDIENCE: Smaller than that.
DAVID MALAN: Smaller than that.
There you go.
AUDIENCE: Erase the big circle.
DAVID MALAN: Erase the big circle.
AUDIENCE: Draw a line
going down the circle.
DAVID MALAN: Draw a line
OK, wait, we need to buffer, buffer.
Hang on.
No.
Undo.
OK, let's restart.
Step one, draw a--
AUDIENCE: Draw a small circle
in the middle of the board.
DAVID MALAN: Draw a small circle
in the middle of the board, Dylan.
AUDIENCE: Keep it.
DAVID MALAN: Keep it.
We'll take it.
OK, step two.
AUDIENCE: Stick figures
with no arms yet.
DAVID MALAN: Draw a stick
figure with no arms yet.
Nice abstraction.
AUDIENCE: The head is the circle.
The circle's the head.
DAVID MALAN: OK, step three.
AUDIENCE: The circle is the head.
DAVID MALAN: What's that?
The circle was supposed to be the head.
OK, version two, step four.
Step four?
AUDIENCE: From the bottom of
the circle, draw inverse Y.
DAVID MALAN: From the bottom of
the circle draw an inverse Y.
Step five.
AUDIENCE: Stemming from the
head, the body and the legs
are the same height or length.
DAVID MALAN: Stepping from the head, the
body and the legs are the same height.
AUDIENCE: So, draw the body
first, and it will look like a Y.
DAVID MALAN: So draw the body
first and it will look like a Y.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
stemming from the body.
DAVID MALAN: After erasing
everything else, I heard.
OK, nice.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Erase the mustache.
OK, step six.
Step six.
AUDIENCE: Draw a V the same way.
DAVID MALAN: Draw a V the same way.
AUDIENCE: From where
you started with the Y.
DAVID MALAN: From where
AUDIENCE: Right side.
DAVID MALAN: On the right side.
No, no.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
No.
Do the opposite of that.
AUDIENCE: Downward V.
DAVID MALAN: Downward V.
AUDIENCE: It's one of his arms.
DAVID MALAN: It's one of his arms,
AUDIENCE: His right arm.
DAVID MALAN: His right arm.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
His arm.
OK, step seven?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Draw the what?
Draw the second part of
the arm from the elbow.
AUDIENCE: Continue to
draw a line from the elbow
DAVID MALAN: Elbow, elbow.
Elbow, yeah.
AUDIENCE: The arm on
your right, make it a V.
DAVID MALAN: On the arm on your
right, make it a V. OK, yes.
OK, we'll take it.
AUDIENCE: Yes.
DAVID MALAN: Yes, OK.
Almost there, almost there.
AUDIENCE: And then the other arm--
AUDIENCE: Make the other arm
touch, put his hand on his hip.
DAVID MALAN: Make the other
arm put his hand on his hip.
Yes, and last step maybe?
Second to last?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Say at 11
to 10 o'clock, draw--
DAVID MALAN: Say at 11 or 10 o'clock--
AUDIENCE: Yeah, from the circle.
DAVID MALAN: From the circle.
AUDIENCE: Look at the circle as a clock.
DAVID MALAN: Look at
the circle as a clock.
AUDIENCE: And draw a line
as big as one of arms.
DAVID MALAN: And draw a line
as big as one of the arms.
AUDIENCE: Put a space.
DAVID MALAN: Put a space.
Yes.
Last step.
Yes, over here.
AUDIENCE: Write hi above it.
DAVID MALAN: Write "hi" above it.
AUDIENCE: Capital H.
DAVID MALAN: Capital H. And
congratulations to Dylan.
That's pretty good.
Pretty good, thank you so much.
So realize, fun as this is,
it's actually non-trivial
to convert these
abstractions with which we're
familiar to things that computers, or in
some cases humans, actually understand.
So realize here too, there's this trade.
Like, saying draw a stick figure
is a very useful abstraction,
but the problem, of course, is that
the precision isn't necessarily there
if you're seeking one particular goal.
So beyond problem solving in
this way and in this class
what more can you do after CS50?
So if you take a look at
that unofficial guide to CS
that we'll link soon on
CS50's website as well,
you can go off in so many
other directions from here
to the direction of hardware,
software, graphics, theory, statistics,
mathematics, and more.
And indeed increasingly,
to the intersection
of computer science with other
worlds, like economics and now
machine learning, which is being
applied to all sorts of fields as well.
And in fact even I years ago have very
fond memories of some of these classes
and only a handful of these
even existed years ago.
I still remember to this day taking
CS141, which is a hardware class,
and even though these days much of
it's been virtualized in software,
back in the day we had tiny little
wires and tiny little breadboards,
and debugging back in
my day was literally
a matter of grabbing all of the wires
that had just frustrated you to no end
and literally ripping them out
of something called a breadboard
and starting over.
Nowadays you can do so
much more in software,
and can conceptualize things
all the more effectively
because of enhancements since.
And perhaps after CS50,
one of my favorite classes,
probably my favorite
class as an undergrad,
was CS161, an operating systems class.
We actually build pieces
of an operating system
which would be akin to
the features of Mac OS
and Windows and Linux and the like.
And so realize even if you're
among those less comfortable,
there's so many different
stepping stones.
So do chat with your TF or myself or
the course's heads or any of the CAs
about what directions
in which you might go.
And even if you don't have
the time or necessarily
the interest on campus
in doing these things,
there are so many courses online
beyond this particular campus
too, on EdX and Coursera and the like so
don't under appreciate the ability now
to go teach yourself new things
albeit with the structure of some
of these freely available classes.
But how about some
concrete steps now too,
as to what you can do after CS50 to
actually solve problems and write code?
Because at the end of
the day, you're not
going to be handed necessarily
these problem set specifications.
You're not necessarily
going to have a TF or CA
to whom you could ask questions with
which they themselves are already
familiar.
You're a bit more on your own in
terms of teaching yourself new things.
So long as, though, you take
advantage of these resources,
can you succeed at exactly that.
Now you're welcome to continue using
something like CS50 IDE for as long
as you would like.
Your accounts will keep working.
And that's meant to be
pretty representative
of a real-world environment.
But of course it's cloud-based, and
so if you're on a plane or a train
or in some of the dorms or houses
where the Wi-Fi isn't so great,
might not work so well.
And so increasingly, comment
after taking one class
would be to start installing these
kinds of tools on your own Mac or PC.
So we'll put these
slides up later as well
so that you have all of these URLs,
but if you'd like, on your Mac or PC,
whether it's over Thanksgiving or J-term
or beyond, install some command line
tools on your Mac or PC.
This means having a
command line environment
on your Mac as suggested here,
which actually comes with Mac OS.
If you install something for
free called Xcode and more,
you get a whole suite of
command line utilities.
In the world of Windows,
you can actually
install a command line
environment that's
much better than the built-in
command prompt with which
you might be familiar, so that
it behaves just like Linux.
It's essentially running Linux
on your own Windows machine.
Now git, this is something you guys
indirectly use throughout the semester
any time you ran Submit 50.
But really, all Submit 50 does is run
a few different commands, all of them
called git.
This is a version control
software, and it's
just one of several different
versions, but git probably
has the most traction these days.
And if you are still in the
habit, and even occasionally I'm
guilty of this too,
at least in the world
of writing essays and letters, if
you're in the habit of copying a file
and then naming it version
two, or copying a file
and naming it Thursday night,
and then Friday morning,
and all of these different
deltas, that is not a good system,
because you're not
leveraging the computer
to keep track of the differences,
especially so that you can rewind back
in time.
So a program like git actually lets
you keep track of all of your changes
and you have an Infinite history of
all of the work you've ever done.
Brian here nicely enough has
given a seminar on how to use git
and in turn GitHub.
On GitHub itself, if
you haven't already, you
can sign up for free
private repositories, which
means you can store your coursework
and your own work privately,
so they're not in public repos,
since to date all of your work
has been in CS50's account, but you
yourselves can start using your own.
If you do this, you can just
fill out the prompts like this,
saying you're students wanting
an individual account for free.
And then you can install git
itself on your own Mac or PC
as by following instructions here.
But what about actually writing code?
I mean theoretically, you
can use most any text editing
program on your computer, like TextEdit
on Mac OS or Notepad on Windows,
but these are not very good
tools in that they don't have
any features that are code-friendly.
But it's very easy to
install something like this.
This is super popular
among students these days,
Sublime Text, as well as software
engineers in the real world.
It gives you features like syntax
highlighting and nice indentation
features, and even
auto-complete and more.
And so this would be a
tool much like the IDE
that you can use on your own Mac or PC.
An alternative that's also
free for use here is Atom.
It behaves very similarly, and that
too is something you can try as well.
If you'd like to go a little deeper
and use some older school tools that
are very much still in
use, myself included,
because they're perhaps all the
more powerful in that they're
much more command-line based,
Vim is a very popular one.
If you add this
autocomplete plug-in, you'll
have very similar capabilities even
within that environment as well.
Now as for final projects, many students
end up making web-based applications,
maybe borrowing P-set
seven or P-set eight's code
and then adding and contributing
their own when ripping out
things that are P-set
specific, you can certainly
use CS50 IDE to host that
website so that friends
at the fair and then friends in the
houses and dorms can try it out,
or friends back home.
But of course with these
free accounts, they
tend to turn off just to save
resources after not using it
for a few hours or days.
You can at least though,
in the short term,
enable this by going to the
Share icon, and CS50 IDE,
selecting public for the
application, and then any friends who
visit a URL that looks
like that can actually
see your P-set seven,
your P-set eight, or soon,
your final project If it's web based.
But a lot cooler ultimately,
and a lot more practical
if you want this thing to survive
in perpetuity and just run 24/7,
would be to use some of these
third-party cloud services.
Heroku is a very
popular service that has
you install a little bit of
software on your Mac or PC, and then
sort of magically
thereafter, anytime you
run a command, any code you've been
working on your Mac or PC gets pushed
to the cloud, so to speak,
deployed to Heroku servers,
and then it can live at your own
domain name, either a default one
you get for free, but if you
want something a little more
custom, can you actually buy or
for free get your own domain name.
Amazon has something called AWS Educate,
which you can use for free as well,
and there's bunches
of other services too.
In fact, there's a
company called Namecheap,
which is not only cheap,
it's also free for students
if you want to buy your own domain
name for your final project or beyond,
head to a URL like this one here.
And then lastly, GitHub itself, beyond
offering version control software,
is partnered with bunches of companies
that just give free levels of service
to students as well.
So if you go get this
developer pack, so to speak,
you'll see even more options that
you can use for some amount of time
to learn from and actually use
compellingly these kinds of services.
So what remains and what lies ahead?
Well of course, we'll be seeing that
the CS50 hackathon, the CS50 fair.
More on those in just a moment.
But you're also at the point now where
you've seen a lot of languages right?
Scratch and C, and Python
and SQL, and JavaScript.
And increasingly if you spend time
in this world of CS and programming,
and if you Google and
read up on Stack Overflow,
you're going to find that
it's a pretty religious world
among some people, where everyone
has these strong opinions, sort
of correct or incorrect.
And so I would encourage you to be
as open-minded here on out as to what
the right solutions to problems are.
It is rarely the case that there is one
thing only you should use and realize
that a lot of programmers,
myself included,
will bring to the table biases
that you should keep in mind
and push back on if you think a
problem could be solved differently.
And realize too it's
all about trade-offs.
And this, to kind of paint this
picture of the various idiosyncrasies
of languages is a wonderful short talk
that a fellow gave at a conference
a few years ago wherein he pointed out
that all languages, the ones especially
that he excerpted, have
these weird features.
And so if you encounter
someone in life who's
like oh, PHP is bad because of this
or Python is bad because of that,
well you could probably
come up with those kinds
of sentences about any language.
But what's cool now is that
we've seen enough languages
and perhaps formed enough opinions
that some of the examples you're
about to see should on their face
be a little nonsensical or weird,
and it's more like programming trivia,
but hopefully now some 12 weeks later,
these examples of programming
idiosyncrasies will make sense.
Let's take a look.
All right, good.
You guys know what WAT means?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Exactly, exactly.
Let's talk about JavaScript.
Does anyone know in JavaScript
what array plus array is?
Well, let me ask you this first.
What should array + array be?
AUDIENCE: Empty array.
DAVID MALAN: Empty array.
I would also accept type error.
That is not what array + array is.
Wrong.
Array plus array is empty string.
Obviously.
I think that's obvious to everyone.
Now what would array + object be?
This would obviously be TypeError,
because those are completely
disparate types.
Does anyone know what this is?
AUDIENCE: Default.
DAVID MALAN: No.
Close.
No, far away.
AUDIENCE: Object.
DAVID MALAN: It's object.
Right, nicely done.
Now of course, because this is
plus, so you can flip the operands
and the same thing comes out.
So if we do, what?
No that's just an object.
If you do object + arrays, you
get exactly the same thing,
which as you can see you do.
And finally, the only one of
these that's actually true
is, because you know
you add arrays, you get
empty string, that doesn't make sense.
But an object plus an object is
actually not a number, technically.
So this one's actually right.
And exactly, right?
Like, what is even
going on in this last?
I just, I don't even understand what
person with a brain in their head
would think that any
of this is a good idea.
OK, OK, enough making fun
of languages that suck.
Let's talk about JavaScript.
If I say array.new 16,
or just array 16, I
get an array of 16 things
which it represents
as 16 commas, which is obvious.
And if I then join those with a
string, then I get the string 16 times.
This is actually the only line in this
entire presentation that's reasonable.
Now if I take that string
and then add a 1 to it,
it interprets the 1 as, or
casts the 1 to a string,
and then we get WAT 1 a bunch of times.
Fine.
Does anyone know what will
happen if I subtract 1 from this?
I'm assuming no one does.
Let me, I'll give you a hint.
Does this help?
Does anyone know?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
DAVID MALAN: WAT-man.
So programmer humor, just a
little taste of it there as well.
What comes next?
We will wrap a bit early,
probably in about 10--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So we'll wrap in about 10 or so minutes.
Before then, we want to give you a
teaser of what lies ahead and why.
So the CS50 hackathon of
course, here on campus,
is about working on, alongside
classmates final projects,
and having some 12 hours or
so in which to dive into them,
not only to actually get something
useful and productive done
and feel good about it, but
also we hope about having
a particularly memorable experience
among all of the course's staff
and all of your classmates.
It's not meant to be 12 hours of office
hours, but really 12 hours of fun
problem-solving with the wonderful
support structure of everyone around.
Upon arrival, you'll
check in like this here.
You'll get set up in HBS's
Hives across the river, where
we had CS50 Puzzle Day.
And throughout the evening,
well, you work with each other
or on your own projects,
solving problems
ultimately to get to an end of having
a project that's either good or better
or best as per your proposals.
Around 9:00 PM, we'll order
in some Felipe's, quite a bit.
Around 1:00 AM, we'll order
quite a bit of pizza as well.
And then throughout
the evening, will there
be not only photo booth
for some souvenir photos.
One of CS50's own therapy
dogs will be on display
to chat with and get to know.
Yes, shoutout to Milo here.
And then of course, shortly
after this, around 2:00,
3:00 AM, such things as this do happen.
But if you can make it through
the evening, at 5:00 AM,
will literally CS50
shuttle show up and take
those of you who would like to
have a culminating breakfast
over down the street to IHOP.
And then just a week or
so later is the CS50 fair,
an opportunity to show
off what you've done
and what you've learned
to all of your classmates
here, but also others across campus.
In attendance every
year some 2,000 students
and faculty and staff
from across Harvard,
some from the surrounding area
high schools as well, all of whom
are here to see what
you have pulled off.
So here is a glimpse for instance
of last year's CS50 fair.
We'll set up laptops and
tables and music and food,
and really just have
you offer an opportunity
to delight in what everyone here
has pulled off during the semester
and hardware demonstrations as well.
Also in attendance will be some
friends and recruiters and alumni
from industry.
Pictured here is one of
the city's former TFs
who actually turned himself
into a software engineer
having taken CS50 as a senior
concentrating in social studies,
and then really bootstrapped himself
in the few years after graduation
to then have a job at
Google writing software.
And of course you'll
receive at the very end,
hopefully, this proud statement
that you took indeed CS50,
and so that will be presented
at the CS50 fair as well.
In just a little bit we'll
adjourn to the pub downstairs,
where Aaron and Brian and
Maria and the whole team
will be waiting to say hello
and congratulations with CS50's
traditional cupcakes, but
before then we thought
we'd invite a few of
the staff up on stage
to participate in an
annual CS50 tradition,
especially in the spirit of
this weekend's competition.
But this one not so much Harvard
versus Yale, but students versus staff.
If we might get four brave
volunteers to come on up?
OK, I saw one hand over here.
Come on up.
OK, one hand over here.
One hand over here, and
a fourth hand over here.
Come on up.
Thank you so much to
our volunteers here.
Right there, that's fine, yeah.
What's your name?
ANDREA: Andrea.
DAVID MALAN: Andrea.
David.
Nice to meet you.
Right this way.
We'll get some chairs.
WILL: Will.
DAVID MALAN: Will.
Nice to meet you.
Right this way.
OLIVIA: Olivia.
DAVID MALAN: Olivia.
Nice to see you.
Right this way.
And--
HANNAH: Hannah.
DAVID MALAN: Hannah.
Right this way.
We've got four chairs for
staff, four chairs for students.
All right thank you.
Go on, let's put the
tablecloths up there too.
And Colton, we can spin this around.
Let's have the students
sit over there on my right.
Thank you.
And the staff will sit
over to their left.
Thank you.
And here we have, excellent.
Excellent.
And you want to do some
dramatic flair here.
All right, so you guys are
in charge of that. one.
You guys are in charge of that one.
Just keep the pen and paper there.
Oh, and even better.
Yes, let's see.
Let's see if we can do a
dramatic flourish here.
I think we can do better for you guys.
Yes.
You guys get the better tablecloth.
There we go, OK.
All right, so you may recall,
as part of problem set eight,
we asked you a few
quiz review questions.
Not all of them made the
cut into the actual quiz.
There was a lot of what is HTTP
stand for and what is HTML stand for?
But that's OK.
We went through the
list and culled a few
that we'll use here for CS50's
annual student v. staff Jeopardy.
Because the questions were written in
the form of questions and not answers,
we'll simply read them as is.
We've excerpted a number of categories
from which your own classmates wrote
questions.
We don't have buzzers, but we
do have things that squeak, so.
We have four of these.
So if you just squeak the
duck if you'd like to buzz in.
Colton will help me adjudicate
as to whose hand went up first.
And let's go ahead and put a
microphone, here microphone here,
and before we begin, perhaps some
quick hellos of name and dorm or house
into the microphones.
OLIVIA: Hi.
I'm Olivia.
I'm a freshman and I'm in Wigg.
HANNAH: Hi, I'm Hannah, and I'm a first
year at Graduate School of Design.
WILL: Hi guys.
I'm Will Yao.
I live in Grays.
ANDREA: Hi.
I'm Andrea.
I'm a senior in Mather.
DAVID MALAN: And let's
now meet the staff.
ERIN: I'm Erin.
ARMAV: I'm Armav.
I'm a sophomore in Eliot.
THOMAS: I'm Thomas.
I'm a senior in Kirkland.
MARIA: Maria, senior in Cabot.
DAVID MALAN: And so perfect
that Maria is up here too,
because I went through our archives,
and if we look back some four years,
there she is as well.
When apparently it was fashionable
to wear Google Glass around campus.
So here we have our Jeopardy
board, implemented in HTML.
And we have single Jeopardy ahead.
We won't run the whole board.
Just a few choice examples
from each category.
Before we began, students
won the coin toss,
so you guys will get to pick
the category and dollar amount.
I'll ask the question.
Colton will kindly keep
track of the score,
and we'll see how this turns out.
Before we adjourn for cupcakes.
What topic would you guys like?
OK, Scratch for?
AUDIENCE: $200.
DAVID MALAN: Scratch for $200.
First one to squeak gets the answer.
Which puzzle piece starts the program?
I think I heard students.
ANDREA: The flag one?
DAVID MALAN: Yes the one flag clicked.
What color is the flag?
ANDREA: Green?
DAVID MALAN: When green flag
clicked is correct, for $200.
Very good.
Very nice.
You're still in control of the board.
OLIVIA: Let's take-- memory?
[INAUDIBLE]
Memory for $400.
DAVID MALAN: Memory for $400.
Stepping it up.
So for Memory, how much
memory does a byte have?
Also didn't make the quiz.
THOMAS: One byte.
Eight bits?
DAVID MALAN: I'll take
eight bits, yes, for $400.
Staff are now in control.
Nicely done, Thomas.
Yes, a byte is a byte.
What category would you all like next?
Whoa, wait.
THOMAS: Algorithms for $400.
DAVID MALAN: What for four?
DAVID MALAN: Algorithms for $400.
So in Algorithms, we have the
following question for you.
What is the Big O?
I heard it over here.
WILL: It's used to
describe time complexity.
DAVID MALAN: Used to
Correct for $400.
Wonderful Students are in control
and are currently up to $600.
Still taking the lead again.
What would you like next?
STUDENTS: C.
DAVID MALAN: C. For $400.
C for $400.
We're going to go with--
why did we start with C?
And there's no answer.
Go ahead.
I heard you squeak first.
WILL: Because if we started
with something else, going to C
would be terrible.
DAVID MALAN: Starting with something
else going to C would be terrible.
Staff, what do you think?
THOMAS: Sure.
DAVID MALAN: All right, for $400.
That was C for $400.
We have time for just one or two more
questions here in Single Jeopardy.
Students are still in control
and really winning now.
OLIVIA: C for a thousand.
DAVID MALAN: C for a thousand.
Oh my goodness.
All right, remember to buzz in.
What is the ending punctuation
to each line of code in order--
I heard I think the staff first.
Yes?
THOMAS: Semi-colon I hope.
DAVID MALAN: It's the staff's turn.
Semi-colon for $1,000.
Excellent.
I think then it's time for us to move
to Double Jeopardy here, at which point
the dollar amounts increase
by a factor of two.
We have time for a few
questions in this category.
Staff are now in control.
$1,400 to $1,000.
STAFFER: Data structure, $2,000.
THOMAS: Data structures
for $2,000, please.
DAVID MALAN: Data structures.
Data structures for $2,000.
Here we go.
How many children does a
node have in a binary tree?
Oh I heard over here.
Yours didn't work.
Your duck didn't work.
Two is correct.
Two is correct for $2,000.
Time for one or two more questions.
Students are back in
control, $3,000 to $1,400.
WILL: Python for $2,000.
DAVID MALAN: Python for $2,000.
Python for $2,000.
Python for two.
OK, how do you say, for $2,000, else-if?
You think Erin?
All right, your duck worked this time.
ERIN: LF?
DAVID MALAN: LF is correct for $2,000.
You're now at $3,400.
OK, don't have the
support of the audience.
Time for one more question before
Final Jeopardy and cupcakes.
What will your category
and dollar amount be?
MARIA: Let's do HTTP, $2,000.
DAVID MALAN: HTTP for $2,000.
Really going to pull ahead with
this question, potentially.
HTTP for $2,000.
OK, when asked for a
question about HTTP,
your classmate asked us to
ask the following question.
Laughing my ass off.
Just use the cat
questions from the test.
Asked by-- We'll try another.
We'll try another.
We are going to go with get coffee.
HTTP/1.1.
MARIA: What?
OLIVIA: Something I'm a teapot?
DAVID MALAN: Yes, students.
OLIVIA: It's the I'm a teapot error.
Okay, sorry, I'll pass it on to you.
DAVID MALAN: No that
was correct, though.
Nicely done. $2,000.
So now, this was an
old April Fool's joke,
where it was introduced
as a joke, HTTP 418.
So now, we're at time for
the Final Jeopardy question
where, for this question you
have a piece of paper and a pen.
The staff have $3,400.
The students have $5,000, so
there's some strategy here.
You're going to first need to decide
on a dollar amount knowing only
what the category is.
The category is going
to be web programming.
How much would you like to
wager on web programming?
MARIA: All of it.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, I don't think
you're supposed to tell me yet.
In Jeopardy, yes.
And we also need, let me
grab just our song here.
Stand by one second.
And students, if you could write
down how much you want to wager,
strategically not knowing
what the staff is wagering.
We need, here we go.
ANDREA: I don't know.
DAVID MALAN: OK, so you
are wagering some amount.
And you guys are wagering.
OK, so the question is, and you'll have
34 seconds to come up with your answer.
This is a real question
by one of your classmates.
Here we go.
The creator of a hybrid language
allowing users to meld HTML and Python
had what color hair?
[MUSIC - "THINK!"]
All right, so we're going
to take a look first
at staff, who were trailing with $3,400.
They wagered, turns out, all of it.
And answered red hair.
The students meanwhile, at $5,000
wagered $1,900 and went with brown.
I think we're going to need to have
the audience decide whether or not
the staff's answer is correct, because
according to your classmate who gave us
the question, the creator of a hybrid
language allowing users to meld
HTML and Python had what color hair?
The answer is ginger.
So congratulations to both
staff and to students.
Thank you so much for
a wonderful semester.
Cake is now served
downstairs in the pub.
We'll see you at the hackathon and fair.