[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right, this
is CS50, and this is lecture 9.
And so we've been diving
into bunches of languages
recently among them have been HTML,
and CSS, and Python most recently.
And soon we're going
to see JavaScript soon.
We're going to see SQL and more.
So let's see just a moment if we can
kind of wrap our minds around what's
going on with these various languages.
So HTML, which we looked at a couple
of weeks back, is used for what?
AUDIENCE: Websites.
DAVID MALAN: Websites.
OK, but be more specific.
What about websites?
AUDIENCE: Markup.
DAVID MALAN: Markup.
OK, be more specific than markup.
What does that mean?
AUDIENCE: The way they look.
DAVID MALAN: The way they look.
OK, good, so marking up a website,
the structure of the website,
and the contents of the website are
what you would annotate using HTML--
Hypertext Markup Language.
It's not a programming
language, so it doesn't
have functions, and
loops, and conditions,
and the kind of logical control
that we've used for some time.
It really is about
presenting information.
Make something bold.
Make something italics.
Put something centered and so forth.
CSS, meanwhile, allows you to
really take things the final mile
and really get the
aesthetics just right.
And so, in fact, what I just described,
boldfacing, and italics, and centering,
early on in version 1 say of
HTML was actually how you did it.
There was no CSS.
But these days, the better approach is
to factor out those kinds of aesthetics
from your HTML and instead put them
in this other language, CSS, Cascading
Style Sheets.
So your HTML now becomes
put this text in a column.
Put this other text in another column.
And structure your
data in a certain way.
And then stylize it with colors,
and fonts, and placement using CSS.
Now meanwhile, most recently,
we introduced Python.
And what was noteworthy about Python?
What do you got?
Some-- back here?
Python--
AUDIENCE: More straightforward syntax.
DAVID MALAN: More straightforward
syntax, yeah, in some ways,
and we'll see some syntax where
you take that back, I think.
But in general, that
is kind of the case,
because you don't need parentheses
if they're not strictly necessary.
You don't need curly
braces just because.
Instead, things like indentation become
more important, which on the one hand
is a little annoying,
but on the other hand,
really does reinforce good habits.
So that's probably a good thing.
And then at the very
end of the last lecture,
we did something that was
hopefully wonderfully inspiring,
which was to implement what in Python?
AUDIENCE: Dictionary?
DAVID MALAN: The dictionary.
And so we've really, we
pretty much re-implemented
all of problem set 5 speller using like
I don't know, 15, 20, 25 lines of code,
not to mention I was able to
type it out within 30 seconds.
And that's not just because
I knew what I wanted to type,
but really because you have
to write so few lines of code.
With Python, and soon with JavaScript,
and even other languages out there,
you just get so much more
functionality for free.
If you want to know the length of
the string, you call a function.
If you want to get a linked list, you
create a data structure called a List.
If you want a hash table, you create
a data structure called a Dictionary.
You don't implement it yourself.
Underneath the hood, someone
else out there in the world
has implemented all of
that functionality for us.
But now we're standing
on their shoulders.
And so today, what we begin
to do is to transition
to this last portion of the class, where
our domain is not just a command line
and dot slash something, but web
programming, where the ideas are pretty
much going to be the same so long as
we now understand, as hopefully you
do or are beginning to, what HTTP
is and how the web and the internet
itself work.
So recall that we looked a little
bit ago at a URL like this.
And so if you were to visit
https://www.facebook.com and hit
Enter in your browser, you're
going to send some kind of message
in an envelope that might physically
in our world look like this.
But of course, it's digital instead.
And what is inside of that
envelope, if you simply
do type that URL before
trying to get to Facebook?
AUDIENCE: An error message
that redirects to--
I guess [INAUDIBLE] that one.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, probably no
error message here, because that URL
did have the HTTPS.
And it wouldn't so much
be an error message,
but like a preference to
go to a different location.
AUDIENCE: Moved?
DAVID MALAN: Sorry?
AUDIENCE: Moved.
Moved, like permanently moved.
DAVID MALAN: Oh moved.
Not moved, only if we had
gone to a shorter URL.
Recall that all of
those 301 one redirects
were the result of, for instance,
leaving off the dub dub dub
or leaving off the S. so
this is actually the good.
This was the end of the story, where
everything just worked and we got back
a 200 OK.
So if I did hit Enter though on my
laptop and tried to visit that URL,
what did I put, or my laptop
put inside of this envelope?
AUDIENCE: Request.
DAVID MALAN: The request to get an
address, so it was like the get verb,
like getme, probably slash, because the
last thing in this URL is the slash.
It probably had a Host header.
Recall, we saw host colon and then
the domain name of the website again.
And there were bunches of
other headers, so to speak,
that we kind of turned a blind eye to.
But in essence, atop the
piece of paper, virtually,
that's inside of this envelope, or
at least these two lines, a reminder
as well as to what protocol, sort
of what handshake convention,
we are trying to use with the server.
And now when the server responds
with an envelope of its own,
how do these headers change?
What's inside of Facebook's HTTP
headers in its envelope back to me?
Kind of spoiled it a moment ago.
What?
AUDIENCE: The IP address?
DAVID MALAN: Somewhere--
let's kind of consider that
on the outside of the envelope, though.
That's how it gets to me.
What's on the inside?
What's the status code going to be
when I visit Facebook's Home page?
AUDIENCE: 200 OK
DAVID MALAN: 200 OK-- and so we
saw 200 OK only when we actually
looked underneath the
hood, so to speak, to see
what was inside of these
envelopes using Chrome's Inspector
toolbar, the developer tools, or
using cURL, that command line program.
Odds are, there are
other headers in there,
like content type is text slash html.
And I think that's the only one we saw.
But moving forward, as you make
your own web-based applications,
you will actually see and Chrome
and other tools a whole bunch
of different content types.
You'll see like image slash
ping or image slash jpeg.
So indeed, anytime
you download a picture
of a cat or something from
the internet, included
in the headers in that envelope
are two lines like this.
But a cat is not a web page.
It's not HTML.
So this would be like image slash
jpeg, if it's a photograph of a cat.
And then below that
though, the dot dot dot,
is where things started to get
interesting in the last half
of our lecture on HTTP, because what
came below all of the HTTP headers
inside of this envelope from Facebook?
What's inside of the envelope?
AUDIENCE: Nothing?
DAVID MALAN: Nothing-- yes,
it's technically an answer.
But--
AUDIENCE: Isn't it like
pieces of the file?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's
the pieces in the file.
I mean, it really is the file itself.
So essentially, when you write
a letter in the human world,
you usually put like the date.
And you might put the person's address.
And you might put like dear so-and-so.
You can kind of think of
all of that like metadata,
the stuff that's not really the
crux of your message to the human,
as being the HTTP headers.
But then once you start
writing your first paragraph
and the actual substantive part of your
letter, that's going to be down here,
so to speak.
And that's going to be the
HTML inside of this envelope.
So if I'm downloading Facebook's Home
page via my browser to my computer,
and I am seeing Facebook's Home page
or my news feed, or if I'm logged in,
all of that HTML is actually
inside of this envelope.
Now technically, it's all zeros
and ones at the end of the day.
But now that we're not sort
of at week zero anymore,
we're thinking in terms of language,
there's just a whole bunch of HTML.
And what did that HTML look like?
Well in the simplest case, it
might have looked like this.
This is a simpler web page
certainly than Facebook's own.
But this would be an example
of the first paragraph,
so to speak, of Facebook's Home
page coming from server to browser.
And so that's the relationship
among HTTP and HTML and, in turn,
CSS, though there's none pictured here.
HTTP is that protocol,
that set of conventions,
ala the human handshake that
ensures that the data is formatted
in a certain way and
gets to me from server
to browser, or from browser to server.
Below that is a very
specific language called
HTML, which is the actual content.
And what does my browser
do upon receiving this?
Well, just like we humans would read
the first paragraph of the letter,
a browser is going to read this
top to bottom, left to right,
and do what it says.
Hey, browser, here is a web page.
Hey, browser, here is
the head of the page.
Hey, browser, here is the title.
Put it in the tab bar.
Hey, browser, here's the body.
Put it in the big rectangular
region of the window.
Hey, browser, that's
it for the web page.
So you can think of these open tags
and close tags or start tags and end
tags as really being these directives.
Do something; stop doing something.
And that's literally what the
browser is doing underneath the hood.
So the last time we introduced Python,
which is unrelated fundamentally
to all of this.
It is just another programming language.
So technically we could have started
talking about Python in like week 1,
right after we looked at
Scratch instead of looking at C.
But instead, we started sort of
with Scratch, the graphical program.
Then we kind of went
super low level with C,
and built, and built,
and built on top of it,
until now we're kind of at Python, where
we can solve all of those same problems
with Python.
And in fact, one of the
challenges of problem
set 6 is going to be to rewind a
few weeks and re-implement Mario,
and Cash or Credit, or
Caesar, or Vigenere in Python,
so that you effectively have your
own solutions handy, or the staff
solutions in C. And it'll
be really kind of a warm-up
exercise and a comforting exercise
to just translate something
that you know works or
should work to a new language
and see the mapping from one to
another, just like we did with Speller,
but more powerfully.
We're also going to start to
build applications using Python
that we've not built before.
And so among them, for
instance, today will
be a handful of examples
that actually use Python
to generate HTML from a server to me.
Because you could write
this on your Mac or PC.
You could save it.
You could upload it to a server
in the cloud, so to speak.
And people can visit it.
But if I visit this page today,
or tomorrow, or the next day,
it's always going to be the same.
It's going to say hello
title, hello body every day.
Facebook, and Gmail, and any website out
there these days is much more dynamic.
The content changes based
on you or other humans,
typically, or even the time
of day, if it's a new site.
So today we're going to explore,
how do you use programming,
in Python in particular, to
generate dynamic content,
ultimately based on data in
your database interactions
from the user or any
number of other things.
So how do we go about doing this?
Well, let me go ahead and open
up the IDE for just a moment
and open up an example from today's
source code called serve.py.
This is an example, a few of whose
features might look a little familiar,
but not all of them.
So let me scroll to the bottom first.
This is a program written in Python
that implements a web server.
So remember, a server--
even though most of us, at least
I certainly grew up thinking of it
as a physical machine--
it's technically a piece of software
running on a physical machine.
So just to be clear, what
does a web server do?
What's its purpose in life?
AUDIENCE: Like connects to the internet.
DAVID MALAN: Connects--
a little too grand--
its functionality is actually much
more narrowly defined, I would say.
What's a web server?
That's kind of like a
router interconnects things.
AUDIENCE: Door?
DAVID MALAN: What's that?
AUDIENCE: Your door to the internet.
DAVID MALAN: Door to
the-- even too fancy
a description-- let's really home
in on what it does functionally.
AUDIENCE: It listens for requests
and then responds to them?
DAVID MALAN: Right, so a
much less interesting answer,
but much more concrete and factual
as to what the server does.
Exactly, it is a piece of software
that just listens for HTTP requests
on the internet coming in what?
--via wired or wireless connections.
As soon as it hears an HTTP
request, like get slash,
it responds to those requests.
So that is what the web server does.
So Facebook.com, and Google.com,
and all of these companies
have web server software running
on physical machines that
are just constantly
listening for those requests.
And the photo I showed last time of
that old rack at Google's headquarters
is an example of a
whole bunch of servers
that were running the same
software, all of which
had internet connections that were
just listening for HTTP connections,
specifically, if we want to get
really precise from a few weeks
back, on TCP port 80,
on a certain IP address.
But again, we can kind of
abstract away from that.
And as you say, it's listening
for connections on the internet.
So how does this piece of software work?
Just to demonstrate
how relatively easy it
is to write a web server, irrespective
of the content it serves up, line 24,
if you could translate
it into English for me,
based only on last week's
material, what is line 24 doing?
And it's not configure server.
More technically, what
does line 24 do in Python?
AUDIENCE: It's just assigning
port the number 8080.
DAVID MALAN: To?
Oh, yes, OK, to port.
So, OK, so what is port exactly?
AUDIENCE: Just a variable.
DAVID MALAN: Just a variable--
what is its data type?
AUDIENCE: It's an int.
DAVID MALAN: How do you know that?
I don't see int.
AUDIENCE: Or the input
is given as an int.
And Python just dynamically
figures is out somehow.
AUDIENCE: Exactly, so we-- unlike C,
you don't specify the types anymore,
but they do exist--
ints, and strings, and
floats, and so forth.
But honestly, why do we
really need to specify int
if it's obvious to the human, let
alone should be to the computer,
that the thing on the right is an int.
Just make the thing on the left an int.
And this is one of the features you
get of Python, and in general, more
modern languages.
Meanwhile, line 25 is similar in spirit.
Give me a variable
called server address.
But this we didn't talk
about too much last time.
I mentioned the word only in passing.
This is a little funky.
We never saw this syntax
in C in this context--
parenthesis something comma
something close parenthesis.
We absolutely saw that syntax when we
were calling functions and so forth,
or when we had if conditions or the
like, or loops, and while loops,
and for loops.
But we've never seen, to my
recollection, a pair of parentheses
open and close that have
nothing next to them
other than, in this
case, the equal sign.
But what does this kind of look like
maybe from other classes you've taken?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, sorry, say again.
You want to go with ordered pair?
Yeah, so if you think to any
math class or graphing class,
anytime you dealt with x and y, it's
kind of common in certain worlds
to have pairs of numbers, or triples
of numbers, or quads of numbers.
And so Python actually
supports that idea.
If you have two related values
that you want to kind of cluster
together in your mind, you can simply
do open parenthesis one value comma
the other.
And the general term
for this is a tuple--
T-U-P-L-E. So it's kind of
like a double or a triple.
But a tuple is any number of things,
one or more things in parentheses.
So why are these related?
Well, in TCP/IP, the protocol
spoken on the internet,
the first thing is the IP address.
The second thing is the TCP port.
So we have both IP
and TCP, ergo, TCP/IP.
And so we're just storing both
of those variables in this--
both of those values in this
address called server address.
Meanwhile, this kind of code we
wouldn't really be familiar with yet.
But this is declaring another
variable on the left called httpd,
d meaning daemon, which is a synonym for
server, so HTTP server, aka web server.
Give me some kind of HTTP server object.
This is like a special
struct, like a student struct.
But this struct actually
implements a web server,
passing in the server address
and whatever this thing here is.
And let me wave my hand
at that for just a moment.
But then the last line of code here
on 29, says inside of that variable
is a function, otherwise
known as a method,
called serve forever
that literally does that.
When you run this program,
and it gets to line 29,
the program never, ever ends.
It doesn't exit.
It just keeps staying there.
Never again do you see a prompt.
It literally is serving forever
by listening for HTTP requests.
Now let me just show
you what this does now.
Let me go ahead in my terminal window.
And how do I run a Python program?
AUDIENCE: Python [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Exactly-- so it's this.
Unlike C, you literally say
Python, which is not only
the name of the language
but it's the name
of the program, the interpreter
that can understand this file.
And if I go ahead and run that,
I can't open file serve.py.
Up No such file in directory.
So technically, I
didn't mean to do that.
But teachable moment,
what's going wrong?
AUDIENCE: You're not
in the right folder.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I'm
not in the right folder.
So before I mentioned it's in
Today's Source Code, Source 9, so let
me just cd into the right
directory, and now do it again.
And now nothing seems
to be happening forever.
And so it seems like the
server is actually running.
So I'm actually going
to go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and go up to
Web Server under the Menu here.
I just have a little
warning from Cloud9.
I'm going go ahead and click App.
And now notice what's happening.
My new URL is going to look
different than your URL might.
But in my case here, I just went to
ide50 dash malan dash Harvard dot edu--
because that's my username on Cloud9--
dot cs50 dot io colon 8080.
Because this program, this server,
it is listening for TCP connections
on port 8080, not the default, but 1880.
And as soon as it hears a
connection, it literally
spits out apparently "hello, world."
So where is that coming from?
Well, if I zoom out and go back to
my program here and look at the top,
we'll see what this thing actually is.
And we won't have to get into the
particulars of why this works.
But this is how a web server
functions at the end of the day.
When a web server receives an envelope
from a user's browser, like this one
here, it looks inside and it
realizes, oh, this is a GET request.
Because literally the verb
GET is inside of the envelope.
So here is a function
called doget, just because.
And then what do we do?
This line here, 13, is telling
the server to send 200, OK.
It's telling it to send this
header, content type text HTML.
And it's telling it to write the
following string, "hello, world,"
in what's called Unicode or
UTF-8 out on the internet.
And that's it.
So this is a very specific example.
This web server is not all that useful,
because no matter who or how often you
connect to this web server
on port 8080 of your domain
name, what is it going to show?
AUDIENCE: Hello, world.
DAVID MALAN: Hello, world--
so not interesting--
you might as well have
just save the whole darn thing as
like index.html and be done with it,
and not use Python at all.
But what if, what if instead of doing
this, you have code in your web server
that says something like this--
figure out what file was
requested from HTTP headers,
because remember it might be slash.
It might be slash zuck, for
Mark Zuckerberg's Home page,
or some other request.
Check if that file exists.
If so, send it back to browser.
In other words, suppose we remove this
hard-coded stuff about "hello, world,"
and just start to write some
code, or at least for now
pseudocode, that makes
the web server dynamic.
Upon getting a request on port 8080,
it checks what the request is for,
per this first line 12.
If it finds it on the
hard drive locally,
it's going to send it back to the user.
And so ultimately, that
is what a web server does.
I hard-coded a simple
one to just forever say,
"hello, world." but that's
what a web server does.
And moving forward, we are not going
to implement the web server itself
in Python.
We're instead going to use a tool,
a pretty popular one called Flask.
So there's bunches and bunches
of different web server software
out there in the world.
Flask happens to be one of them.
It's technically called
a micro framework,
because it's like a small amount of
code that other people wrote just
to make it easier to serve up websites.
And so rather than write
the web server ourselves,
we're going to use a web server
that someone else wrote, Flask,
and actually start writing our own
applications on the web with it.
So now what does this mean?
Let me go ahead and do the
following back here in the IDE.
Let me ahead and kill this server
here, close that file here,
and let me go ahead
and let's say do this.
I'm going to go ahead
and create a new file.
And if I Google this, Python--
Python Flask, the only way I
would know what I'm about to do
is if I had looked up the
documentation for Flask
and I followed the instructions,
literally read the documentation.
And at one point, I kind of read
through the user guide here.
I looked at some examples.
I played around with my IDE, saved
some things and tried them out.
And thus was born this kind of example.
So if you want to use Flask, it turns
out you essentially have to do this.
You first define an application.
And you say, Flask name.
Why?
It's not all that useful for now
for us to dive into the weeds here.
But this just says, hey,
Flask, give me a web app.
I don't care how it's implemented.
You take care of that, so
I don't have to write code
like the previous serve.py file.
And then after that, I need to
tell flask what to do and when.
And so the way you do this in
a lot of modern web software
is you define what are called routes.
You say to Flask, or your
web server more generally,
hey, server, if you get a
request for slash, do this.
If you get a request
for slash zuck, do this.
If you get a slash for slash
login, do this other thing.
And so the pseudocode in a server
might be something like this--
if request is for slash,
then send back home page.
Else if request is for slash zuck, which
again was just one of the sample URLs
two times ago, then
send Mark's Home page.
Else if the request is for login, then
prompt user to log in, and so forth.
So this is a web-based
application, albeit in pseudocode.
It has nothing to do with TCP/IP per se.
That is going to be the job of
the web server to deal with.
I don't want to even know there are
envelopes virtually on the internet.
I just want to start
writing code in my logic.
Just like in C, I want to write my
main function and my helper functions.
Here is what my web
application is going to do.
So how do you do this?
Well, suppose that you
want to do the following.
Let me go into--
save this as application.py, which
is just a convention, application.py.
And let me create momentarily
another file called index.html.
So I need a really quick web page here.
And this will come with
practice, but let me go ahead
and just quickly whip up a
little web page-- head here,
title, hello, title, and then
down here body, and hello body.
OK, so super simple web page, same
as we did a couple of weeks back.
That's all.
It's in a file called index.html.
How do I now connect these two files?
If I have a program written in
Python, or technically pseudocode,
and one of the things I want this
program to do is this pseudocode here--
if request is for slash,
then send back the Home page.
We've branch into, I think,
briefly a couple times ago
that the default Home page
for a website is often, just
by human convention, called index.html.
So this pseudocode now is kind of this.
If the request is for slash,
specifically send back index.html.
But instead, if the request is for
slash zuck, then send Mark's Home page.
So what might that look like?
Let me actually go and
copy this, make a new file.
And just for kicks, I'm going to save
it as a zuck.html and then hello, world,
I am Mark.
So suppose this is Mark's Profile page.
It's super simple.
It's obviously not what
Facebook looks like.
But it is a valid HTML page.
So now I have two files
and one web application.
So technically, I should
really send back zuck.html.
And if I continue this sort of imaginary
example, then prompt user to log in,
that probably means then
show user login.html,
which is yet another page
that has like a form on it.
It's just like the form we made
for our simple Google example.
So in short, all a web
application is, it's
a program written in some
language that respond
to requests based on some logic.
And this is the logic that we
did not have in HTML alone.
This is why we need Python,
or Java, or Ruby, or PHP,
or any number of other
languages can do the same thing.
C can also do this, but it would
be an awful, awful nightmare
to implement this in C. Because
just think of how annoying
it is to like compare substrings or
extract something like the HTTP headers
from a longer-- it's just a lot of work.
A fun fact-- two years ago we had
problem set, where we did exactly
that, but now it's a little different.
So here's how we transition to
making this an actual web app.
Let me go ahead and translate
this to actual code.
Let me delete this.
And it turns out, in Flask, if you
want to find a route, so to speak,
for slash, you do this.
My app shall have a route for slash.
And when that route
is visited by a user,
by making a request in
one of these envelopes,
go ahead and call a function
in Python called index--
though I could call it anything I want--
that simply returns the result of
rendering a template called index.html.
And we'll see why that is
called a template in just a bit.
But know that Flask gives me this
special function called Render
Template that will spit out a file.
But it does more than that, which
is why it has a fancier name.
The file I want it to
spit out is index.html.
Meanwhile, if I want to support
Mark Zuckerberg's Home page,
I'm going to do what then,
if you just kind of infer?
AUDIENCE: Def zuck.
DAVID MALAN: Def, OK, zuck.
AUDIENCE: And then return
his-- the rendered template.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so return
render template of zuck.html.
And one more thing--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] backslash zuck.
DAVID MALAN: Backslash--
backslash where?
No need for backslash
or escape characters,
but there's one-- one of these things
is not like the other at the moment.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so we need to
define this function as being,
quite simply, the function that Flask
should call when the user visits
slash zuck.
Now again, it seems a little
stupid that we've written zuck
in three places, index in two places.
That's just kind of
the way it is in Flask.
Like this could just be Foo.
This could be bar.
The function names don't matter.
But you might as well keep yourself
sane and use the same names
as relate to the routes themselves.
So now we've replaced two of
my conditions in my pseudocode
with actual code.
And if we take this one step
further, to do the Login screen.
I bet I just need to do something like
app dot route slash login and then
maybe something like def login return
render template login dot html, which
I didn't bother making,
but I certainly could
with some copy/paste and some edits.
So now we have a web application
that supports three routes.
When it gets a request in an envelope
from someone on the internet,
it will look inside that envelope
and check, what are you requesting?
Well, if you're requesting slash,
I'm going to this function.
If you're requesting slash zuck,
I'm going to call this function.
Or slash login, I'm going
to call that function.
And that's it.
The web app is not
complete because notice,
we seem to have no code that actually
checks usernames, and passwords,
and sort of fancy features that
you would hope actually exist.
But that's more code to come.
For now, all we're doing is spitting
out, conditionally, different files.
So how do I now make this work?
Well turns out, I need to make
a directory called templates,
so make dir templates-- or I could do
it with the file browser, with the GUI--
Enter.
I'm going to move both
index.html in there with mv.
And I'm going to move
mark into there with mv.
And now I need to do one other thing.
In my program up here,
I've deliberately-- whoops,
oh, let's close the tabs,
because I moved the files.
That's OK.
It's just because I moved the
files into a subdirectory.
So let me re-open those.
So I left the room appear
deliberately for a couple of reasons.
One, Flask-- rather Python--
has no idea what Flask is.
When Python was invented years ago,
there was no such thing as Flask.
That was written more
recently by a community
of people, who have been making
better web server software since.
So if I want to use a package that
someone else wrote, aka a library,
recall that I can do something like
this from Flask import FLASK, which
is a little stupid looking.
But this just means
somewhere on the IDE,
we have pre-installed
a package called Flask.
Inside of there is a feature
called FLASK-- capital letters--
which happens to be what I'm using here.
And for today's purposes, you
can think of this as a structure.
It's not a student struct, which
is the go to example thus far.
But it's a special web app
structure that I'm somehow using.
But you can just take on faith for
now that that's what that does.
But render template is also not
a function that I implemented.
And indeed, nowhere in the file is
it actually defined or implemented.
Turns out that comes with Flask, so
I can also import a second function.
Just like I imported get int
or get string or get float,
I can import this function
called render template.
And that's all I actually need here.
So now I'm going to go ahead,
and if I didn't make any typos,
I'm going to go ahead and now do this--
Flask run.
So Flask, in addition to being
like a framework, a way of writing
web applications, it is
also a little program
called Flask that takes some
command line arguments, one of which
is Run, which just says run the
web app in my current directory.
And that file, by convention,
has to be called application.py.
So when I hit Enter, I see a
whole bunch of debugging output.
Debugger is active.
We'll see what that means some time.
And now here is the URL.
It's really ugly looking, because I have
a pretty long user name here on Cloud9,
but notice it's the port
8080 that's important.
Let me go ahead and open that.
And now I see "hello, body."
But up here-- and remember
that the slash is inferred.
Chrome is just being used
friendly and hiding it.
If I change this to zuck--
Enter-- "I am Mark."
And if I change it to login,
what's going to happen?
AUDIENCE: Nothing, because it--
DAVID MALAN: Not found-- so something
deliberately at this time it's going
to go wrong because I didn't--
whoa-- OK, so I didn't bother
making that template yet.
And so you'll soon be familiar,
not with segfaults any more,
but probably with something
called an exception.
And we'll see more of these over time.
But Python, unlike C, supports
something called exceptions, which
is a type of error that can happen.
And essentially, one of the features,
if a little cryptic, of Flask,
is that anytime something really goes
wrong like a segfault, but in this case
called an exception, you'll
see a somewhat pretty web page
that I did not write.
I didn't make any of this HTML.
Flask generates that
for me just to show me
all of the darn errors
that somehow ensued,
so I can try to wrap my
mind around what's going on.
Fortunately, the most important
one is usually at the top.
And it kind of says what I need
to know-- "template not found,"
even though I'm not sure what
this means yet, "login.html."
So I can infer from that
what's actually gone wrong.
So that might be my very first example.
And the key takeaways here are that
I have written Python code with logic
to decide, if the request
comes in for this, do this.
If the request comes in for
some other thing, do this,
else do this other thing, so kind
of a three-way fork in the road,
even though the results
are just some text files.
OK, any questions or
confusions at this point?
OK, so now that we have
a programming language,
we can do much more
powerful things, kind
of sort of like I tried
to do back in my day
when I first learned how
to write web applications.
And one of the first things I did--
let me go ahead and
close all of this up.
One of the first things I did was
to make a website for the Freshmen
Intramural Sports Program.
And let me go ahead in here to
Frosh IM0, open up some templates,
and we're about to see is this.
Here's a little web application
that I made in advance.
It's in a folder called Frosh IM0, which
has a template subdirectory, inside
of which are a whole bunch of web pages.
And you can probably infer
what they are used for.
Index is probably the
default. Success has something
to do with things going right.
Failure is probably the opposite.
And we don't know yet what
layout.html is, and an application.py.
That's it.
So let's actually see what
index.html looks like.
And that's the following.
In index.html, it looks like
we have a whole bunch of HTML.
And I've cut off deliberately
the first couple of lines.
But what's an H1 tag?
AUDIENCE: Header.
DAVID MALAN: Header, so it's
like a big bold piece of text.
So "Register for Frosh IMs" looks
like the main text atop this page.
Form, action, register, method, post, we
saw this briefly when we re-implemented
Google a few weeks ago.
So here, "action" means
that when you click Submit,
this is going to be submitted to
the current domain slash register.
And it's going to use
a method called Post.
So we didn't talk about this in
detail last time, but it turns out
there's at least two verbs
to know in the web world--
Get, which puts everything you type
in into the URL, and Post, which,
in short, does not.
It hides it sort of
deeper in the envelope.
So based only on that definition,
whereby recall that Google uses Get.
If I go to Google dot com slash
search question mark q equals cats--
and hopefully they're doing
better today than last time.
OK, so notice the URL here--
I have to stop pulling up Daily News.
So notice the URL here
has my search query.
Why might it not always
be a good thing to put
into the URL what the user typed in?
AUDIENCE: Cause it's like a password.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, if
it's your password,
you probably don't want
it showing up in the URL.
Because maybe someone
nosey walks by and can just
read your password off the URL.
But more compellingly, a lot of
browsers have autocomplete these days,
and they remember your history.
So it would be a little lame if
your little sibling, for instance,
could just click the little
arrow at the end of this window
and see every password
you've typed into websites.
You could imagine this not being good
for uploading content like photos.
Like, how do you put a photo in a URL?
That doesn't feel like it would
really work, though technically you
can encode it as text.
Credit card information
or anything else,
I mean anything resembling
something private or secure to you,
probably don't want
cluttering the URL bar
because it's going to get saved somehow.
When you use incognito mode though,
for instance, that kind of stuff
is thrown away.
But this is just bad practice to force
your users to use a mode like that.
So Post does not put it in there.
And so if Google used Post, which they
don't for their search page instead,
we would appear to be at this URL,
just slash search, no question
mark, no q, and no cats, but the
query can still be passed in.
It's just kind of, again,
deeper inside of the envelope.
So long story short,
I chose to do exactly
that just because with Frosh
IMs, because we don't really
need to be storing all of the
freshmen's names, and email addresses,
and dorms in people's
URL bars unnecessarily.
So input name equals
name, type equals text.
This is going to give me a text box,
just like q for Google, for someone
to type in their name.
Select-- it's kind of a weird name,
but what does a select element give you
visually on a screen, if you recall?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It's like a dropdown bar.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's a dropdown menu.
So all of the items in that menu are
going to be drawn from these Harvard
freshman dorms here.
And then down at the bottom of
this file, if I keep scrolling,
notice there's one other
input whose type is Submit.
And what does a input
whose type is Submit
look like on the screen, if you recall?
AUDIENCE: It's a button.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's just a button.
That's it.
And you can style it
to look differently,
but it's just a button by default. So
long story short, this web application
gives me a form via which frosh
can register for intramural sports.
And I can see this as follows--
if I go into Frosh IM0,
and I simply do Flask run, I'm
going to see my same URL as before,
but now a different application
is running on the same port.
Here's what it looks like.
It's super simple, super ugly, but
it does, indeed, have a text box.
It's got a dropdown.
And it's got a Register button.
And now with the world
suddenly got more interesting,
because now I have not just static
content, like "hello, world"
or "I am Mark."
I actually have something
interactive for the user to do.
And if he or she fills out this
form now, clicks Submit, two
or three weeks ago, we
just punted completely,
and we let Google handle
the user submission.
But now we have Python in a
programming language that can receive,
inside of the same envelope,
the user's query for cats
or the user's name and dorm.
And we can actually
do something with it.
So this program doesn't do
all that much with it yet.
If I go in here and zoom in, and I
register David from Matthews and click
Register, notice what happens.
I do end up, as promised,
at slash register.
And I'm told "You are
registered," well, not really.
And that's because this is version 0.
It actually doesn't do all that much.
What does it do?
Well, let's go back and
try to be less cooperative.
So I just reloaded the page.
It's still asking for my name and dorm.
You don't need to know that information.
I want to keep it private.
I just want to anonymously register
for a sport, whatever that would mean.
Register-- OK, I caught it.
Notice that the URL is
still slash register.
But I'm being yelled at for
not providing my name and dorm.
All right, so fine,
I'll give you my name.
But I don't want you to know where I
live, so I'm just going to say David--
Register.
And it's still catching that somehow.
So only when I actually give it a dorm
and a name, like David from Matthews,
and click Register, does it
actually pretend to register me.
So what does the logic look like?
In just English pseudocode, even
if you've never written Python,
what kind of pseudocode would be in
application.py for this application?
AUDIENCE: If there is no
text, provide error message.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect, if
there is no text provided,
provide this error message instead.
And so let's take a look
at how that's implemented.
In Frosh IM0, in
addition to my template,
I again had this application.py.
And let's see what's new
and what's different.
So first, this is mostly
the same as before.
I just added one other
thing in here, Request,
for reasons we'll see in a moment.
Here is the line of code
that says, hey, Python,
give me a web application called app.
Hey, Python, when the user visits
slash, render the template index.html.
That's how I got the form.
But this is the interesting part.
Let me zoom out slightly.
These lines of code are
a little more involved,
but let's do the one at a time.
This first line, nine,
is saying, hey, Python--
or specifically Flask--
when the user visits slash
register using the post
method, what do I want to call?
Just to be clear, what function?
AUDIENCE: Register?
DAVID MALAN: Register-- so
again, the only relationship
here, even though the syntax looks
a little cryptic, is this says,
hey, server, when the user
visits slash register,
call the function immediately
below it called Register.
And then what does that function do?
Well, here is the logic that you
proposed verbally a moment ago.
If not request dot form dot
get or not request dot form dot
get dorm, name and dorm, then
return failure.html, else
implicitly return success.html.
So the only part that's a little new
and different here is 11, line 11.
Because in C, you would have
to use the exclamation points.
You would have to use vertical
bars for Or So some of that
syntax is a little different.
But this works as follows--
there exists a function called Get that
is inside a special variable called
Form that is inside a special variable
called Request that I have access to,
because I imported it up here.
And that function, Get, checks
inside of the virtual envelope
for a field called Name that would
have been populated in the envelope
if a user typed his or her name.
And if it exists, it returns it,
quote-unquote, "David," quote-unquote,
"Maria," or whoever it is that's
registering, but if not, inverts it.
So if not a name, or if not a dorm,
go ahead and spit out failure.html.
So what does failure.html look like?
Well, failure.html just has
this hard-coded message,
"You must provide your name and dorm."
And now at the risk of introducing
one too many languages at a time here,
there is another one in here.
These funky curly
braces and percent signs
are what's called a templating language.
But before we explain what that
is, notice at the top of this file
is mention of another file, layout.html.
That
We've not seen this before.
In the past, we've just had full
and complete index.html files
or zuck.html files.
But what was true a moment ago
about index.html and zuck.html
from our last example?
Let me go ahead and
quickly open those again.
Index.html, recall looked like this.
And zuck.html looked like that.
What do you notice in
layman's terms about the two?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
is mostly the same.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, they're
almost identical, right?
They seem to differ
only in their titles,
obviously, and in the body's content.
But all the other
structure is identical.
And to be fair, there's
not that much in red there.
There's not too many tags.
But I mean, I literally, in front
of you, copied and pasted this.
And generally, that is already
a step in the wrong direction.
And so there's an opportunity here.
There's a problem to be solved.
And we've done this in the past, right?
In C, if you were to just
blindly copy and paste code
you need in multiple
places, that's kind of dumb.
It's kind of messy.
It's hard to maintain.
Rather, you should probably
be defining it as a function
that you call in multiple places.
Now this is not a programming
language, so there's
no comparable notion of a function.
But because it's a markup language
that just has hard-coded values,
you can think of this as kind
of being a template or a mold,
like put something here, and then
maybe here, put something else here.
So again, if you think
of the physical world
as having templates, or again,
like a mold into which you
pour specific values, this is
kind of what we're talking about.
And that is what layout.html
is in this Frosh IMs example.
I've not opened it until now, but
here is, somewhat cryptically,
an example of layout.html.
And notice, it's got the doc type.
It's got HTML head, title,
some other stuff up there body.
But then it has this placeholder.
And I'll admit it, the syntax
is sort of annoyingly cryptic,
but this is just saying
put something here.
And that's all.
What are you putting there?
Well, if I go back to failure.html,
notice that it works as follows.
Failure.html conceptually
extends this template.
It borrows that mold,
called layout.html.
And then notice the same keywords
here, block body and block.
This just means plug
this into that file.
And this allowed me to
break my habit quickly
of just copying and pasting everything,
even though the format of these files
is almost identical.
So if I go back now to
application.py, notice
that this program does spit out
either index.html or failure.html,
or success.html.
So it would have been pretty lame to
copy and paste my code three times.
That's why I took the time to create
a fourth file, layout.html, just
to factor out everything that's common.
And the upside of this, too,
means that all of these pages
structurally look the same.
And if I had like a
fancy logo on my website
and a nice brand to the
web site, all of my pages
would look the same except for a
message that changes in the middle,
say, of the page.
And so this, then, is Frosh IM0.
Any questions on how this now looks?
All right, so we have a couple
of other opportunities here.
I would propose that it would be kind
of interesting to actually remember
that the user has
registered, instead of just
pretending by spitting out a hard-coded
value, like "You are registered."
Well, not really, because I'm not
doing anything with their name or dorm.
So maybe we could start
storing that in memory
and see who is registered for the site.
It would be even cooler if, like in
my day way back when I implemented
the actual Frosh IMs website, you could
email someone when he or she registers
to confirm that they're registered.
Or better still, why don't we
actually save it to a mini database,
like a CSV file, that I, like
the person running Frosh IMs,
can actually open in Excel, or Numbers,
or Google Spreadsheets, or the like.
So before we to get to that, let's
take our five-minute break here.
And we'll come back and
solve exactly those problems.
So we are back.
And so I thought today
would be opportune,
since you might have been
wondering who Stelios
is who has been our example in
quite a few of our memory examples.
But visiting from Yale University today,
one of our head TAs there, Stelios.
STELIOS: Hi, everyone.
AUDIENCE: We love you!
[APPLAUSE]
STELIOS: Yale is on break,
so I said, why not come by?
Yeah, it's glad to see you.
I've been in here before many times.
It's a beautiful space.
And, yeah, come by and hi after lecture.
DAVID MALAN: So glad to have you.
Thank you, Stelios.
So, it was brought to
my attention, since I
wasn't focusing so much on my
logs in the terminal window, which
record all of the HTTP requests that
you get during a server running.
And this is a screenshot of my terminal
window from just a little bit ago.
And you'll recall that I visited
slash, and then I tried to register.
But in between there,
someone in the audience,
apparently, or on the internet,
tried to visit slash was up,
using Get in their browser.
I scrolled past a few other
inputs from the internet.
But the more shareable
ones were these here--
bro slash David and slash nice.
So that was the last one before
I killed the actual server.
And this is because, even though I'm
listening on a nonstandard port, 8080,
that domain name, I did share my
workspace publicly so that anyone could
access it while the server is running.
And if you happened to be
here physically or tuning
into a live stream,
it's obvious that I'm
advertising now publicly that port 8080
is where we've been spending our time.
But if we turn back now to Flask and
maybe minimize our logs moving forward,
let's consider how we can actually
now remember that users are logged in.
So in fact, let me go ahead and
demonstrate among today's examples,
Frosh IMs1, by running Flask run.
And then I'm going to go to
the same URL as before up here.
And we'll see this
time, that if I go ahead
and register as David from Matthews--
Register, notice now that instead
of just going to slash register,
I changed things a little bit.
And I'm going to slash
registrants, because there I
seem to have some HTML that
generates a bulleted list of whoever
has registered.
And so now let me go ahead here
and go back, perhaps, and register
let's say Maria from Apley Court--
Register.
And now we have two.
Moreover, if I just reload the page,
notice that this information persists.
So how is this actually working?
Well, let's go ahead and take a look
inside of application.py for Frosh IMs1
dot--
for Frosh IMs1.
So what do we have inside here?
So as before, I'm configuring
my app with a line like this,
like, hey, Flask, give me an app.
And then this, I claim,
is my registrants.
So this is just a comment in
Python, the hashtag registrants.
Students equals open bracket close
bracket represents what, though?
AUDIENCE: List.
DAVID MALAN: A list,
yeah, it's an empty list.
It's like an empty array.
But unlike in C, where
arrays can't grow or shrink,
in Python lists, which are
similar in spirit to an array,
can actually grow and
shrink dynamically.
So if you want an empty
one, you literally just
say, give me an empty one.
And then we'll figure out
the ultimate length later.
And so what's compelling
about this on line 7,
is that I have a variable
now called Students,
that's initialized to an empty list.
But it's now in the web
application's memory.
Because recall that when we
run Flask, I don't immediately
get back to my prompt.
The program doesn't
just run and then stop.
It just keeps listening,
and listening, listening,
waiting for more of these
envelopes to come in.
As such, as these various
functions get called--
index, or registrants,
as we'll see, or others--
they all have access to this global
variable, in this example, Students.
And so any of them can just put
more, and more, and more data
inside of Students.
And so here, if I go ahead and do this--
let me go ahead and show that
in the user visits slash,
we just return index.html.
Otherwise, if they visit
slash register, notice
that I've actually got some
interesting logic going on this time.
So if the user visits
slash register via Post--
and the only way thus far we've
seen that this could happen
is if the user does what?
How do you do something via Post?
AUDIENCE: You submit.
DAVID MALAN: You submit a form.
So Get, we humans can
simulate really easily.
If you just go to a URL, by
typing it into your browser,
you are by default using Get.
You can't do the same
nearly as easily for Post.
You only have access to the URL bar.
But if you have a web form,
like the one in index.html
with the Dorm dropdown
and the Name textbox,
you can submit via Post, which
is how this route can apply just
to that particular route.
So here on line 21, I'm saying,
hey, give me a variable called Name,
and put in it whatever the
user typed into the Name field.
Give me the same for the Dorm.
And so we notice, even if it
was a big dropdown of items,
the user is only selecting one of those.
And so we're getting
back just this one value.
And then here is a little
sort of Pythonic-type logic.
If not Name or not Dorm,
which is kind of nice.
It's a little terse, and it would
have looked strange a few weeks ago,
but now it looks better, perhaps,
than it would have in week one
in C. Then go ahead and
return failure.html.
If we're missing the name or the dorm.
Meanwhile, if that's not the case,
and we've not returned a failure,
go to do this, students dot
append and then this F-string.
So dot append, if you don't recall--
and you might not recall, because
I don't remember if we showed you--
is a method or function
built into a list that
allows you to literally append a
value to a list called Students.
So this is how, in
Python, you grow an array.
You just append to it and
the program will figure out
the length of this list.
This F-string just means here comes
a formatted string, similar in spirit
to print F, but the syntax
is a little different.
And the string I'm forming here
is so-and-so from such-and-such,
so Name from Dorm.
And the curly braces inside of
a format string or an F-string
means that we should plug those
variables into that F-string.
And then lastly, this is a new feature.
You can return not just
render template, you
can literally return
redirect and the path
to which you want to redirect the user.
And take a guess.
If you call redirect
slash registrants, what
does Flask, because Flask gave
us this redirect function,
put inside the envelope for us?
AUDIENCE: A new address.
DAVID MALAN: A new address--
and what kind of status code?
AUDIENCE: 301.
DAVID MALAN: Like a 301--
we saw that a couple of times ago.
301 means redirect the user.
So this function handles
all of that for us.
We don't have to know or worry about
how those status codes are actually
generated.
Meanwhile, slash registrants
is super simple, but it does
have one nice new feature.
So slash register, to which the form
submit, ultimately does all this stuff
and then redirects the user to
slash registrants, just because.
And it's kind of better
designed if this route is only
used for saving
information, and this route
is only used for seeing
information, because this way
you can visit it via Get as well.
Notice that I'm returning
registrants.html.
But I'm doing a little
something different this time.
What is different about line 16,
vis-a-vis all of our other render
template calls before?
AUDIENCE: Students equals.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, students equal
students, which is a little strange.
But we know that one of those values
is referring to this list here.
And so this is an example of
Python supporting named parameters.
It turns out that if you want
to pass data into a template,
you can put a comma and then the names
of the values you want to pass in.
Index didn't need this.
Failure didn't need this.
Success didn't need this,
because it's all hard-coded.
But Registrants does.
Based on what we saw, it's going to
generate a bulleted list of like David
from Matthews and
Maria from Apley Court.
So we kind of need to know
who those students are.
So, OK, registrants.html comma,
students shall be the named parameter.
And the value of it shall
be the list up here.
So the right-hand side
is a variable, or a value
that must exist in the current program.
And the left-hand side
is a variable that's
going to be inside of,
we'll see, registrants.html.
So let's open registrants.html,
because the other templates, honestly,
aren't that interesting.
Index.html is just like the web form
with the dorms and the name field.
Failure just says, sorry, you
must provide name and dorm.
Layout is just the similar
web structure as before.
So the only new file here, besides
the changes to application.py,
are in registrants.html.
This file, as before, extends a layout.
So that's the mold that it's using.
And it's going to fill in the
following block for the body.
So again, this is just specific
to the templating technique,
just to clean up the code.
But the real interesting stuff is here.
This is kind of sort of HTML,
but kind of sort of not.
So what does this look like?
AUDIENCE: Python code.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it kind
of looks like Python code.
And it's technically not.
And I realize this is this
awkward part in the semester,
maybe like most of the
semester, where we introduce
all these darned things at once.
But this is a language called Jinja--
J-I-N-J-A-- that is a
templating language.
And you'll see that word in
documentation and so forth.
It's a very lightweight language
for just displaying information.
It gives you some loops.
It gives you some conditions.
And it pretty much is Python code.
You can think of it that way, but
it's not necessarily identical.
So for now, you'll see by
example what we can do with it.
So here, we have a Jinja template
that says, "For student in students."
This is very Python-like.
So "For student in students"
means iterate over students,
and call each student
along the way "student."
So with this, I needed to call students,
because it's passed into my form.
This could be foo, or
bar, or S, or whatever.
It's just a loop.
And then you can perhaps
guess what this line does,
even though it's a little cryptic.
On line 7, I have some
kind of familiar HTML,
familiar only insofar as for a
few seconds a couple of weeks ago,
we showed you a bulleted list in HTML,
which had a bunch of Li-- list items.
But take a guess.
What is line 7 probably
doing, if you had
to guess, based on what the
output of this program was?
AUDIENCE: Print [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Printing what?
AUDIENCE: Printing the students.
DAVID MALAN: The
individual students-- so
remember that the Students list is
just a list of strings, so-and-so
from such-and-such, so-and-so
from such-and-such a place.
So, if we induce this kind of
loop, iterating over that variable.
And on each iteration, we spit out a
new link list item, a new list item,
like in other words, a new bullet, a
new bullet, a new bullet, each time
printing out just the
name of that value,
we're going to get a
bulleted list of students.
And sure enough, the
HTML might not be pretty
because it's being generated
this time by a human.
But this is the HTML.
If I view Chrome Source for
that page, notice that I've
got all this stuff from my layout.
Down here, meanwhile,
I've got ul and ul,
which I did hard-code into that file.
But these are not hard-coded anywhere.
They were dynamically generated.
And this is now really the
first evidence of, not just
the logic within our
Python-based web application,
but also the ability to generate
content back to the user.
And if I kept running
the server and kept
having people submit, and
register, and register,
that list would just get
longer, and longer, and longer.
And the proctor or whoever
is actually managing
the intramural sports can
actually look at that list
by going to slash
registrants and know whom
to contact, at least if we asked
for more personal information
like emails and the like.
So any questions then on this example?
All right, so it's in example 2,
where now we recreate the website
that pretty much I implemented
back in 1997 or 1998,
albeit in a different language,
that actually allowed freshmen
to register for intramurals.
And we can do that as follows.
If I go into Frosh IMs2,
and I do Flask run--
I'm going to now reload that app.
And now I'm asking for one other thing.
So I made the form a little bigger
by asking for an email address.
Because this time, I'm actually
going to try sending an email.
Let me go back over here to the file.
And let me minimize this to make room
for Frosh IMs2 application.py, which
does the following.
So I have some mention of password
here, but more on that in just a bit.
And notice that up here I have
a new import, not to mention OS.
Notice up here-- let's see.
Notice up here, we have import smtplib,
so SMTP, Simple Mail Transfer Protocol,
which happens to do with email.
And that's because this
example works as follows.
In slash, we just return
that template, index.html.
If instead you do register, notice
what actually happens this time.
And I want to move this up here.
There we go.
So now we have this file
here-- this method here--
that operates as follows.
If the user tries to register
via Post, call this function.
Get their name.
Get their email.
Get their dorm, and then just
a little bit of a sanity check
that's not complete now,
because I'm just asking,
like before, if not name or not dorm.
But how do I also make sure that this
user has given me their email address?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so if
not name, or not email,
or not dorm-- now I've improved
upon this example versus the last
by also checking for
their email address.
And if they don't provide
one of those, we say failure.
Otherwise, what is this line 23 do?
AUDIENCE: Sends its message?
DAVID MALAN: It sets a
message, a variable called
Message, equal to quote-unquote,
"You are registered."
The next line here is a
little cryptic, and you'd only
know this from reading
the documentation,
like I did when writing this example.
On the left-hand side I have
a variable called Server.
This time it's not a web
server, it's an email server,
to which I want to connect.
Specifically, I want to use
this library, called smtplib.
It's SMTP functionality,
Simple Mail Transfer Protocol,
to connect to an address that you
might not have explicitly seen before,
but you can probably guess whose server
I'm connecting to on TCP port 587.
Long story short, even though
most of us, if you use Gmail,
just go to Gmail.com,
and you start using it,
and it appears to be a port 80.
Underneath the hood, anytime
you compose a message
and click Send or send an
archive, what is happening
is code like this at Google.
They're connecting to their
own outgoing mail server,
called an SMTP server, which
happens to be this address.
They're connecting to it using TCP
port 587, because it's not a web page.
It's mail, so it has
its own unique number
that humans decided on years ago.
This line here, 25, start
tls, this turns on encryption
so that this way, theoretically,
no one between you
and Google can see the email that
you're sending out to their server.
And then I hard-coded a
few values, here which
wouldn't be best practice
in general, but this
is just for me to register
some first years for Frosh IMs.
So what happens next?
On line 26, this is the line.
According to this
library's documentation,
via which I can log in as username
jharvard@cs50.net, passing
in his password.
So recall a couple of
times ago, I think I
mentioned that there are these
environment variables, when
we talked about programs memory space.
Environment variables are like these
global values that aren't in your code
but you do have access to.
So this just says get
from the environment,
from somewhere in the
IDE, JHarvard's password.
So I don't have to hard-code it
and broadcast it on the internet.
Meanwhile, line 27 does kind
of what the function says.
This says, using this server, Gmail,
send mail from jharvard@cs50.net
to this email address with this message.
And this message, as you've noted,
is just, "You are registered."
And where does this email variable
come from, just to be clear?
To whom is this email going?
AUDIENCE: To the user.
AUDIENCE: The student.
DAVID MALAN: The student
who registered via the form,
because we got their
name, email, and dorm.
Assuming he or she typed in
a legitimate email address,
it's being passed to the second argument
to send mail, and then it's being sent.
And then lastly, render template
success.html, and voila.
So now you are about to experience
either one of the cooler demos
we've done in class or one of
the more embarrassing failures.
If you would like to play along at
home, go to tinyurl.com/fridaycs50.
That's a lot easier to remember.
Tinyurl.com/fridaycs50-- Enter, that
should redirect you via our old friend
HTTP 301, should put you at this form.
And then I will play along at home, too.
David from Malan, actually, I'm going
to tell it my address is John Harvard's.
He will be from, let's
say, Pennypacker--
Register, and registered really, which
hopefully you shall soon see, too.
And meanwhile, I get a security
alert in my Google accounts,
because everyone's using it.
But that's OK.
I am registered at JHarvard.
And, oh, my goodness,
all of these examples,
OK, and the errors that we'll soon see--
we'll soon explain--
so what did I just get?
If you, like me, check your mail
in some number of seconds from now,
you should see an email from
jharvard@cs50.net with the message,
"You are registered" that was sent
directly to me, or hopefully to you.
Now, at least two of you
will not get this message,
because according to my
bounced mail, three of you
have mistyped your email
addresses into the example.
And so they're bouncing back to me.
So if you don't get
it, simply try again.
So what actually happened here?
So I actually wrote code clearly, in
this case, that via application.py had
this route slash register that
didn't just save things in a variable
this time.
It actually tucked them up
into a special type of library
that actually knows how to send mail.
And this is literally what
I did back in the day.
It didn't occur to me--
actually, it might have
occurred to me, but I
didn't know in 1997 what a database
was or where we could actually
store the information.
So I'm pretty sure, the very
first version of registrations
online at Harvard for Frosh
IMs were to literally just send
the proctor an email, who was
responsible for that intramural sport.
And it was good enough.
They could just use their inbox
as essentially their database,
and know who had registered.
Eventually though, we were
able to improve upon this
and actually save things
in a lightweight database.
I still didn't know SQL, and I didn't
know how to do things more fancily.
But I didn't know what a CSV file was.
I had Microsoft Excel, or Numbers
more recently, on my computer,
so I can open up spreadsheets.
And so it turns out, that
if we instead look up
say Frosh IMs3, which is our
final version of the Frosh IMs
suite of examples, I actually
went ahead and did this.
In this version of the program--
it's a little cryptic,
but I figured this
out just by reading on Python's
documentation and how to use CSVs.
And I came up with the following.
So as before, on line 12,
if not name or not dorm--
so I've reverted to the
old syntax, because I'm not
using email address for this example--
then I go ahead and return failure.htlm.
But the new code here, instead
of email, is this functionality.
So here I have file, which
is a variable, gets stored--
gets the return value of Open.
So this is a function in Python that's
similar to fopen in C. They just
kind of clean up the name here.
It open a file called registrants.csv.
And what do you think the
quote-unquote "a" means?
We probably-- you didn't use "a."
You used a different letter in p-set 4.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: What's that?
AUDIENCE: R or W?
DAVID MALAN: We used R
or W for read or write.
Turns out a is a little different,
which makes sense in this case.
AUDIENCE: Append.
DAVID MALAN: OK, thank you.
OK, it's append.
And append make sense here because
write, by default, literally
overwrites the file.
It creates a new file.
Whereas, append literally does that.
It adds a line to the file,
a new line to the file, which
is good if you want to have more
than one person ultimately saved
in the file.
You want to remember
everyone else by appending.
So this says, hey, Python,
open the file in append mode,
and store it in a variable called File.
This is a line of code that uses
some syntax we didn't quite see in C,
but we're declaring a variable called
Writer using the CSV library, which
I've imported at the top of this
file, similar to importing the mail
library in the last one.
And it has a function called Writer
that I can pass in an open file.
And this is just a
special library that knows
how to put commas in between
values, knows how to save things,
knows how to escape things if
there's actually commas in your file,
and so forth.
And then this line is a little funky.
But it does use some building
blocks from earlier--
writer dot write row-- writer write row.
So this kind of does what it says.
This says, use the library to
write a row to the open file.
What you want to write?
Now if there's deliberately these
additional parentheses here,
turns out this function is
supposed to take a tuple.
A tuple is zero or more
values separated by commas,
which is kind of nice because
it's kind of similar in spirit
to a set of columns.
Like a tuple is something comma
something comma something.
That is exactly what we want to put in
a CSV, something comma something comma
something.
Because if you're unfamiliar, a CSV
is just a file where all of the values
are separated with commas.
And if you open it in Excel, or
Numbers, or Google Spreadsheets,
each of those commas demarcates a
barrier between various columns.
So this says, go ahead and
write a row to the CSV,
containing the student's
name and the students dorm.
And then close the file
and return Success.
So at the risk--
there's like a 30-second
internet delay, which
means we can keep this
clean for about 30 seconds.
Let me go ahead and run this example
here in Frosh IMs3 and do Flask run--
Enter.
And if you'd like to go ahead to my
same URL, tinyurl.com/fridaycs50,
that will take you back to a
slightly older version of the form,
no email address, so
make sure you hit reload.
And you should see just
this version, name and dorm.
And if I wrote the code
right, we should all
be able to register in a file
called registrants.csv in my IDE.
You're not going to get an
email this time, because we
ripped that functionality out.
But this Register page
claims that it's working.
So if you'd like, take
a moment to do that.
I'll go back to the IDE here.
Looks like a lot of registrations
coming in, so that's pretty cool.
These are the logs here.
And so you can see everyone visiting
the site and hitting Register.
That's actually a lot
of people registering.
That's pretty cool.
I'm going to briefly turn
off the screen this time
and see who has registered
by going into this directory.
This is-- OK, I'm going to go into
Frosh IMs3 is what I'm doing here.
I see registrants.csv.
OK, let's just scrub this.
[LAUGHTER]
OK, David Malan 2.0 registered, great.
All right, I'm going
to download this file.
I think it looks pretty clean.
Let me download this.
And I'll show you what I'm
doing in just a second.
But this is the best demo
ever, from what I can see.
All right, and let's make
sure I didn't miss this here.
Uh huh, OK, some of
you are just hitting--
Brandon was just hitting
Submit a lot, apparently.
All right, I don't think I'm
going to regret any of this.
OK, we're good.
All right, so what did I just do?
We're back.
So now that we've run everything
through the censors, what I've noticed
is that, oh, I have a registrants.csv
file in the same directory.
And that was what was getting
appended to each time.
Meanwhile, if I go
ahead and download this
file by doing registrants.csv
and then Download.
Or I could just open it in the IDE
to see the actual rows and columns.
Let me actually do that real quick.
So you'll see this file here.
But it's a little hard to see.
So I'm going to deliberately close
it, because I downloaded it earlier.
And I can actually open it in Excel.
And if in Excel I just expand my
columns, each of these columns
represents the gap between a comma.
Brandon was apparently trying to
make his name very big and bold,
but that doesn't work in CSV files.
Montreal is apparently the best.
A lot of first names--
more Brandon-- unknown, OK--
there is that one I
mentioned, someone's dad.
Maybe someone's dad is here today, OK.
All right, we, MTL is the Best, John
Harvard, John, Olivia, Batman, Kyle--
[LAUGHTER]
DAVID MALAN: OK, there's
Worthy of Wiggles--
now it's getting a little strange--
faces, buttface, OK,
that made it through.
I didn't notice.
David, I'm scared, OK.
[LAUGHTER]
So we finally have,
thanks to programming,
the ability to actually keep
some of this data around.
And so this ultimately
allows us to now start
making applications that
are truly interactive.
And they actually allow us to
store information and retrieve
that information, ultimately.
And it all reduces to some
of these simple paradigms.
And now, absolutely, there's a whole
bunch of cryptic syntax involved.
And there's some new ideas along
the way, things like tuples
and things like routes.
And I didn't use the word before,
technically this at sign denotes
something called a decorator.
But as with C, back in those
early days, keep in mind
that once you start
noticing these patterns,
even if you don't appreciate
everything or understand everything
from the get-go, you
can kind of iteratively
get more comfortable with the material.
If you kind of take on
faith that I don't really
remember how this works, but I know
that I have to do it now, that's fine.
Because if you understand
more of the stuff below it,
that'll solve the problem for
you and get the work done.
And as you get more at ease with this,
then can you start, through section,
and office hours, in
the p-set itself, start
to really understand
some of the nuances here
and how it relates or doesn't relate to
things we've seen in the past with C.
So where are we going with this?
Well, with problem set 6, we're going to
bridge these several worlds of the web,
and of Python, and
also of edit distance,
and dynamic programming from our
Yale lecture a couple of weeks back.
And if you're a little behind
on some of those topics,
or some of today's material wasn't quite
on the tip of your tongue, that's fine.
Do go back, though.
Because realize the past three lectures
really now culminate in problem set 6.
You will be challenged to
go back and re-implement
Mario, either the less or the more
comfy version, not in C, but in Python.
And odds are, you'll be struck
for at least two reasons.
One, odds are if you did solve it
successfully the first time around,
even if you're a little
rusty, odds are you
will solve it much more
quickly this time around,
even though it's a new language.
And you'll see what some idea
from C maps to some other idea
in Python, just like we did from Scratch
to see that same kind of transition.
Same thing for Cash or Credit,
same thing for Visionaire,
or Caesar, or Crack as well.
But the icing on the cake is then going
to be to not just write code in Python,
but write code in Python for a
web application that actually does
something graphical with a website.
So for instance, here we have the
more comfortable version of the staff
solution to Similarities,
one piece of problem set 6.
And you'll notice on
this web-based form,
I'm currently at
similarities.cs50.net/more.
Your URL, of course, will
be different, whether you do
the less comfy or more comfy as well.
But here we have a web form with
two strings waiting to be typed in,
two textboxes.
And now this form arguably looks
a lot prettier than the ones
I've been doing today.
And because the ones I've been
doing today had no what in them?
AUDIENCE: CSS.
DAVID MALAN: There
was no CSS whatsoever.
So what I was getting
were the pretty old, ugly,
1990s styles defaults that Chrome,
and IE, and Edge, and Firefox,
and Safari all give
me by default. But you
can use libraries out
there that allow you
to make your websites much prettier.
So long as you just understand
how to generate the markup,
you can let someone else style it
and take it that last mile for you.
So most of the aesthetics of what
you see here, the nice navigation
bar at the top, the font sizes,
the nice gray highlighting here,
the fact that this goes all
the way to the edge, the fact
that there's the same margin over
here as there is over here, the fact
that the button doesn't look as ugly
as it did before, all of that is CSS.
And we happen to be using
a library called Bootstrap,
which is a very popular library
that's got a lot of functionality,
like forms, to help
you style these things.
And if I, in this application, type
in a string like Harvard and then type
in a string like Yale and click
Score, what you will see here,
a little cryptically-- very cryptically
if you're not fully caught up
on our lecture from Yale--
is you see a matrix at the top here.
This is just a grid of rows and columns.
The top row of this
matrix says H-A-R-V-A-R-D,
so obviously the first word I typed in.
And on the y-axis it says Yale,
Y-A-L-E And what each of these numbers
represents is the cost, step-by-step,
of converting one string into another.
Now that in and of itself is
kind of a useless exercise,
but the number of steps to
convert one string into another
rather gives you an estimation of how
similar or how different strings are.
If there's very low cost to
change one string to another,
odds are they're really similar.
If it takes one step to
convert one word into another,
odds are they're identical
except for one character.
Or if the cost is really high,
like six, then it takes six steps
to convert Harvard into Yale.
And that kind of makes sense, because
they are really different words,
except for maybe the fact
that they have an A in common
that maybe we can reuse without
having to change that completely.
So edit distance is a technique that
can be solved very slowly and very
expensively in the naive way, using
essentially a couple of for loops,
where you iterate over one string,
you iterate over the other string.
And you just iteratively, or
rather by a bit of recursion,
try every possible change to the string.
Well, what if I delete
this and then add this?
What if I add this and delete this?
What if I just change this, and
then add this, and then delete this?
There are so many permutations
of adding, and deleting,
and editing characters, that it's
just a really slow problem, especially
when the strings get longer than these.
And so what you'll do,
if you choose to do
the more comfy version
of the problem set,
is you'll implement this
by a dynamic programming.
And this matrix up here
just remembers, just
stores, all of the temporary values that
I've so-called memoized along the way,
such that if you recall
from Benedict's lecture,
you just kind of work your way
from top left to bottom right
to get your final answer.
And the fact that that
number is relatively big,
6, means that Harvard is not very
similar to Yale, at least in terms
of its string comparison here.
I didn't realize the semantics of
that until I said that sentence.
So meanwhile-- oh, and then as an
aside, if you didn't notice already,
at the bottom here is kind of a log.
This just shows you, once
you've implemented the top here,
what it is that has to happen to
Harvard in order to turn it into Yale.
We have to delete an h,
delete this a, delete this r.
Then we have to change a letter
to y, change another letter to l,
and another letter to
e, and voila, Yale.
But notice, if we do something more
similar, like let's say, let's say,
suppose we do Mario from p-set
one and Maria from the heads team.
This is a much more similar
string, because it only takes
one step to convert one into the other.
And so the log is much smaller as well.
And so you get an
estimation of similarity.
But we can take this one step further
using different algorithms that
may or may not perform as well.
So here's the less comfy version of
the same problem, whereby now I'm
being asked for two files,
so not just two strings.
You can you do even
bigger files in this way,
because it's not quite as
expensive, and it's a lot easier
to show on the screen.
So I downloaded, or I whipped up a
couple of examples in advance here.
I have a file called hello.c,
which looks like this--
a little flashback from week 1.
And then I have another
file called hey.c,
which is identical except for
some word, like, hey comma world.
So I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead and
upload hello.c and hey.c.
Or I could just click these, and then
I could navigate through my hard drive
like you might on your Mac or PC.
But I'm just going to
drag and drop them.
And then I have three
choices of algorithms.
Because if you can think
about what a text file is,
I don't really know off the top of
my head how best to compare them.
I can probably tell you
if they're identical.
I can just use like a while
loop or a for loop in C
and iterate over every character in
the file and tell you True or False,
these files are identical.
But if there's a little difference, like
hey and hello, or maybe some spacing,
then I have different options.
So what if we compare
these files line by line?
Should most of the lines
in hello.c and hey.c
be similar or different, do you think?
AUDIENCE: Similar.
DAVID MALAN: Similar, except
for that one printf line.
So let's see what happens.
If I go ahead and choose compare lines
as my algorithm and click Compare,
I see highlighted in yellow, in the
user interface, the two programs left
and right, hello and hey, with all
of the identical lines highlighted.
So the fact that there is so much yellow
means, OK, these are pretty similar.
I'm not slapping a value on
it, in this particular case.
But I certainly could say that it's
all but one of the lines are in common
and ascribe it that kind of score.
Meanwhile, sentences doesn't
necessarily make sense.
But if this were an essay, or if you're
familiar with sites like Turnitin
and so forth, like an English essay,
I could upload two different essays
and see how many sentences
do they have in common.
So that even if one sentence is
up here and another is down here,
because the students used
the same quotes or whatnot,
I can at least find those
by breaking the text up
based on periods in an
English sentence, which don't
exist in quite the same way in code.
But what about substrings?
Substrings is a more
fancy term just to say
a portion of a string of length
one, or two, or three, or four.
And here I have a textbox
where I can configure this.
So if I want to look for
common substrings of length 10,
that would be a pretty long
string of text that's in both.
Compare, and indeed, there's
a lot of stretches of 10
because they're all so similar.
If I instead change this to one,
looking for all the common characters,
you'll see that almost everything is in
common, except for what missing letter?
AUDIENCE: Y.
DAVID MALAN: Y-- so there's going
to be a couple of different ways you
can implement this, actually
many different ways that you
can implement each of these algorithms.
But what's key is that
by using Python, you're
going to have a lot more
tools at your disposal.
You're going to have different
data types like Lists, and Sets,
and Dictionaries, if
you want to use them.
And what you're not going to have
to do, as you might have in C,
is actually parse out these
characters individually.
Rather, if you want to split
up a file based on its lines,
just call a function for that.
If you want to actually
grab all of the whitespace,
just call a function for that.
If you want to take a
substring of a certain length,
just use the right
Python syntax for that.
And so once you've taken this
sort of scaffolding approach
of porting some of your
C problems to Python,
you'll culminate in
implementing either of these.
We'll wrap a bit earlier today.
I'll stick around for questions.
Best of luck, and see you next time.