[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50, and this is lecture three.
And today, the goal is to be a lot
more algorithmic than code-oriented,
and to really kind of come back to
where we started in lecture zero,
when we talked about computational
thinking, and algorithms.
Because now you have a
few weeks under your belt,
and you have a few new tools, and
hopefully skills, under your belt,
even though odds are,
you're still getting
comfortable with some of those skills.
And so let's look, then,
at this piece of hardware
that we talked about a couple times.
And this is an example of what?
AUDIENCE: Memory.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, memory,
or RAM, random access memory.
And this happens to be
pretty big on the screen,
but it's actually pretty
small, if you were
to find it in your Mac, or PC, in
your laptop, or some other device.
And this is just memory.
And so, memory is places you can store
information-- numbers and characters
and strings, and bigger things still.
And recall that if you want to use
this memory, you need to address it.
You need to put something
in particular locations.
And we're going to start doing this
all the more So in particular, there's
at least, like, five--
four black chips on here, which is
actually where the zeros and ones are
stored, in the green circuit board.
And little gold connectors
you see on the screen,
too-- that just allows
all of those black chips
to intercommunicate, ultimately, and
for the zeros and ones to move around.
But if we zoom in on just
one of these chips of memory,
arbitrarily, and then zoom in here, you
can think of this, wonderfully enough,
as a rectangle.
Could be any shape, certainly, but
if we think about it as a rectangle,
we can divide this chip of
memory up into a grid, like this.
Completely arbitrary how I've
drawn this, but the fact, now,
that I have a whole
bunch of small boxes--
you can start to think of this
as being one byte, and then
another byte, and then another byte.
And I coincidentally wrote eight bytes
across, but it could be any number.
It doesn't really matter.
And so, you can start to
think about these bytes
as having specific locations,
or numbers, or addresses,
as we're going to start calling them.
So if I zoom in on the
top of this, you could
start to think of the top
left as being byte number 0,
because computer
scientists generally start
counting at zero, and then byte 1,
and 2, and 3, and 4, and dot dot dot.
And then, just as a refresher, in
a typical Mac or PC these days,
how much RAM, or memory,
would you typically have?
AUDIENCE: Four?
DAVID MALAN: Four what?
AUDIENCE: Four gigabytes.
DAVID MALAN: Four gigabytes.
And giga means billion, so
that's four billion bytes.
And maybe you have a little less,
maybe you have a little more,
but on the order of billions of bytes.
So we're only scratching the surface
of just how much storage there is,
and how many numbers and
characters you can store.
But the point is that we can address
them, in some way-- zero, one, two,
and so forth.
So this is how we stored
Stelios' name in memory.
Recall, this was an
example last time, where
we needed to put the characters
of his name somewhere.
And so we actually put
the S, and then the T,
and then so forth, starting at
the leftmost location on forward.
But we also put something else.
It's not sufficient just to put
the letters of his name in memory.
What else did we have to do?
AUDIENCE: Put a zero in there?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, the zero command,
or more specifically, the zero byte,
or the so-called null byte--
N-U-L. And it's
represented as backslash 0.
Because if you were just
to type a normal zero,
that would technically be a
character from your keyboard.
It looks like a number, but it's
technically a character, a char.
And so backslash zero literally means
8-0 bits in that byte's location.
OK.
So now that we have this
ability to represent Stelios
with a sequence of characters,
null-terminated at the end,
we don't really need to worry
about the hardware anymore.
Right?
We can abstract away from that
just as we did in week zero,
and not worry about how those
zeros and ones are stored.
We can just trust that
they are, somehow.
And so we can abstract
away, and just start
thinking about it as a sequence,
or a grid, of letters like this.
But that backslash zero
is important, because it
is the only way that this
language we're currently using,
C, knows where strings end.
If you didn't have that, it
would-- printf, for instance,
might just keep printing all of the
contents, all four gigabytes, of memory
that your computer has, no matter
what those characters actually are.
And then, of course, you couldn't
distinguish Stelios' name from Maria,
or someone else altogether in memory.
So, let me go ahead and open up the
IDE, just to demonstrate now what
you can do with this kind of knowledge.
Suppose I wanted to write
a program that allows
me to let a user type
in his or her name,
and then I just want to print
out his or her initials.
And for simplicity, I'm going to
assume that the person's initials,
or whatever the capitalized letters
are, in the input they type.
So, I have to be a little nit-picky,
and type in my name properly.
But with that said, let me
go ahead and whip this up.
So, I'm going to save
this as initials.c.
Just out of habit, I'm going to
start by including the CS50 library,
because I'm going to want to
get a string from the user.
I'm going to go ahead and
include standard io.h, so that I
can print something to the screen.
And we'll decide later
if we need anything more.
I don't need any command line arguments
for the purpose of this program,
so I'm going to go back to our old
version of main, where you just
specify void-- no argc, no argv.
And then here, let me go ahead
and declare a string called s,
and get a name from the user,
as with, "name," and get string.
And then, what do I
want to do after this?
I want to go ahead and iterate over
the characters in the user's name,
and print them out only
if they're uppercase.
But you know what, rather
than just print them out,
you know what I want to do?
I actually want to create a new string,
myself, containing the user's initials.
So, I don't want to go ahead
and just print out, with percent
c, one character after
the other-- rather, I
want to go ahead and store the user's
actual initials in a new string,
so that I've got one
string for their name,
and one string for their initials.
And, ladies and gentlemen, Ian.
SPEAKER 2: Sorry for the video glitches.
DAVID MALAN: Thanks.
All right.
So, to be ever more clear, let
me go ahead and rename this
to name, literally, and then I want
to have a string for their initials.
But we know what a string
is, as of last time.
It's really just a
sequence of characters.
And a sequence really has
another name in programming.
What is another synonym we've
used for a sequence of something?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: An array.
An array is that data
structure we had when we
started using square bracket notation.
So, if I actually kind of roll this
back and break the abstraction,
if you will-- don't think
about it as a string.
What is a string?
It's a sequence of characters.
Technically, I could say char,
and then I could say initials,
and then I can specify
however many letters I
want to support in a human's initials.
And by-- assuming we have a first name,
maybe a middle name, and a last name,
three characters should do it.
Three characters.
So, David J. Malan,
DJM, three characters.
Is that enough chars?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: I'm hesitating,
because it doesn't--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: It's not, but why?
AUDIENCE: You need for
the null character.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So if we want to terminate even my
initials-- which isn't technically
a word, but it's
certainly a string, it's
a sequence of characters--
we need a fourth character,
or we need to anticipate
a fourth character,
so that whatever we put in the
computer's memory is technically,
in my case-- like, D-J-M backslash 0.
You need that fourth byte.
Otherwise you do not have room
to actually terminate the string.
So, now, even though this
doesn't look like a string,
insofar as I'm not saying the
word string, it really is.
It's a sequence of characters of size
four that I can put characters in.
Now, what are the characters in this
array, by default, have we said?
When you just declare a variable
of some size, what values go in it?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Sometimes
zeros, but generally,
what's the better rule of thumb?
AUDIENCE: You don't know.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, you don't know.
It's so-called garbage values.
Nothing-- you should not trust
the value of a variable, generally
speaking, unless you yourself have
put the value there, as by storing it,
with the assignment operator, or
by manually typing it in yourself.
So, just to be clear,
if I wanted this program
to be kind of useless for anyone except
myself, I could actually do this--
I could go ahead and do--
initials, bracket 0, get "d",
initials, bracket 1, get "j",
and then finally initials,
bracket 2, get "m".
And then lastly, and this is the
thing you might forget sometimes,
you actually need to do
the backslash zero there.
But of course, this
is not at all dynamic.
But I have, in this
these lines of code now,
created a new string called initials.
It's of length-- it's of
human length three, DJM,
but the computer is actually
using 4 bytes to store it.
But this is not the
point of the exercise,
because we already asked the
user for his or her name.
I need to now figure what that is.
So just logically, or
algorithmically, if you will,
what process could we use, given a
name like David J. Malan, or Brian Yu,
or anyone else's name--
how could we look at
that input and figure out
what the user's initials are?
What's the thought process?
Let me go a little farther back.
So, David J. Malan, or any other name.
What's the process?
What do you think?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, good!
So, iterate with a for loop over
the letters in the name-- and you've
done that before, or in
the process of doing that,
for something like caesar
or vigenere, most likely.
And then you can use
something like is upper,
or you can even do asciimath, like we
did a while ago, to actually determine,
is it in the range of A to
Z capitals on both ends?
So we have a couple of options.
So, let me try to convert that to code.
Let me get rid of the
hard-coded name, which
is just kind of nonsensical,
but demonstrative of how
we could store arbitrary characters.
And now let me do this.
For int i get 0, i is less than the
string length of name, i plus plus--
and then I'm going to
do something like this.
If the i-th character character
in name is an uppercase letter--
and I'm going to use a function that
you might not have used yourself,
but recall that it does exist--
is upper will return, essentially, true
or false, this is an uppercase letter--
so, if this is uppercase, I'm
going to go ahead and do what?
Well, the story is not quite complete.
It's not enough to just
iterate over the names and--
the letters in the name--
we now need to decide where to put the
first capitalized letter that we find.
It's obviously going to
go in the initials array,
but what more do I need to
add to my code to know where,
in this block of four characters,
to put the first character, D,
in the case of my name?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] initials i?
DAVID MALAN: Initials i.
OK, so if I do that--
good thought.
So let's do, initials,
bracket i, gets name bracket
i-- that would seem to put
the i-th character of name
at the -th location in initials, which
at the moment is perfectly correct,
because i is 0.
And if I typed in David J. Malan,
D is at the zeroth location.
So, we're good.
But there's going to be a bug here.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] continue to the
name, then you'll have less slots.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
I is going to continue marching
forward, one character at a time,
through the entire name of the
user, but you only want to index--
you don't want to keep doing that
same amount in the initials array,
because again, the
initials is much smaller.
So even as i moves
through the user's name,
you want to take baby steps, so
to speak, through the initials.
So, how can we solve this?
I can't use i, it would seem.
AUDIENCE: You could use a
variable that's like a [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, great.
Let's do that.
We need another variable.
So, I could put this in
a few different places,
but I'm going to go ahead
and put it here for now.
So, int counter gets zero--
I'm just initializing
my counter to zero--
and then as soon as I won't
find an uppercase letter,
I think I want to do this?
Put it at whatever the
value of counter is?
And then there's one more step.
What do I need to do once I, yeah,
put it at the counter location?
AUDIENCE: Increment counter by one.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Increment counter by one.
So, I can do this in a few ways.
I can do it very literally-- counter
gets counter plus one, semi-colon.
It's a little annoying to type.
You could do plus equals one,
which is slightly more succinct.
Or, the ever-prettier, plus plus,
which achieves the same result.
Fewer characters, same
exact result, in this case.
OK, so now, I think we have
a for loop that iterates
over all the letters in the name.
If it's an uppercase letter, it stores
that letter, and only that letter,
in the initials array,
and then increments
counter so that the next
letter is going to go
at the next location
in the initials array.
So, if all that seems to be correct--
ultimately, I want to do this--
I want to go ahead and print out
percent s, backslash n, initials.
I want to just print
the user's initials.
But there's one key step in this
blank line that I should not forget.
What's the very last thing I need to do?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: You need to print
a null character [INAUDIBLE]
put a null character at
the end of the [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
I need to put a null character
at the end of the array.
So, how do I do that?
Well, I have the syntax, and I think--
you know, I want to say, end of array--
but how can I do that?
What values should I put here?
Yeah.
DAVID MALAN: The string length name?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I could do
strlen of name, well, not of name--
AUDIENCE: Of the initials.
DAVID MALAN: The initials, but now, you
kind of got me in a circular argument,
because I'm trying to--
it's kind of a catch-22 now.
I am trying to store a backslash
n at the end of the string.
But recall from last
time, the way strlen
knows where the end of the string
is, is by putting the backslash 0.
So, it's not there yet.
So we can't use strlen.
But, we already have,
I think, the solution--
AUDIENCE: Can't you
just put initials four?
[INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So, we could absolutely
do that, or almost that.
It's not quite four.
One tweak here, yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: In back, yeah?
DAVID MALAN: OK, good.
So, actually-- so, counter--
is, yeah.
Spoiler, counter is
going to be the answer.
But let me just fix this one bug here.
Four was the right
intuition, but remember,
if you have four characters possible,
it's 0, 1, 2, 3, is the very last one.
So, we needed to fix that to 3.
But even more general would be to put
counter, because the value of counter
is literally the length of the string
we just read into the initials.
And so if we want to
terminate that string,
we already know how many
characters we've counted up.
And in fact, it would technically be
wrong to just blindly put backslash
zero only at the very end
of these four characters.
Why?
In what situation would that
be-- logic be incorrect?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: If someone has
more than three initials.
DAVID MALAN: If they have
more than three initials,
we really have a problem, because
we don't have space for anything
beyond three actual letters
and a null terminator.
And there's another
problem, potentially.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: If they don't
have a middle name?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, if they
don't have a middle name,
there's going to be, only maybe two
letters, first name and last name.
And so, you're putting
the backslash zero
at the end of your array, which is good.
But what's going to be that third
value, that second to last value,
in the array?
AUDIENCE: A garbage value.
It's just garbage, so to speak.
And so it could be some
funky character, you
might get weird symbols on
the screen-- you don't know,
because it's just incorrect.
The backslash zero has to go
at the very end of the string.
So, let me go ahead, and if I've
made no syntax errors here--
let me go ahead now and save this,
and go ahead and do make initials--
OK, so, hmm.
Implicitly declaring library function
strlen with type unsigned long.
So, there's a lot of words, only some of
which I kind of recognize immediately.
I could run this through help50,
which should be your first instinct,
on your own or in office hours.
But let's see if we can't tease
apart what the error actually is.
What did I forget to do?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Uh, [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I needed the
string library, which now I'll
start to get in the habit of more.
Anytime I'm using strlen, just
try to remember to use string,
otherwise you'll see that
error message again and again.
Maybe there's more
errors, but I'm not sure,
so I'm going to go ahead and just
recompile, because again, you
might have more errors on the screen
than you actually have in reality.
But there is indeed one more.
So, similar error, but
different function.
Implicit declaration
of function is upper.
So that's, again, same mistake.
I've forgotten something.
Anyone recall?
This one's a little more--
less common, I would say.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: You need the
character type library.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, the character
type, or C type, library.
So again, you'd only know
this by checking the [? man ?]
page, so to speak, or
reference.cs50.net,
or checking your notes,
or whatnot, or Google.
And so that's fine.
It happens to be in Ctype.h.
Now, let me go ahead and recompile.
Seems to work, so, initials-- let me
go ahead now and type David J. Malan,
enter-- seems to work.
Let me try a corner case, like Rob
Bowden, without his middle name.
RB.
And so, it seems to work.
This is not a rigorous testing
process, but let's trust that we did
at least get the fundamentals right.
But the key here is that we broke
this abstraction, so to speak,
of what a string is.
Because if you understand
that, well, a string is just
a sequence of characters, and hey, a
string must end with a backslash zero,
you can do that yourself.
And this is what you can do in C.
You can put characters anywhere
you want in memory, you can put
numbers anywhere you want in memory.
And this ultimately gives you
a lot of power and flexibility,
but also, as you'll soon see, a
lot of opportunities for bugs,
with this power.
All right, any questions
on that particular example?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Can you explain
the initials counter?
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
Let's explain the initials
counter, which is used here,
and is declared up here.
So, we essentially want to
keep track of two locations.
If my name is sort of of this length,
I'm going to start at the first
character, D, and with i, iterate
from D-A-V-I-D, space, and so forth.
So, that one just kind of
marches on, one step at a time.
The initials array, meanwhile,
is another chunk of memory.
It's of size four, somewhere
else in that green silicon chip,
with all those black chips on it.
And we want to move through it
more slowly, because we only
want to move to the next
location in the initials array
once we've put a capital letter in it.
And that's going to be
less frequent, presumably,
unless the user typed in all caps.
So, in order to achieve that,
we need a second variable.
And you proposed that we use
a variable called counter.
But we could have called
it j, or something else.
And so, the counter is
initialized to zero,
and it is incremented here any
time we encounter a capital letter.
So, it has the effect of literally
counting the capital letters
in someone's name: D, J, M. And so it
should be 3, at the end of those loops.
And that's perfect, because
as we realized earlier,
3 happens to be the correct location
for where you put the backslash 0, even
though it wants to go in the
fourth location, the address of it,
or the location is technically 3.
So, we sort of solve multiple
problems at once, in this way.
Good question.
Other questions?
All right.
So.
With that said, let's not worry
as much about that low-level kind
of implementation, and consider what
more we can do with these things
called arrays.
If we start to get rid of
the addresses, and just
know that we have sequence of
characters, or anything else in memory,
and really, at the end of
the day, we have the ability
to lay things out
contiguously in memory.
Back to back to back to back, like this.
So, here are, then, eight boxes,
inside of which we can put anything.
But we've kind of been cheating
as humans for some time.
When we had Stelios' name on the
screen, all of us in this room
just kind of glance up, and you kind of
absorb his name all in one fell swoop.
But it turns out that computers are not
quite as intuitive, or as all-seeing
as we are, where we can sort of
take in the whole room, visually.
A computer can only look
at one thing at a time.
And so, a better metaphor
than a box like this
for the locations that you
have in your computer's memory
would really be like
eight lockers in a school,
where a computer, in order to look
at the value in any of those boxes,
actually has to do a bit of work and
open the door to see what's inside.
And you cannot, therefore, see all
eight locations simultaneously.
So, this is going to have very real
world implications, because now,
if we want to start checking
the length of a string,
or counting the number of things in
an array, or moving things around,
we're going to have to
do one thing at a time.
Whereas we humans might
just kind of look at it
and say, oh, sort these
numbers in some intuitive way.
And that actually is a good segue
to a very different problem,
which is that of sorting values.
So, for this, we have, say, the
equivalent of seven lockers,
up here now.
And behind these doors, so to
speak, is a whole bunch of numbers.
So we'll transition away
from characters and strings,
and just generalize it to
numbers, because they're
convenient to work with, and we have
so many of them at our disposal.
But I'd like to find one
number in particular.
So, suppose that a computer were
storing an array of numbers,
a whole bunch of integers,
back to back to back to back.
Here's what they might look like.
The doors are closed, though, so we
need an algorithm for finding a number,
because a computer can't just look at
it and say, there's your number there.
The computer has to be
more methodical, probably
going from left to right, from right
to left, starting in the middle,
randomly opening them.
We need an algorithm.
So, for that-- could we
get one brave volunteer?
OK, come on down.
What's your name?
CHRISSY: Chrissy.
DAVID MALAN: Kristen?
DAVID MALAN: Chrissy.
Come on down, over this way.
All right, so Chrissy, all you know
is that there are seven doors--
nice to meet you--
here on the screen.
And using your finger, you should be
able to just touch a door to open,
or unlock it, and we'll see what it is.
And I would like you
to find the number 50.
Dammit.
[LAUGHTER]
Very good!
[APPLAUSE]
I feel-- we need a better prize
than a stress ball for that.
But very nicely done.
And let me ask you, if we can-- if
you don't mind me putting the mic
in your hand--
here you go.
So, what was your amazing
algorithm for finding 50?
CHRISSY: I just clicked on it.
DAVID MALAN: OK, that's great.
CHRISSY: It looks nice.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So, you-- OK.
So, good.
So, wonderfully effective.
Let me go ahead and reveal--
actually, let's do this.
So, here's where you could have
gone wrong any number of places.
And let me ask the audience
before we try one other example.
What strikes you about these numbers?
Anything in particular?
AUDIENCE: They're unordered.
DAVID MALAN: They're all in order?
AUDIENCE: Unordered.
DAVID MALAN: Unordered.
Kind of random.
Although, the very astute
might notice something.
Or, someone who watches too much TV.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: They're the numbers from Lost.
DAVID MALAN: Yes, thank you.
The two of us watch a lot of Lost.
So-- plus we had a seventh
number, so we added ours.
So, they are actually in random order.
I just kind of shuffled
them arbitrarily.
They're not sorted from
smallest to biggest,
they're not sorted from
biggest to smallest.
There's really no pattern, because
I really just did shuffle them up.
And that's problematic, because even
though Chrissy got lucky, finding 50--
was just so good at finding 50--
it might be hard to replicate
that algorithm and find it
every time, unless you
know a little something
about the numbers behind the doors.
And so, we do know that
in this next example.
So, in this next example, there
are still seven doors, and still
the same seven numbers,
but now they're sorted.
And knowing that, does
that change your approach?
CHRISSY: Uh, well, I guess if they're
sorted, like, lowest to highest,
then it would, because I would
know it's closer to the end.
But if I don't know
how it's sorted, then--
I guess I wouldn't really know.
DAVID MALAN: OK, good.
So let me stipulate they're
sorted from smallest to biggest,
and let me propose that you,
again, find us the number 50.
Yeah, this is not working out very well.
That is very well done.
OK, so, congratulations.
[APPLAUSE]
So, you'll see-- thank you.
So, you'll see just
how much more efficient
her second algorithm was, when
she leveraged that information.
But in all seriousness, you
could do better, especially
for very large datasets, if you
know something about the data.
If you know that these
numbers are sorted,
you could, as Chrissy did very
intuitively and very correctly,
go to the very end, knowing
that that's the biggest number,
it's probably all the way on the right.
If she didn't know that, and just
knew that the numbers were sorted,
and did not know if 50 was a
small number, a medium number,
the largest number-- just it
was a number behind doors.
What would a smart strategy be,
given that lesser information?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
halfway, and then if it's
greater, you move it to the
right, if it's less, move it left.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, we
can try that same divide
and conquer approach we did in the
very first class, with the phone book,
right?
Where we looked roughly
in the middle, because we
know that the Ms, give or
take, would be in the middle.
And then if the--
we're looking for Mike Smith,
whose name starts with an S,
we know that he would be to the right,
and so we would go to the right,
and then to divide the problem--
[LAUGHTER] Today is not going very well.
So, we would divide and conquer
the problem again and again.
And we can do that here.
Even though it's not quite as
visually engaging as a phone book,
you can kind of go to the middle.
And if Chrissy had opened
that middle door, and seen 16,
you would know-- what?
And actually, I can recreate this.
I'm just going to refresh the screen.
So in this case, we have the same doors.
I know 50's somewhere, and I don't
know how-- where it is, but 16.
Now I know it's to the
right, as you propose.
So, now I can essentially eliminate all
these doors, not even worry about them.
And indeed, if I open
them, we can confirm
that I don't need to waste any
time actually searching them.
Now I've got three doors.
What would you propose we do next?
AUDIENCE: Go in the middle again?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, go
in the middle again.
So here, 42 is a great answer, but
it's not the one we're looking for.
And indeed, we can throw
this half of the problem
away, and finally search the right
half, which now has been whittled down
to one, and then we would find 50.
And if I can reconstruct
what would have been
a great history, in the first
example, how well might Chrissy
have done theoretically, or if we
did this exercise again and again
and again, with the first example.
If you don't know anything
about the numbers,
you can get lucky, as one might
by just choosing a door and, wow,
that happens to be the number.
But that's not going to happen
all the time, most likely.
And so you might have to just start,
you know, maybe at the beginning-- no--
no-- no.
Maybe you can get clever
and skip ahead-- no--
no-- OK, eventually, you will
find it, if it's actually there.
But if you don't know anything about
the numbers, the best you can do
is what's called brute force.
Just brute force your way
through the possibilities
until you find the answer.
But in the worst case,
how many doors might I
have to open to find the number
50, if I knew nothing about them?
AUDIENCE: All seven.
DAVID MALAN: Yes, all seven.
Right?
If n is the number of doors, it
might take me as many as n steps.
In this case, it was like
n minus one, or six steps.
But in Chrissy's case, clearly,
there's a really exciting lower bound,
because if you do get lucky, it
might only take you one step.
So, that's an interesting
range to consider.
The solution to your problem
might take one step, or n steps,
or any number in between.
But the binary search that you
proposed in the second approach, where
you divide and conquer--
recall that when we
did that in the past,
we had a very nice shape to the
curve that we drew that described
the efficiency of that algorithm.
And we'll come back to that before long.
But let's just, for clarity, formalize
just what these two algorithms are.
If I start from the left and go
right, or start from the right
and go left, following a line,
we would call that linear search.
And it can be written
in any number of ways.
I came up with this pseudo code,
but again, any reasonable person
could come up with an alternative one
and say it, too, is linear search.
These are not official definitions.
And I wrote it as follows.
For each element in array, if
the element you're looking for,
return true.
So, this is a very concise way of
saying, for each element in the array,
just look at it from left
to right, or right to left.
If it's the one you're
looking for, return true.
I found the number 50, or
whatever it actually is.
Otherwise, return false at the very end.
And notice the indentation.
I un-indented it because only as the
very, very last step do I return false,
if none of my iterations through
the loop actually return true.
So, that would be linear search.
Binary search, you have to be a little
more verbose to explain it, perhaps.
And there's many different
ways to write this out,
but this is very similar
in spirit to something
we saw before, with Mike
Smith and the phone book.
So if we go ahead and look at
the middle of the sorted array,
just as you proposed, and if the element
you're looking for is right there,
go ahead and return true.
I found 50.
I got lucky, it was dead center
in the middle of my array,
in one particular
running of this program.
Else, if the element is to the left,
search the left half of the array.
Else, if it's to the right, search
the right half of the array.
Otherwise, return false, because
it's presumably not there.
So, this would be binary search.
And even though it's more
lines of code, or pseudo code,
it arguably should be
a little faster, right?
Because of that dividing and conquering,
and throwing half, half, half, half,
half, half of the
problem away, the problem
gets smaller much, much more quickly.
All right.
So with that said, it seems
to be a very good thing
that having things sorted for you is a
very powerful ingredient to a problem.
Right?
It takes more work-- should
have taken Chrissy more work;
would take all of us,
in general, more work
to find a number using linear
search than by using binary search.
Much like it would have taken me forever
to find Mike Smith flipping one phone
page at a time, versus
using divide and conquer,
where I found him much more quickly by
dividing the problem in half, and half,
and half again.
So, that invites the question,
how do you get something sorted?
Well, let me go ahead and
pull up these things, which
we happen not to use in this
class, but elsewhere on campus,
you might have these blue books.
And at exam time, you might
write your name, and the class,
and all that on them.
And we've kind of simplified, so, this
is a person whose last name starts
with A, last name--
a person's name starts with
B, C, and all the way to Z.
But suppose that people
finish at different times
during the exam, and of course,
when you're in the science center
or wherever, everyone just
starts handing them in,
and they kind of come
in like this, and then
the TFs at the front of
the room, or professor,
has to actually sort
through these values.
Well, what's this algorithm
going to be that we actually use?
If you've got a pile of exam
books like this, all of them
have a letter associated with them,
how would we go about sorting these?
What do I do?
AUDIENCE: Compare two at a time.
DAVID MALAN: Compare two at a time?
OK, so let me go ahead
and pick up a couple here.
And since I'm the only
one that can see them,
you should be able to see them on the
overhead, thanks to Ian and Scully.
So, P and H, so, H goes
before P, alphabetically.
All right, now what do I do?
Pick up another two?
AUDIENCE: Pick up one.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so
maybe just pick up one,
and I happened to get N, so,
that goes in between H and P.
So I can kind of slide it in.
Now I picked up G. That
goes before H. Now I
picked up another one, E.
That goes before G. So,
it's actually getting kind of easy.
Uh-oh, U-- this goes
at the end, after P.
And so, I can keep grabbing
one at a time, F in this case,
and then kind of insert it
into its appropriate location.
And we won't do this the whole way,
because it's going to get tedious,
and eventually I'm going to embarrass
myself by getting one of the letters
wrong.
But that's an algorithm, right?
For each book in the pile,
pick it up, compare it
to all of the elements
you're already holding,
and insert it into the
appropriate location.
And we can actually call
that something, and that's
something called insertion sort, insofar
as the emphasis of the algorithm is--
thank you-- on inserting
letters, in this case,
into their appropriate location.
So, with that said, are
there other ways than that?
Let's go ahead, here-- and we have
enough stress balls to do it with just
one more human demo here,
beyond these books--
these numbers here.
Suppose we wanted to sort these.
I have eight stress balls,
eight pieces of paper--
could we get eight other volunteers?
So, yes, right and back, two three--
let's go farther back-- four.
Can I get farther back?
Five, six, seven, and eight.
Come on up.
Ah, next time.
Next time.
All right, come on down.
OK.
What's your name?
JERRY: Jerry.
DAVID MALAN: Jerry.
OK, If you want to go ahead and
step in front of a board there.
ARMAH: [? Armah. ?]
DAVID MALAN: [? Armah, ?] David.
CHRIS: Chris.
DAVID MALAN: Chris, David.
Thank you.
KAYLIND: Kaylind.
DAVID MALAN: Kaylind.
NOLAN: Nolan.
DAVID MALAN: Nolan, David.
JAY: Jay.
DAVID MALAN: David.
MATTHEW: Matthew.
DAVID MALAN: Matthew, David.
OK.
So, this is statistically
anomalous, insofar
as we're actually very excited
to say, in CS50, this semester,
for the first time ever-- we
watch these numbers annually--
and we actually have 44%
women in CS50 this year.
So, as you can see, none
of my demonstrations
are going correctly today.
But trust in that data.
So if each of you could
stand behind one of the music
stands here-- hopefully I have
counted out exactly eight people.
We have, in front of you guys, numbers.
So go ahead and turn
around the pieces of paper,
which represent the numbers
that we have on the board here,
if I got the same order right.
So, there's going to be
a bunch of different ways
we can sort these eight values.
So, how do we go about doing this?
Well, much like you proposed earlier--
just pick up a pair of blue books
and compare them-- why don't
I try that same intuition?
So, four and two-- these numbers
are obviously out of order.
So, what do I want to go ahead and do?
Yeah, so I can go ahead and swap these.
And now, problem is
solved, which is great.
I've taken a bite out of the problem.
And then we move on.
Four and seven?
Those look OK.
Seven and five?
Not OK.
So, what do I want to do here?
AUDIENCE: Switch them.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so I
can swap those, thank you.
So, seven and six?
Also out of order.
Let's swap those.
Seven and eight?
That's good.
Eight and three?
Not correct, so if you want
to go ahead and swap those.
And, eight and one, if you want
So, what was the net effect?
Have I sorted this list of numbers?
So, obviously not.
But I did improve it.
And what's the most glaring example,
perhaps, of the improvement, in front
of these?
AUDIENCE: Eight's at the end.
DAVID MALAN: Eight is
now at the very end.
So the biggest number, if you
will, bubbled up to the end,
as though it was bigger
and sort of bubbled up.
So that's good, but there's
still work to be done here.
So, I can, again, just try to
fix these problems locally.
Just pick up a couple of
problems and try to solve it.
So, two and four?
We're good.
Four and five?
Five and six?
Six and seven?
Ooh, seven and three?
If you guys want to swap those?
Wonderful.
And then, seven and one,
we want to do it again.
And now, do I need to bother
comparing seven and eight?
Technically no, right, because if
we know eight made its way-- now
we can start cutting some
corners, but correctly,
just to shave some time
off of the algorithm,
make it a little more efficient.
Good.
So, sorted now?
No, so we have to keep doing this.
And let me let you guys now
execute this, pair-wise at a time.
So, here we go.
Two, four.
Four, five.
Five, six.
Six, three.
Six, one.
And we can stop there, because
we know seven is in order.
Now we do it again.
Two and four.
Four and five.
Five and three?
Five and one?
Improved, good.
And now, next, two and four,
four and three, four and one,
and then two and three, three and one--
and then two and one--
OK, now it's sorted.
Yes, very well done.
Very well done.
So, it's kind of tedious,
frankly, and I didn't
want to keep walking back and forth,
because thankfully we have, like,
all of this-- this manpower, these
multiple CPUs, I guess, literally
today.
So, we have all of these
CPUs, or computers,
that are able to help me out.
But it was still very slow.
I mean, it's a long story.
So, let's rewind just
once and do one more.
If you guys could rearrange
your pieces of paper
so that it matches the screen again,
just to reset to our original location.
Let's go back there.
And let's try one other approach.
I've tried the insertion approach,
whereby I just take a problem,
like the blue book, and insert
it into its correct location.
But honestly, that was getting a little
tedious, and that's why I aborted,
because it's going to take
me longer, and longer,
and longer to find the right location
among all of those blue books.
So, let me try just
a more intuitive one.
If I want to sort these numbers,
let me just go and select
the smallest number I see.
OK, four, at the moment, is
So I'm going to grab it for just now.
Now, again, these are lockers.
Even though we humans can
see them all, the computer
can only see one location at a time.
And this is, indeed, the smallest
number I have seen thus far.
So I'm going to grab it.
But very quickly, I can
abort that, because now I've
found an even smaller number.
So I'm going to hang onto that instead.
Seven, I'm not going to worry about
that; five, six, eight, three, one--
I've found a smaller number.
Now, I need to kind of
do something with this.
I want to grab the one, so I
could just put the two here.
And what do I want to do
now with the number one?
Yeah, I kind of just
want to put it here.
And so, I can do this
in a few different ways,
but you know what, I'm
just going to evict
whoever's here, because it's a pretty
low number, but it's also random.
It could have been a big number.
So let me just make
room for it and do that.
I have selected the smallest element.
Is the list sorted?
I mean, obviously not.
But is it better?
It is, right?
Because the one is now, at
least, in the right location.
So I've solved one eighth
of the problem so far.
So that's not bad.
What could I do next?
Let me apply the same algorithm.
Let me select the smallest, which
is currently this one, still
this one, still this one--
nope, three is smaller-- oh, two is
even smaller, so let me ultimately
grab this.
And you know what, four, you
really don't need to be there;
I'm just going to evict you again,
and put two where it belongs,
and move this one over here.
So now, the list is even more sorted.
And if I proceed to do this again
and again, if you want to just keep
handing me the smallest number-- three?
OK, so I'm going to go ahead and
just evict seven, because it's
kind of a random number anyway.
And now, thank you, four--
I'm going to go ahead and evict
five, even though, kind of feels
like I'm making a little bit
of work for myself, on average,
it's not going to matter.
Sometimes it will be good,
sometimes it'll be bad.
So let me go ahead and
put five over here.
Now I need to select the next smallest
element, which happens to be five.
So we recovered pretty quickly.
So I'm going to evict six over here.
Now I'm going to look
for the smallest element.
Now it's indeed six.
I'm going to evict eight,
put this over here--
and now seven is good, eight is good--
done.
But it's still kind of
a long story, right?
Like, I'm going back and forth,
looking for these numbers.
But this would be what
we'd call selection sort.
So thank you all very much-- if you'd
like to keep your pieces of paper,
you're welcome to.
And let me give you guys
a stress ball as well.
And a round of applause,
if we could, for you guys.
If you want to hand those out.
So, as before, let's
see if we can apply--
let's see if we can apply some
pseudo code to this algorithm,
because it's one thing to talk about
it, and it's one thing to sort of reason
through it intuitively,
but at the end of the day,
if you want to program this,
we've got to be more precise,
and we've got to consider the lower
level operations that the computer is
going to execute.
So, here's how we might
implement bubble sort.
Repeat until no swaps.
For i, from 0 to n
minus 2-- and n is just
the size of the problem, the number
of doors, the number of humans,
the number of numbers, whatever the
input to the problem actually is.
So, for i, from 0 to n minus 2, if
the i-th and the i-th plus 1 elements
are out of order, swap them.
So, this is kind of a mouthful.
But if you think about it, I'm just
kind of applying some of the vocabulary
that we have from C, and
kind of sort of from scratch,
to an otherwise very
organic human experience,
but using more methodical language than
I was just kind of doing off the cuff,
when we were doing it with humans.
Because what does this mean?
For i from 0 to n minus 2.
That means start at,
like, the 0 location,
and if there's n elements
here-- this is 0--
and this, at the very end, is location--
it's going to be n minus 1.
Right?
If you start counting at 0, you
have to readjust your whole life
to subtract 1 from the tail
end of that range of numbers.
Right?
0-- if that was 1, this would be n.
But if that were 0,
this is now n minus one.
So I'm saying, though, for 0--
for i from 0 to n minus 2,
which is technically this.
So I'm using sort of for loop-like
language to start iterating here,
and do something like
this, up until the second
to last element, which
we've not done before.
Seems almost buggy.
But if you read ahead in the
pseudo code, why did I do that?
And only iterate until the
second to last element with i?
What jumps out at you?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Because then you're gonna swap
the i in the i-plus-one-th elements?
DAVID MALAN: Good.
AUDIENCE: When you get to n minus
2, you'll swap it with n minus 1.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Recall that bubble sort was all about
swapping, or potentially swapping
pair-wise elements,
neighbors, if you will.
So, you have to make sure that if you're
iterating through all of these numbers,
you have to stop short of the end
of the array, so that i plus 1
actually refers to an element
that's actually in your list,
and not, for instance,
way over here, which
would be some garbage value that
you shouldn't actually touch.
So, if those elements are
out of order, we swap them,
and I have a big outer
loop there that just says,
keep doing this, again and again and
again, until you don't swap anything.
At which point you can
infer that you're done.
Because every time I walked
back and forth on the list,
and the guys helped out by swapping
their numbers as appropriate,
I kept doing it again if there
was still room for improvement.
And intuitively, why is it
absolutely, logically safe
to stop that whole process once you
have not made any swaps on a pass
through the list?
Why is that a safe conclusion?
So, if I walk through the list--
no, these are good, these
are good, these are good--
OK, you didn't want your number--
these are good, these are good--
how do I know that I don't
need to do that again?
AUDIENCE: It's sorted already.
DAVID MALAN: It's sorted already, right?
And it would be kind of irrational--
if you've walked through the list,
looking at everything pair-wise,
found nothing to swap, to
even bother doing that again--
why would you expect different
results, if the numbers themselves
are not moving and you
didn't move them yourself?
So you can just stop.
But this still is going to invite the
question, well, how expensive was that?
How many swaps, or
comparisons, did we make?
And we'll come back to that before long.
Selection sort, though, can be expressed
maybe even a little more succinctly.
And that was the second algorithm
we did with our eight volunteers
here, for i from zero to n minus 1.
So this time, all the way
through the end of the list,
find the smallest element
between i-th and n minus 1-th.
So between those two
ranges, the beginning
of your list and the end, and then swap
the smallest with the i-th element.
So what does this mean?
So again, for i from 0 to n minus 1.
This is just pseudo code for saying,
start a variable i at location 0.
And do this until i equals n minus 1.
So, do this until you've gone
all the way through the list.
What is it telling me to do?
Find the smallest element between the
i-th element and the end of the list.
N minus one never changes.
It always refers to the
end of the list, so that's
why I walked through the list looking
for, ultimately, the number 1.
And what did I do with the number 1?
Swap the smallest with the i-th element.
And I might have gotten one of the steps
wrong when I did a little switcheroo,
but we fixed it thereafter.
Ultimately, I kept evicting
whoever was in the i-th location
to make room for the element
that I knew belonged there
And I could have shuffled them
to make room for those elements,
but it turns out,
mathematically, it's just as fine
to just evict it and move it all
the way to the end, as we did.
And once I've gone all
the way through the list,
there is no more
smallest element to find.
And as we saw, the list is sorted.
So, maybe this is faster,
maybe this is slower--
it's not immediately obvious.
And insertion sort, which we actually
came up with by way of the blue books
on the floor, might
be described as this.
For i, from 1 to n minus 1, call the
0th through the i minus i-th element
the sorted side--
that's a mouthful-- so,
consider the left of your list
the sorted side of the list.
And initially, there's nothing there.
You have zero elements
sorted to your left,
and eight unsorted
elements to your right.
So that sort of describes
this story, when
we had volunteers and numbers here.
There are no elements sorted;
everything to my right was unsorted.
That's all that's saying.
Remove the i-th element.
That was like picking
up this blue book, if we
were using blue books in this example.
Then what do I want to do?
Insert it into the
sorted side, in order.
So, if this is the sorted side,
this is the unsorted side,
this is the equivalent of
saying, take that blue book
and just put it in the first location.
And you can kind of make
a visual gap for it.
Now, this is the sorted side,
this is the unsorted side.
Or, equivalently, when I was
down here with the blue books,
the books in my hands were the sorted
side, and everything still on the stage
was the unsorted side.
Same idea.
So, what happens next?
I then iterate one location next,
and I remove the next element,
and whatever number that is, I
figure out, does it go to the left
or does it go to the right?
Which was the same
thing, again, on stage,
me sort of picking up a
third blue book and deciding,
does it go in between these books?
Does it go below, does it go above?
I inserted it into its
appropriate location.
So in this insertion sort algorithm,
you sort of take each number
as you encounter it, and
deal with it then and there.
You take the number
and deal with it, so,
you know what, this one's got to go
here, if we just kind of pretend what
the numbers look like for a moment.
So that would be inserting
it into the right location,
like I did with the blue books.
Maybe this one-- oh, maybe this
one's a really small number,
and so I insert it over here.
So I kind of literally deal with
each problem as I encounter it,
but it just gets expensive,
or very annoying,
to have to move all of
this stuff out of the way
to make room for those elements.
And that's why I got bored
with the blue book example,
because it was getting
very tedious looking
through all of the blue books
for the correct location.
So in short, all three
of these algorithms,
while very differently
expressed, and while all of them
are kind of intuitive until you try to
describe what your human intuition has
actually been doing for the
past some number of years
that you've been sorting
things just in the real world--
they can all be described, at
least, in terms of these algorithms.
So these algorithms-- and we started
this conversation in the first
lecture--
all have, ultimately,
some kind of running
time associated with them, like how
long does it take to do something.
And we talked about the process
of finding Mike Smith in terms
of this pretty generic graph.
It wasn't very mathematical, it
wasn't very sophisticated-- we just
wanted to get a sense of the
relationships, or tradeoffs, of space
and time, so to speak.
And so, on the x-axis, or horizontal,
we have the size of the problem--
so, like, a number of
pages in the phone book,
or number of people in the phone book--
and on the y-axis, or vertical,
we had the amount of time
to solve the problem.
How many seconds, how
many page turns-- you
could count using any
unit of measure you like.
And the first algorithm for Mike Smith,
when I started with the very first page
and turned, and turned, and turned, was
a straight line, a linear relationship.
One more page, one more step.
So, it's straight line.
The next algorithm was searching by
twos, recall, in the first lecture.
Two, four, six, eight.
And that's still a straight
line, because there's
a predictable relationship between
number of pages and number of seconds,
or page turns.
It's two to one instead of one to
one, so it's still a straight line,
but it's lower on the graph.
It's better.
But the best one, by far, was the
divide and conquer approach, we said.
Right?
And it certainly felt faster; it's
great, because it was intuitive.
It wasn't quite as easy to
express in pseudo code--
that was among the longer ones today--
but it at least got us
to the answer faster.
And this is logarithmic, in
the sense that the logarithm--
technically base 2, if you
recall some of your math--
it's because you're dividing the
problem in half, and half, and half.
And it's fine if you're
uncomfortable with it,
don't even remember what a logarithm is.
For now, just assume that logarithmic
time has this different shape to it.
It grows much more slowly.
Any time you can choose log of n over
n, when picking between two algorithms,
go with the log n, or
something like that,
because it is going to be smaller,
as we can see visually here.
So, let's just consider
something like bubble sort.
There's a couple of ways
we can look at this.
And again, the goal here is
not to be very mathematical--
we're not going to start doing
proofs, but at least, by taking
a glance at some of the
steps in this algorithm,
you can get a general sense of how
slow or how fast an algorithm is.
And indeed, that's the goal.
There's this fancy notation we're about
to see called asymptotic notation,
with special Greek characters.
But at the end of the day,
we're really just trying
to get an intuitive sense of how good
or bad an algorithm is, much like we
were trying to do with this picture.
But now we'll do it a
little more conventionally,
as a computer scientist might.
So in bubble sort, recall that
we compared every pair of humans
and made a swap if
they were out of order.
And then we repeated.
And we repeated, and repeated.
And we kept going through the list.
So, that can be quantized-- like,
you can kind of break that down
into some total number of steps.
So, if you've got n humans
in front of the room,
and you want to compare them
from left to right in pairs,
how many possible pairs
are there as I walk
through the list for that first time?
If there's n elements, and I can
put the stands back where they were.
How many pairs were there, as
I walked from left to right?
I compared these two,
these two, these two.
Yeah, there's n minus one.
Specifically seven.
And even if you're not quite
sure where we're going with this,
if there's eight stands-- like, this
is one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven--
and there's eight total.
So, that's indeed n minus 1.
So, that's how many
comparisons we might have made
the first time through bubble sort.
But the very first time I went
through the list in bubble sort
did the list get fully sorted?
No, we had to do it again.
We knew that 8 had bubbled up to
the very end, so that was good.
8 was in the right place.
But I had to do it again, and
fix more problems along the way.
But the second time, I didn't need
to go all the way through the list.
To be clear, who did
I not need to look at?
The last location, or 8,
in our very specific case.
So the second time through
the list of humans,
I only have to make n
minus 2 comparisons.
Right?
Because I can just ignore number
8, the final human, and just deal
with the seven other humans
that are somehow misordered.
So, if I wanted to really be nitpicky
and write this down, and count up
how many steps, or how
many comparisons, I made,
we could generalize it like this.
All right?
It's going to be n minus 1, plus n minus
2, plus n minus 3, plus dot-dot-dot.
Or, more specifically, 7
plus 6 plus 5 plus 4-- this
is just the fancier formulaic
way of saying the same thing.
Now, I don't remember my
back-of-math-book formulas all that
well, but I remember this one.
You know, in your physics books, your
math books, often in the hardcovers,
you'll see little cheat sheets
for what series of numbers
actually sum to or multiply out to.
And so it turns out that
that summation can actually
be expressed more succinctly as n
times n minus 1, all divided by 2.
That is the same thing,
mathematically, as the long series
that I had a dot-dot-dot there for.
So if I multiply this out,
just using some algebra,
that's like n squared
minus n, divided by 2.
And then if I kind of multiply that
out, that's n squared, divided by 2,
minus n over 2.
So if I wanted to be
really precise, this
is the running time of bubble sort.
It takes this many
steps to sort n people.
Why?
Because I literally just counted
the number of comparisons I made.
That's how many comparisons
it takes to do bubble sort.
But honestly, this is
really getting tedious,
and my eyes are already
starting to glaze over.
I don't want to remember
these algebraic formulas here.
So let's actually try an example,
just to get a sense of how slow
or how fast this is.
Suppose that n were a million.
So not eight, but a million
people, or a million numbers.
How slow, or fast, is
bubble sort going to be?
Well, if we plug in a million,
that's like saying n is a million.
So that's a million squared, divided
by 2, minus a million divided by 2.
Because that's what it
all summed up to be.
So if I do this out,
it's a really big number.
500 billion minus 500,000.
And in any other context, 500,000
is a pretty darn big number.
But not so much when you
subtract it from 500 billion,
because you still get 499,999,500,000
after subtracting those off.
Which is to say, of those two terms,
the one on the left versus the one
on the right, which is the bigger one?
The more dominating factor in
the mathematical expression?
It's the one on the left, right?
That's the one that's massively bigger.
And so more generally,
n squared divided by 2
feels like a bigger result
than n divided by 2 alone.
And we've seen it by proof-- by
example, which is not a proof,
but it at least gives us a feel
for the size of the program,
or the number of comparisons
we're actually making.
So you know what, ugh-- if that is
the case, if the dominant factor--
the one on the left, in our
case; the one with the square,
specifically-- is just
so much more influential
on the number of comparisons
we're going to make, then
let's just wave our hands
at the lower-ordered terms,
and divide it by 2,
and anything like that,
and just say, ugh, this
algorithm feels like n squared.
I'm going to throw away
the denominator, I'm
going to throw away the
thing I'm subtracting off,
I'm going to throw away anything
that is not the dominating factor,
which is the term that contributes
the most to the total number of steps
incurred.
And indeed, this is what a computer
scientist would describe, generally,
as the running time of this algorithm.
It is on the order of n squared.
It's not n squared, but it's on the
order of n squared, as we've seen.
It's pretty darn close, and it's
good enough for a conversation
with another reasonable person who wants
to debate whether his or her algorithm
is maybe better or worse than yours.
So, this would be called big O notation.
Big O is used to refer to an upper
bound on an algorithm's running time.
Upper bound meaning, we'll consider,
for our purposes, in the worst case,
how much time might this algorithm take?
Well, it's going to take on
the order of n squared steps.
Because if the list of
numbers is unsorted initially,
we've got to do a lot of
work to actually sort it.
There's other terms that we
could put in those parentheses.
Some algorithms are not
on the order of n squared.
Some algorithms are
actually order of n log n;
some algorithms are on the order
of n itself, or log n, or even 1,
where 1 refers to constant time.
And in fact, the ones
I've highlighted here,
we've actually seen examples along
the way of all of these so far.
For instance, what
algorithm have we seen
that has a running
time on the order of n?
n steps?
AUDIENCE: Linear search.
DAVID MALAN: Linear search.
If we were to think back, even
to today, to linear search--
or from the first lecture, when I was
just looking for Mike, really slowly,
one phone book page at a time,
that's a linear algorithm.
If there's n pages, or n humans, it
might take me on the order of n steps,
because Mike Smith--
S is toward the end of the alphabet,
so he might be way over there,
or way toward the end of the
phone book, or, God forbid,
his name starts with
a Z, then I'm really
going to have to go all the
way into the phone book.
And so that's on the order of n steps.
So, n here would be linear.
We've also seen another
algorithm, here in yellow--
big O of log n.
Saw it just a moment ago.
Which of our algorithms was on
the order of log n running time?
Yeah, so binary search.
Divide and conquer.
We didn't call it--
we didn't describe it this
formulaically in the first lecture,
but that's how you would
describe the running time.
Not just with a pretty picture,
but just with an expression
like this, that all humans--
at least computer
scientists-- can agree upon.
And constant time.
The funny thing here is,
because we're throwing away
terms that don't really
matter, O of 1 does not
mean an algorithm that
takes one step only.
That would be a very limited number
of options for your algorithms.
But it does mean, symbolically,
a constant number of steps.
A constant number of steps.
So, what's something you might do
that takes a constant number of steps,
in an algorithm?
Maybe in, like, the first lecture,
we had the silly peanut butter
and jelly example.
Which of the steps that
day might have taken big O
of 1 steps, a constant number of steps?
I remember one, like,
insert knife into jar?
That's kind of one step.
Maybe it's two, because I might
have to, like, pick up the knife,
and insert it into the jar then.
One step, two steps-- but
it's a constant number.
The number of steps is not at all
informed by the algorithm itself.
It just happens.
You do that in one step.
So, if there's any number
of other algorithms here--
and we'll leave in white one that
we'll come back to-- but let's
just consider the opposite
of this, if you will.
If big O is our upper bound
on running time, it turns out,
there's a vocabulary for discussing the
lower bound on an algorithm's running
time.
Which, for our purposes, we'll generally
consider in the context of best case.
So in the best case scenario, how
little time might an algorithm take?
Well, this is a capital omega, and
it's used in exactly the same way.
You just say, omega of n squared,
or omega of n, or omega of log n.
So it's the same symbology, it
just refers to a lower bound.
So, it takes this few
steps, or this many steps.
Big O, big omega.
So, what's an algorithm, therefore,
that is in, so to speak, omega of 1?
Like, what algorithm, in the best case,
might actually take just one step?
And who is best to answer this
question today in the room, in fact.
What algorithm could take one step?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, linear search
could take omega of one steps.
Because in the best
case, it is right there.
Or in Chrissy's case,
even if our algorithm
is to sort of choose
randomly, in the best case,
it is right there, the number 50.
So even her algorithm, and even
our linear search algorithm--
and for that matter, even
our binary search algorithm--
are in omega of 1, at
least in the best case.
Because if you get lucky, you're done.
One step.
By contrast, what is an algorithm
that takes at least n steps?
So, omega of n?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: That's a good one.
So you say bubble sort, I heard.
AUDIENCE: Yes.
DAVID MALAN: Why?
AUDIENCE: Because if they're
all already in order,
you just go through each
comparison, and then make no swaps.
DAVID MALAN: Good.
So in the case of bubble
sort, where we generally
had a lot more work to do
than just finding something
with a searching algorithm, bubble
sort is, minimally, an omega event
you need at least on the order of
n steps-- maybe it's n minus 1,
or n minus 2-- but
it's on the order of n.
Why?
Because only once you go through
the list at least once do
you know-- what, to be clear?
AUDIENCE: That they're all in order.
DAVID MALAN: That they're in order.
And you know that as a side effect
of having not made any swaps.
So, you can only determine that a
list is sorted in the first place
by spending at least n
steps on that process.
Excellent.
So, there's yet another
one, and this is the last,
whereby if you happen to have
an algorithm, or a scenario
where the upper bound and the
lower bound are the same--
turns out there's a symbol for that
too; you can just describe the algorithm
in terms of theta notation.
That just means theta of n,
theta of log n-- whatever it is,
that just means upper bound and
lower bound are one and the same.
And there's more formalities to this,
and you can actually dive in deeper
to this in a theory class.
But for our purposes, big O and
omega will be a generally useful way
of describing, generally speaking, just
what the running time of an algorithm
actually is.
So, big O of n squared is the
fastest we've seen thus far.
Unfortunately, it does actually
tend to run pretty slowly.
We saw it with an example of,
like, 500 billion steps just
to sort a million elements.
Turns out we can do
way better than that.
Much like in the first lecture,
when I crazily proposed,
I think, suppose your phone book
had, like, four billion pages--
well, you only need 32
steps using binary search,
instead of four billion
steps using linear search.
So, it would be nice if, after all
of this discussion of algorithms
and introduction of these formalities,
if we can actually do better.
And it turns out that we
can do better, but this
has been a lot to do already,
so let's go ahead in here
and take a five-minute. break.
And when we come back, we'll blow out of
the water the performance of all three
of those algorithms we just saw.
All right.
So, let's take a quick look at
what these algorithms look like,
so we can actually compare
them against something
that I claim is actually
going to end up being better.
OK.
So, here we have an array of numbers
represented as vertical bars.
So, small bar is small number;
tall bar is big number.
And so it's a nice way to visualize
what otherwise is pretty low level
numbers alone.
I'm going to go ahead here and
make the animation pretty fast,
and I'm going to go ahead here and
choose, for instance, bubble sort.
And, actually, let me
slow it down a little bit,
just for the sake of discussion.
So, you'll see, in this
algorithm, bubble sort.
It's making multiple passes
through the list, just as I did,
highlighting in pink
two neighbors at a time,
and deciding whether
or not to swap them,
just as we were, with our eight
volunteers, doing the exact same thing.
Of course, with this visualization,
we can do it more quickly,
and we can speed this up to the
point where you can kind of now
start to feel the bubbling effect,
if you will, whereby the bigger
numbers are bubbling up to the top, to
the right, just as the number 8 did,
when we did it on paper.
So, this is bubble sort.
And we could watch this for quite
some time, and in some sense,
it's kind of mesmerizing.
But in another sense,
it's pretty underwhelming,
because at the end of the
day, all you're going to get
is a bunch of bars, sorted,
from short bars to big bars.
But perhaps the takeaway
is that I'd kind of
have to stall here for
a decent amount of time,
even though we're running this at
the fastest speed, because it's only
fixing, at best, one number at a time.
And maybe some others are improving,
but we're only moving all the way
to the end one number at a time.
And we have to then go back, and go
back, and go back, and do more work.
It's going to be very ungratifying to
abort it, but let's go back to random.
And now, if we choose, for
instance, selection sort,
you'll see that the algorithm
works a little differently.
Let me slow it down.
And what it's doing now, which
is a little less obvious,
is it's looking through the list
for the next smallest element,
and it's going to put it at
the beginning of the list.
All the way at the left.
So, it's looking, and
looking, and looking,
and it leaves highlighted in
red the most recently discovered
smallest element.
And then as soon as it gets
to the end of the list,
it's going to move that smallest
element all the way to the left.
So that we now, kind of like
the opposite of bubble sort,
have all of the smallest
elements to the left.
Though, this is arbitrary.
We could bubble up the small
elements by just reversing
the order of our operations;
we could sort from biggest
to smallest-- that is irrelevant.
It's just by human convention we tend to
sort from smallest to biggest, at least
in examples like this.
And we can speed this up, but it doesn't
quite have quite the same comparison
effect, because all you're doing
is a swoop through the list looking
for the smallest, looking for the
smallest, looking for the smallest.
And so, this way, it's going
to build up from short to tall.
Let me go ahead and do it one more
time, this time with insertion sort,
and slow it down.
And so, what we're doing
here is the following.
We identify the next element, and then
we go and insert it into the place
it belongs in the "sorted
half" of the list.
So, recall that I generally describe
stuff on the left as being sorted,
stuff on the right as being
unsorted, and the implication
of that is that even though
these numbers here on the left
are indeed sorted, when I encounter a
new number, out in the unsorted area,
I might have to move some things
around and shuffle things around.
And unlike the cheat I
was doing here in person--
when I grabbed that music stand before
and just kind of moved it over here--
that's not really legitimate.
Right?
This is garbage value land.
Like, I should not have
had access to this memory.
And so what we did with our actual
eight humans was more legitimate.
The fact that our volunteers
did the physical labor
of moving those numbers around?
That was the low-level work that
the computer has to do, too.
And you see it here all the more, either
at this slow speed or the faster speed.
It's being inserted into
the appropriate location.
So, case in point, this
tiny little element?
We have to do a huge amount
of work to find its location,
until finally, we've found it,
and now we do the same thing.
So, all of these have some
pluses and some minuses.
But it turns out, with merge
sort, we can do even better.
An algorithm that goes by
the name of merge sort.
But to do better, we need to have a new
ingredient, or at least more formally
defined, that we've kind of sort of
leverage before, but not by name.
And to do this, I'm going actually take
out a little bit of code, in CS50 IDE,
a program called sigma-0.c.
And we'll see the
interconnection in just a moment.
So in this program,
notice the following.
We have a main function,
whose purpose in life
is to get a positive
integer from the user,
and to pester him or
her, again and again
and again, until they cooperate
and provide a positive integer.
That's what the do-while
loop is often useful for.
And then, what do we do with it?
We simply pass that value,
n, that the human typed in,
via get int, to a function called sigma.
And sigma is like the Greek character,
or the capital E-looking character,
that generally means, in math,
like, sum a bunch of numbers.
Add a bunch of numbers together.
So, this is essentially a function
called sigma, whose purpose in life
is to sum all of the
numbers from 0 to n.
Or, equivalently, from 1 to n.
So, 1 plus 2 plus 3 plus 4
plus, dot-dot-dot, n, whatever n
happens to be.
And then, via printf,
we're just printing it out.
So, let me just run this program to
make super clear what's going on.
And I can do this by doing, of course,
in my source three directory for today,
make sigma 0, enter, dot slash sigma
0, positive integer, I will do 2.
So by that definition, it
should sum 0 plus 1 plus 2, so 1
plus 2-- that should be 3.
So I should see 3.
And indeed, I see 3.
Let's do one more, if
I add in three numbers.
So, this should be 1 plus 2 plus 3--
so, that's 1-- that's 6, in total.
And so forth.
And they get pretty big pretty quickly.
If I do 50, then we start
to get into the thousands.
So, that's all it's doing.
And how is it doing this?
Well, we could implement this
in a whole bunch of ways,
but if we leverage some of our
sort of techniques thus far,
we might do it using a for loop.
That's kind of been one of the
most common tools in our toolkit.
And how am I using it here?
I'm first declaring a variable
called sum, initializing it to 0,
because I've done no work yet.
Then I have a for loop, for i
equals 1 all the way up through m.
Why m?
Well, just because.
Recall that when you make your own
function, whether in Scratch or in C,
you get to decide what to call
the inputs to that function.
The arguments, or parameters,
as they're called.
And just for clarity,
I called it m, even
though we've typically been using n.
I could have called it anything I want.
I just wanted to make super
clear it's a different variable.
But more on that in a week or so.
And so I'm just counting from one to
m, and I'm adding to sum whatever i is.
Now, just as a quick
check, why am I not doing
sum plus plus, as I usually
do in these kinds of cases?
AUDIENCE: Because you're not
incrementing by [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
I'm not incrementing by 1, I'm
incrementing by 1, and then by 2,
and then by 3, and then
by 4, and so forth.
So I need this loop to
be counting up, and I
need to be adding i to the sum,
not just a plus plus, in this case.
Then I return the sum.
And so, this is an
example of an abstraction.
Like, I now have a
function called sigma--
just like in math, you might
have the big capital sigma
symbol that just says, add
all these numbers together,
I have a C function that does that.
And so now, higher up in my
code, I can call that function
and then print out the answer.
But it turns out that this
simple function lends itself
to a nice example of another programming
technique, something called recursion.
And we won't have terribly
many opportunities in CS50
to apply this technique, but
we will toward semester's end.
If you continue on to a class like
CS51, you'll use it all the time.
If you use another type
of programming language,
you'll very often use this technique.
And it's called recursion,
and it looks like this.
Let me go ahead and open
up another file that's
available on the course's
website called sigma 1.
Notice that main is identical.
So, main is identical.
And indeed, it's still calling
a function called sigma,
and then using printf
to print out the answer.
So there's no difference there.
But what is different, in this next
version, is the code for sigma.
So, what's going on here?
It still takes, as input,
an integer called m.
So that's good, because I need
to know what to sum up to.
It returns an integer, as before.
And it amazingly has, like--
what, four real lines of
code, plus some curly braces?
And even those lines of
code are super short.
And there's no additional variables, and
there's this weird, crazy logic here.
But let's see what it's
doing, first and foremost.
On line 23, I'm saying if m is
less than or equal to 0, return 0.
Now, why does this make sense?
Well, I only want to support positive
numbers, or non-negative numbers,
from 0 to m.
And so I just kind of need
an error check there, right?
If the human somehow passes into this
function negative 50 or something else,
I don't want the function to freak
out and give unpredictable behavior,
I just want it to return
0, in cases of error
or when the number gets that
small as to hit 0 or even lower.
So this, I'm going to call base case.
It's just, like, this
sanity check, like,
don't let the math go beyond
this point of 0 or less.
So, amazingly, if you really zoom in on
this code, the entirety of this program
really boils down to one line.
And what's going on here?
So, I am returning,
from sigma, an answer.
But, curiously, my answer is kind
of defined in terms of itself,
which generally is a bad idea.
Right?
It's like in English,
if you try to define
a word by using the
word in the definition,
usually someone calls you
on that, because it's not
all that helpful to use a word
in the definition of the word.
And that's the same idea, at
first glance, of recursion.
You are using the same function
to solve a problem that
was supposed to be solved by
that function in the first place.
So, what do I mean by that?
Main, of course, is calling
sigma, and that means this code
down here that we've been
looking at gets executed.
So, suppose that we
hit this line of code.
What recursion allows
us to do, in this case,
is take a bite out of the problem,
and then defer to someone else
to figure out the rest of the problem.
So, what do we mean by that?
Well, sigma, again, is just this process
of adding up all the numbers between 0
and some number, m.
So, 1 plus 2 plus 3 plus dot-dot-dot.
So, you know what?
I don't want to do all that work, as
I did in version 0 with my for loop.
Let me just do a piece of that work.
And how do I do that?
Well, you know what, when you ask
me, what is the sum from 0 to m?
I'm going to be kind of circular
about it, and be like, well,
it's the answer of--
the answer is m, the biggest number you
handed me, plus the sum of everything
below it.
Right?
So, if you passed in the number 10,
it's like saying, well, sigma of 10
is 10 plus sigma of nine,
and, like, leave me alone.
I don't want to do the rest of the math.
But, because you're calling the same
function again, that's actually OK.
A function can call
itself, because if you
think about where the story is going,
now sigma gets called, in this story,
with sigma of 9.
What does the code do?
Well, sigma of nine returns 9
plus whatever sigma of 8 is.
So we're not solving the whole problem.
We're handing back a 10, plus a 9--
and if we keep going, plus
an 8, plus a 7, plus a 6.
But we're not going to do this forever.
Even though I'm using sigma in my
implementation of my answer, under what
circumstances am I not calling sigma?
AUDIENCE: If m equals 0.
DAVID MALAN: If m equals 0, or is even
less than 0-- which shouldn't happen,
but just to be sure, I made sure it
can't, with the less than or equal to.
So eventually, you're going
to ask me, what is sigma of 0?
And I'm not going to be difficult
about it, I'm just going to say 0.
And no longer do I keep passing
the buck to that same function.
And so even though it takes a while
to get to that point in the story--
because we say 10 plus
sigma of 9, sigma of 9
is 9 plus sigma of 8, which is
sigma of 8 plus sigma of 7--
like, it keeps going
and going and going.
But if you kind of mentally
buffer, so to speak,
much like a video in your
browser, all of those numbers
that you're being handed
back, one at a time--
which are, technically,
being added together
for you by your program with the plus
operator-- the last number you're
going to be handed back is zero, and
at that point, all of the plus signs
can just kind of kick
in and give you back
whatever number you're
actually looking for.
So, recursion is the act of
a function calling itself.
Which is very, very, very bad, unless
you have a base case that ensures that
eventually, as you take
bites out of the problem,
you will handle, with a
special case, so to speak--
a base case-- a small piece
of the puzzle, and just hand
back a hard-coded answer,
to make sure that this
doesn't happen infinitely many times.
So, any questions on this principle, of
a function being able to call itself?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So, the base case
here was when m equals 0?
DAVID MALAN: When m equals 0 or is
even less than zero, just to be sure.
But yes, when m equals zero.
Indeed.
So, let's see.
If you're comfortable, at least,
with the fact-- oh, and actually,
there's a good little geek humor now--
if you go to Google.com,
and suppose you wonder,
you're wondering what recursion is,
especially a few hours from now.
Well, you can Google it, and then
the computer scientists at Google--
there you go.
OK, so if you're laughing,
you get it, which is great.
So that, then, is recursion.
Something giving you back an
answer in terms of itself.
So, why is this useful?
Well, it turns out we
can leverage this now
to solve a problem if we know that
we can actually convert it to code.
We'll focus less on the actual
implementation and more on the idea,
but let's see if we can't wrap
our minds around the problem
to be solved with this code.
This is merge sort, in pseudo code.
And again, like all the pseudo
code we've ever written,
you could write this in
bunches of different ways.
Here's one such way.
Notice, the first thing, on input of n
elements-- so, n numbers, n blue books,
n whatever-- go ahead
and do the following.
If n is less than 2, return.
So it's a little different from
the condition I had a moment ago,
but the context here is
sorting, it's not summing.
So, why is it logically OK to say,
if n is less than 2, just return?
Yeah, that's just itself.
If it's less than 2, that means there's
only one blue book, or maybe even
0, so in either case,
there's no work to be done.
Just return.
The list is sorted, however short it is.
But if it's longer than that,
you might have to do some work,
and actually do some actual sorting.
So, what happens then?
So, else-- you know what?
Sort the left half of the
elements, and then sort
the right half of the elements,
and then, OK, merge them together.
So it's the same kind of,
like, blase attitude, where,
like, ah-- if you ask me to sort
something, I'm just going to tell you,
well, you go sort the left,
then you go sort the right,
and then we'll just merge
the results back together.
And this is cyclical
in the sense that, how
do you sort the left half of anything?
You need a sorting algorithm.
But this is the sorting algorithm.
So this is like saying, use
merge sort to sort the left half,
use merge sort to sort the right
half, and then merge them together.
Merging doesn't really need
to be a fancy algorithm;
merging is like, if you've
got one pile of numbers here
that are sorted, one pile of
numbers here that's sorted,
you can just kind of eyeball them
and grab the appropriate one to kind
of interleave them in the right order.
That's what we mean by merging.
So, how in the world
is this even correct?
Because we haven't actually done
any apparent work, in this way.
There's no loops, there's
no comparisons, it seems.
It's just completely recursively
defined, so to speak.
Well, let's see what
actually this means.
And this is a sequence
of visualizations that
can potentially fall off the story of.
So I'll try to go slowly, but not
so slowly that the example itself
is boring.
We'll just go through
this once, and then
again, the slides are
online, if you kind of
want to step through the visualization.
So, here is a list of 8
numbers, the same 8 numbers,
that we looked at before.
I've drawn them contiguously,
as though they are in an array.
This list is currently of size 8.
So an input of 8 elements is
the beginning of this story.
What was the first
step in our algorithm?
Well, we were going to check,
if n is less than 2, return.
That is irrelevant, because
n is 8, not less than 2.
So that's a moot point.
So, the first three things
for me to do to sort this list
is to sort the left half,
then sort the right half,
then to merge the sorted halves.
OK, so let's see how we get there.
So here's the list,
here is the left half,
and I need to sort the
left half, apparently.
How do I do that?
Well, how do you sort a
list of four elements?
AUDIENCE: Break it up again?
DAVID MALAN: Break it up again.
Sort the left half, then its right half,
then merge those two halves together.
So let me do that.
I'm going to draw a box
around only the elements we're
thinking about at the moment.
So, let me look at the left half.
OK, now I need to sort this list.
How do I sort a list of size 2?
It's actually 2, it's not less than 2.
So I have to do some work.
So, how do you sort a list of size 2?
It's a little strange to say it, but--
sort the left half, then sort the
right half, then merge the two.
And at this point in the
story, you may very well
be lost, because we literally
just keep saying the same thing,
and not actually doing any work.
But think of it like you're
buffering these instructions.
Like, I've said to sort the
left half, then the right half,
but you focused on just
the left half for now.
But unfortunately, you
got a little distracted,
because now to sort the left half,
you have to sort the left half,
so you have to do a little more work.
So if you just kind of let
this mental baggage build up,
we have to remember
to go back through it.
But we've not actually
done the real work yet.
We're about to now.
Because now that you've told me, given
a list of size 2, sort the left half,
here's where we bottom
out with that base case
and actually start to
make some progress.
So here's 4 and 2, a list of size 2.
Let's sort the left half.
How do you sort a list of size 1?
You don't, right?
Because n is 1; 1, of
course, is less than 2,
and what was the one instruction that
we had at the top of this function
merge sort?
Just return.
Like, do nothing.
So, OK, everyone.
I have now sorted the number 4 for you.
Like, it's true, it's kind
of a foolish statement,
but the magic must therefore
come when we combine the results.
So, let's see where the story goes.
I've sorted the left half-- done.
Return.
Now, what was I supposed to do next?
Now I have to sort the right
half of that list of size 2.
OK, done.
What's the third step at
this point in the story?
Merge them.
So I'm now looking at a list of size 2
again, each of whose halves is sorted--
according to the crazy
logic we're using here--
but now, something interesting happens.
I have on the left the
number 4, I have on the right
the number 2, and each of
these lists is of size 1.
And if you vary, in your mind's eye,
or just visually, with my fingers,
consider, like, your left hand
pointing at the first list,
your right hand pointing at the second
list, the process of merging numbers
is just comparing what your fingers
are pointing at and deciding
which one comes first.
Obviously 2 is going to
come first, so in a moment,
we'll see that 2 should
move over here, and then
there's nothing left for my right hand.
It's done.
So, 4 is obviously going to go here.
And that process of merging 2 followed
by 4 is what we mean by merging.
It's pretty much what I was
doing with insertion sort,
but here we're just doing it with
individual elements at a time, kind
of weaving things together,
or zipping things together,
like with a zipper, if
you think of it that.
Way.
So, now, let me grab 2 and put it here.
Let me grab 4 and put it here.
OK.
So I sorted left half, I sorted
right half, I merged them--
how do we unwind the story?
Where did we leave off?
AUDIENCE: Sort the right half.
DAVID MALAN: Now we have to sort
the right half that was, like,
a minute ago in the story-- which, just
to highlight it now, is the 7 and 5.
So now I have to do the same thing.
I'm sorting a list, of size 2, that
happens to be on the right of the left.
So now, I sort the left half, done.
Sort the right half, done.
I now have to merge the two together.
So now my hands have to do some work,
but I'll just do it from over here.
5 goes down, then 7 goes down.
And at this point in the story, we have
sorted the left half of the left half,
and the right half of the left half.
So, what point in the
story are we at now?
Right.
We're-- now we have-- well, we
did the right half just now.
We now have to merge
the two halves together.
And, frankly, if you do this at home, if
you want to kind of retrace your steps,
literally just write down a to-do
list, like, from top to bottom
on the sheet of paper.
And then as you do something,
cross it off, and go back
to the previous thing in the list,
you would actually see, or feel,
even more what it was,
that mental baggage
you were accumulating that
you need to attend to.
But now I have two lists of size 2, so
let's do the finger thing again here.
So, I start pointing at the left list,
start pointing at the right list.
The first number to merge in
is, presumably, going to be 2.
Then what comes after that?
I'm going to update my
left finger, so now 1--
my left hand's pointing at the 4,
at this point; my right hand, still
pointing at the 5, so which comes next?
4.
There's no more work for my
left hand, so it's probably
going to be pretty trivial--
5 and 7.
But I do need to do the merging.
It looks merged already,
but we have to do it.
And I'm going to do it in some
new space, just as before.
So, 2 and 4 and 5 and 7.
And now you can really
see it for the first time.
The left half of the original
list is finally sorted.
Unfortunately, like three minutes
ago is when we started the story.
And now we need to unwind, in our mind,
to go back to the original right half.
So if you think about it now, even
though I've said a lot of words,
this is technically the
second step in our algorithm.
Or at least the first
invocation thereof.
All right, so we'll do it a
little faster, but same idea.
Sort the left half.
How do I do that?
Sort the left half, then the right
half, which are stupidly easy and dumb,
but now I have to merge 6 and 8.
So, merging in this case
didn't have much effect,
but it needed to be done to be sure.
Next, let's sort the right
half of the right half.
Now I'm going to sort
the left, sort the right.
Now the key step is merging.
And now we're doing some actual work.
And now we really have
some work to be done--
now we have to sort the left half and
the right half of the original right
half.
So it's 1, then 3, then 6, then 8.
Now we're finally, almost at the end.
Now what do we do with these?
Now we have two halves, the original
left and the original right,
and you can think of the
fingers as doing the work again.
1 is going to go here, 2 is going to go
here, 3 is going to go here, then 4--
and I constantly compare
where my fingers are pointing,
but my fingers are constantly
moving from left to right.
As soon as I deal with a number,
it advances to the next number
in the list.
So it's obviously going to
be, now, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
But notice, if you imagine
my fingers doing this work,
they're constantly moving toward
the right, to the end of the list.
So, as soon as my fingers hit the ends
of those lists, I must be done merging.
And voila.
We've now sorted the elements.
It's a huge number of words,
and it would be a nightmare
to kind of do it with humans, because
there's just so much going on,
and you have to remember, or
buffer, so many of those steps.
But in the end, we've done something
that is kind of captured even
by this picture.
So it turns out that merge sort, even
though it sounds like a long story,
is fundamentally faster, and it's
fundamentally faster because we're
dividing the problem in half, as we
have been doing with binary search,
in the phone book example even days ago.
So if we look on the screen, you
can kind of see the remnants of work
that we've done.
Like, how many times did we move the
elements, from one row to another?
They started up here, then they
eventually made their way here,
and then here, and then here.
So that's one, two, three movements
of the letters, or of the numbers,
in memory, if you will.
So if you imagine each of these
rows as just a different chunk
of memory and RAM, I'm just
moving things around in memory.
So, three is just a number.
But it turns out, and if we
did more general cases of this,
turns out that log base
2 of n, where n is 8--
8 is the number of elements we
started with-- log base 2 of 8 is 3.
And so indeed-- and if
you'll take on faith for now,
so that we don't have to go
through an even bigger example,
to show it even more--
the number of times we move
the numbers is going to equal,
turns out, log base 2 of n.
Which, in this case, happens to be 3.
And so that, then, invites
the question-- on each
of the rows, every time you move these
numbers into a new location in memory,
how many times are you touching that
number while it's in that position?
Or, how many times,
equivalently, are you looking
at it, to do something about it?
What do I mean by this?
Well, the movement from top to
bottom was happening anytime
we did the merging.
Right?
We would move the numbers
from here to here.
But as soon as we did that, we had to
do some work, with the left pointer
and right pointer.
I needed to then merge those together.
And I emphasized earlier that
anytime I'm comparing numbers,
my left hand and right
hand are constantly
advancing from left and right.
I never double back.
Much like I constantly was doubling
back with bubble sort, insertion sort,
selection sort-- there was so
much damn comparison going on,
it felt like a lot of work,
and it physically was.
But here, you know, merging,
I'm moving things around,
but my hands are constantly moving
forward, looking at, on each row,
n numbers total.
My left hand or right hand pointed
at each of the numbers once.
Never doubled back.
So, it was never n plus
1, or 2 n, it was just n.
So, we have log n movements
of the numbers, in memory.
And every time we do that, we merge
them from left to right, effectively
touching each number once.
So we're doing n things log n times.
And so, that would be
mathematically equal to n log n.
So, again, even if you're not
super comfy with logarithms,
you do know, from our picture, with
the straight lines and the curved line,
that which is smaller?
Log of n, or n, generally speaking?
AUDIENCE: Log of n.
DAVID MALAN: Like, log
of n is smaller, right?
That's why the green line was
lower, and it was also curved.
It was below the linear line n.
So, generally speaking, the bigger
n gets, the more slowly log n grows.
And again, if you just
take on faith that this
is a mathematical expression that
communicates the time required
to do something, it's less.
So, which, therefore, is smaller?
N squared, which of course is n times n?
Or n log n?
AUDIENCE: N log n.
DAVID MALAN: N log n.
So, we've now found an algorithm that's
unlike all of the others we've seen.
And even though it took a while to
explain, and even though, frankly,
you might have to kind of sift through
it again to really wrap your mind
around it-- it took me a while, too--
it is fundamentally faster as well.
So, just to take one other stab at
this, let me show one other perspective.
At least if you're more mathematically
comfortable it after today,
if you're worried that this is way
more math than you were expecting,
realize we very quickly abstract
away from these details,
and we start to wave our hands
using big 0 and big omega.
Let's consider how we could
look at this a different way.
If the picture wasn't
really working for you,
let's see if we can just, like,
jot down how many steps each
of these lines of code is.
And there's not many
lines of code here, so it
shouldn't be a very long expression.
So, how long does it take to
decide if n is less than 2?
And, if so, return?
Well, you're past a bunch
of numbers, so, you know,
I'm going to call it constant time.
Like, you know how many
numbers you've been handed--
nope, it's not less
than 2, or yes, it is.
You're just answering yes or no.
Constant time.
Big O of one.
All right?
So I'm going to describe that as this.
This is the formal way of saying it.
T of n, which is just how much time does
it take, given a problem of size n--
just a fancy way of saying that.
It's on the order of one step.
Maybe it's two, maybe it's
three, because you kind of
got to look at something.
But it's a fixed number
of steps to decide,
there are fewer than n
elements in front of me.
It's not going to take you very long.
So, that piece of the puzzle
takes big O of one step.
So now, we have three
other questions to ask.
That's, like, kind of a throwaway.
That's really quick, if it's just one
step, or two steps, or three steps.
So, are these the expensive things?
Well, let's see.
Sort the left half of elements.
Well, here, too, I can be kind of
clever and propose the following.
You know what?
The amount of time
required to sort n elements
is technically equal
to the amount of time
it takes to sort half of those elements,
plus the amount of time required
to sort the other half of those
elements, plus, to be fair,
some merging time.
And it's essentially n, but I'm
going to generalize it as big O of n,
because I did have to
move my hands around.
But again, the key thing was, my hands
were constantly moving to the right.
There was no looping back and again, and
again, like with the other algorithms.
So it's, like, n steps
to do the merging.
If I've got 4 numbers
here, 4 numbers here,
I have to touch a total of 8 elements.
8 is n, so it feels like, yes, on the
order of n steps to do the merging.
Unfortunately, this is
like a recursive answer
to the question of how
efficient is merge sort.
But that's kind of
consistent with the fact
that merge sort is being implemented
recursively in this code.
And it turns out here,
too, if you've got
one of those old-school textbooks
that's got a cheat sheet in the front
or the back of your
physics or your math book,
this is a series that you can actually--
that mathematicians know actually
sum up to something known,
which is n times log n.
And we won't go into the weeds
of why that is, mathematically,
but if you take a problem of
size n, and add the running
time for first half, second
half, and then add an n,
this is what, mathematically,
it ends up being.
And so, if you're more
comfortable with that,
realize that this derives from just
counting up of those several steps.
And ultimately, this is
much better than that.
And in fact, we can
kind of feel this here.
You'll be able to feel it even
better with other data sets,
but let me go ahead and reload here,
and go ahead, at the same speed
as we were before, choosing merge sort.
Let me fit it onto the screen at once.
Actually, we should speed
it up to the original.
So, what is it doing?
It's using a bit of extra memory,
just as we were on the screen,
using some additional space.
But notice, as it does that work, it's
kind of moving things back and forth.
And it's actually saving space.
Even though I used log n amount
of memory by keep moving it,
this was stupid.
Like, I didn't need to keep using
more memory, more memory, more
memory, because I wasn't
using the stuff anymore above.
So with merge sort, you really
just need twice as much memory
as those other algorithms, because
the first time you need to move them,
move them here.
And then, even though I did
it visually, deliberately
to move it to yet another location,
just keep moving things back
and forth as needed.
And that's what's happening
with that algorithm there.
It's not quite as clear to see
with this visualization, so let
me open up this other one here.
Now, go.
And you'll see merge sort
all the way on the right--
done.
All right, so, insertion
sort got a little lucky here,
just because of the order of the
elements, and the size of the dataset
isn't that big, which is why I
wanted to show the other one.
But if we do it once more, you'll
see, again, that merge sort
is pretty darn quick.
And you can see it
doing things in halves.
And selection sort, and bubble
sort, are still doing their thing.
And if we did this using
not, like, what is that--
10, 20, bars total, but 100 bars?
Or a million bars?
You would really, really
feel the difference,
just as we did with the
phone book example as well.
Any questions there on that?
And we won't walk through
the code, but if you're
curious to actually see how some
of these ideas map to C code,
you will find, in the CS50 appliance,
in the source code from today,
a couple of files-- binary zero and
binary one in linear.c, all of which
implement binary search and linear
search in a couple of different ways,
if you actually want
to see how those map.
But what we thought we would
do, in our remaining time today,
is tee up one of the next
algorithmic challenges.
It turns out that there are wonderful
opportunities in computer science
to intersect with other
fields-- among them
the arts, and very specifically, music.
And it turns out that music,
whether you're an audiophile or even
a musical theoretician,
there are relationships
among the sounds that we hear and the
rate at which we hear those notes.
Which is to say, they follow patterns.
And these patterns can
be produced by computers,
they can be generated by
computers, and what we'll do,
ultimately, in problem
set three, in fact,
is introduce you to a
bit of the musical world,
whether you have some
prior experience or not.
And Brian, if you wouldn't mind coming
up just to assist with this teaser.
Here are just a few
keys from a keyboard,
and here are 88 keys
from an actual keyboard.
And Brian will help us, in just a
moment, with some of these definitions.
But you'll see here that there are eight
keys, or one, two, three, four, five,
six, seven white keys and
five black keys on the board.
And it turns out that mankind--
at least, in Western
music, years ago-- decided
to standardize on how
we describe these keys.
And we assigned letters to them.
And you might have heard of
middle C, even if you've never
played a piano before, and you might
think of that as being the leftmost key
there.
And then it's D, E, F, G, and then
A, B. And of course, on a real piano,
there's keys to the left, and
there's keys to the right.
Do you want to play what
C might sound like here?
[PIANO PLAYS]
So, that's C. And then, if
you want to-- very well done.
[APPLAUSE]
Do you want to go all the way
up through the scale to B?
[PIANO PLAYS]
That's kind of unresolved, too,
because what should have come next--
[PIANO PLAYS]
That would be another C. And so
what Brian's played for us is
a full octave, now, referring to eight.
So, C to C inclusive, in this case.
And those of us who are kind
of are familiar with music,
or like listening to
certain music, you'll
notice that certain things sound good.
And there's actually mathematical and
formulaic, or algorithmic, reasons
that some of these sounds
sound actually good.
But what about these black keys?
They actually can be defined
in a couple of different ways.
And if you've ever heard
of flats, or sharps--
Brian, do you want to explain
what the relationship now
is among the white keys and the black
keys, and how they sound different?
BRIAN: Yeah, sure.
So, a bit of terminology first.
A semi-tone is just the distance
from one note to the note
immediately after that, both
white and black notes included.
And all it means for
something to be sharp,
represented by the hashtag or
pound sign up there, is take a note
and move it up by one semi-tone.
So, if we start with C, and make
that note sharp, to C sharp,
we move one semi-tone
to the note immediately
after it, which is that black note in
between C and D. So, that's C sharp.
And likewise, if we add E sharp, that is
one semi-tone, or the note immediately
after, E, which in this case,
is the same thing as F. So,
F and E sharp are the same note.
And in the meantime, flat is
just the opposite of that.
If sharp means move up one semi-tone,
flat means move down one semi-tone.
So if I have E, E flat is one semi-tone
moving left on the piano keyboard.
DAVID MALAN: And so even though
a typical piano keyboard wouldn't
be labeled as such, it
does follow a pattern,
and it does repeat, to the
left and to the right as well.
And so as you learn to play piano,
you learn what these notes sound like,
you learn where these
keys are, and you also
learn, ultimately, how to read
music, which might look like this.
This is a familiar song, now
officially in the public domain.
And you'll see here that there are
these little shapes called notes,
or little circles, that happen
to be on specific lines.
And it turns out that if
a note is on one line,
it might represent the note A;
if it's on a different line,
higher above or down below, it might
represent B or C or D or E or F or G.
And if there is a sharp symbol,
or a flat symbol, in front of it,
that might shift it ever so
slightly, so that you're actually
touching, in many cases, one
of the black keys as well.
Which is to say that once
you have the vocabulary,
and you know what the alphabet
is to which you have access,
can you start to write it out, much
like we write computer programs.
But this is what a musician
would actually see.
And just to give us maybe a
teaser of what you can actually
do when you take into account
the different sounds of notes,
and the different pace
at which you play notes,
can you give us a little
something more than just a scale?
BRIAN: Sure.
[PIANO PLAYS]
[APPLAUSE]
DAVID MALAN: So, if you're
a little worried what
we're getting into, not only
computer science and programming,
but now music--
I am absolutely among the
least comfortable with this,
and this is why Brian has
kindly joined us here today.
But it'll be fun, we hope,
ultimately, to explore
these relationships, and also the
intersection of one field with another.
And to now tie these
topics together, we thought
we'd end by looking at
a short visualization
here, about a minute's worth of
computer-generated sounds, that
give you not just a visual
feel of some of the algorithms
and others that we've looked at
today, but also associate sounds
with the operations of moving
things, swapping things,
and ultimately touching bigger
and smaller numbers digitally.
So, here we have, up
first, insertion sort.
[COMPUTER SOUNDS]
Again, it's inserting into
the right place the number.
This, now, is bubble sort.
And again, you can both see, and
now kind of feel, all of the swaps
that it's doing.
We will get the satisfaction this time.
This, now, is selection
sort, whereby you
go through the list selecting
the next smallest element,
and plop it in its place.
And the bars are getting higher
and higher, just like the notes,
or the frequencies.
This, now, is merge sort.
And notice the halves
that are developing.
And this is by far the most gratifying
sound, at the end of this one.
This is gnome sort,
which we didn't look at,
but very distinctly has
a different shape, too.
It's not quite as ordered as the others.
And that, then, are algorithms.
And Brian, play us out for today.
Otherwise, we will see you next week.