[MUSIC PLAYING]
BENEDICT BROWN: So
welcome to CS50 at Yale.
My name is Benedict Brown.
I'm a new lecturer in
the department here.
I came from the University
of Pennsylvania,
and so I'm really excited to be
joining this in the third year.
And we have, of course, a
team from Harvard as well.
We are currently about
25% larger than last year,
which we're really excited about.
[CHEERS]
We'd love to see at the
end that we're 100% larger,
but that's our job-- to convince
you that you want to be here.
So what I'd like to do
at the start is just
tell you a little bit about
what's different this year
and introduce you to
the team here at Yale,
before I'll pass it off to David
Malan for the opening lecture.
If you've heard from your friends
about CS50 in the last couple of years,
especially last year,
not a lot has changed.
So it's pretty good advice
that you'll be getting.
One of the changes, the biggest
change probably this year--
we've got a staff of 40 TAs
that we're really excited about,
a fantastic group.
So you'll have lots and lots of
support, just like you have in the past.
In addition, after this
week most of the lectures--
there will be two more that are
done at Yale, and the rest of them
are recorded at Harvard, and
you'll be watching online.
But during this Thursday
time slot, I will
be here and talking about enrichment,
complementary information, maybe going
into a little more depth on
some of the applications,
talk about ways that you might use them
or they might connect to other fields.
So these are areas that are
not going to be on the exam.
They're not going to be graded.
They're totally
optional, but they should
be fun, help you give
a little more context,
learn a little more about what's
going on in computer science
in the field in general and how
you might use that in other areas
than we can fit into the course proper.
And so I hope that a lot
of you will enjoy coming,
and we'll see you at those.
And with that, I'd like to
also bring up Natalie Melo,
who will be the course manager and
co-head of the course with me--
[APPLAUSE]
-- and our wonderful
head TA, [INAUDIBLE]..
[APPLAUSE]
And I'm going to bring up also Natalie's
counterpart at Harvard, Doug Lloyd, who
you will not see much here at Yale.
But you will see his name a lot.
He's very involved also
in creating the course,
and so he's a good
person to have in mind.
And with that, since you'll get
to see me all semester long,
I'm going to turn it over to David.
[APPLAUSE]
[INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Thanks, [INAUDIBLE].
So thank you so much to
Benedict and the whole team.
This has been a really special
collaboration over the past three
years now, and this is indeed the third
time we're all gathering here together.
And perhaps most pointedly for
me, and for Benedict too, is he
and I actually go way back.
We were undergrads together, and I was
good friends with one of his roommates.
And I had a habit of going to their room
a lot, perhaps more often than mine.
And for whatever reason, these guys
were really into ordering pizza.
And back in the day, before there really
was Domino's as as popular of a thing,
there was a pizza ring,
which-- in Cambridge, for $8
you could get a double-decker pizza.
And it was about the quality you
would expect for $4 for a large pizza.
And these guys, and with
Benedict's blessing,
photographed this, even
before there were cell phones.
And so this was the
number of pizzas they
accumulated over the course of
a semester, maybe, or so forth.
And if you enhance there,
you'll see Benedict himself.
So we go some 20 years back, and
it's especially special for us,
I think, to be now collaborating
across these two towns.
But today we introduce CS50 itself
and, in turn, computer science.
The overarching goals of this class
is to give you an introduction
to the fundamentals of computer
science, so that if you're
interested in going on to
studying higher-level classes,
whether it's in artificial intelligence,
or graphics, or hardware, or software,
or theory, you have that
basis with which to proceed.
But it's also meant to be a
terminal course for those of you
who are perhaps non-majors
or who simply are
coming from some other field in the
sciences, the arts, natural sciences,
social sciences and beyond, who
want to bring some technical savvy
and comfort to your own field so
that when you have a large data set,
you can do something
interesting with it.
When you're working on your thesis
and you want to compute data,
you have the tools and the techniques
and the mindset with which to do that.
And so this course, ultimately, is
for majors and non-majors alike.
And that means something in particular.
In fact, years ago CS50 at Harvard was
the very first CS class I ever took.
And as I've often related to
others, I was frankly pretty daunted
by taking a CS class, let alone
this particular introduction,
which for years--
ever since my day and
Benedict's day-- has
had this reputation to sort of beware.
And daresay, a lot of students feel
that way about computer science.
It's an unfamiliar field.
They don't have any prior experience.
It feels like everyone else in the
room must surely know more than they,
and so these are barriers to actually
putting your toe in unfamiliar waters.
And I felt that way freshman year.
I didn't have the nerve to shop the
class, so to speak, freshman year.
And it was only sophomore year
that I finally got up the nerve
to go into CS50's first lecture.
And even then, it was
only because the professor
allowed me to take it pass/fail
and actually sign that sheet.
And that helped me get
over the mental hurdle.
And I found, of all things, that
I actually loved this world.
And it was so empowering
that just with my laptop--
which for years I'd been using to
write essays and other mundane things--
it's just so empowering to be able
to create something with that device.
And I had initially
strayed away from this.
I had studied government
initially, and I
had banged out half of the
requirements for the major at Harvard.
And I gravitated toward government
only because, frankly, I
was familiar with it.
In high school I liked history
and constitutional law,
and those kind of felt like the
closest fit to political science
or to government.
And so I just stayed
on this familiar path,
and it was only once I stepped
off of it, so to speak,
that I found this new world
where homework was genuinely fun.
And I felt challenged
and sort of inspired
to be able to create things from
truly nothing, everything now digital.
And if it's any reassurance,
68% of you here and in Cambridge
have never taken a CS class before.
So if you're among those who, like me,
was a little timid about considering
some new field or a
class like this, realize
that a majority of the people around
you are feeling exactly the same way.
And in fact, in CS50 we've long had
this tradition of different tracks,
so to speak, or comfort
levels within the class--
for those less comfortable,
those more comfortable,
and those somewhere in between.
And these are just unofficial labels
that you kind of know it if you are.
If you sort of have one
foot halfway, mentally,
out the door because you're
not sure if this is for you,
you're probably among those less
comfortable-- never programmed before.
You're not a computer
person and so forth.
If you've been programming
since you were six years old,
but it was a lot of
self-teaching, and you
have a lot of gaps in your
knowledge, maybe you're
among those more comfortable, or
you're indeed somewhere in between.
And these percentages--
about 56% less comfortable
was the breakdown from
students just a few years ago.
And in fact, this past summer some of
our team from Harvard and Yale spent
a while traveling around and visiting
former teachers and students of CS50
and discussing with them the challenges
that they faced in computer science
or as an on-ramp there to--
the kinds of exposure they had
or lack thereof to the field.
And so you'll see this in the
course's first problem set next week,
but you'll see at project5050.org.
We have a lot of these
stories or vignettes
about folks who have come before you,
if you'd like to get a sense of folks
with similarly disparate
backgrounds that
may have come through here before--
and later on, some Spotify.
So what's most important,
though, is this--
this is perhaps the most telling
statement in the course's syllabus,
which you probably
received on the way in,
which is that what ultimately matters
in this course is not so much where you
end up relative to each
your classmates, but where
you, in week 11, the end of the
semester, end up relative to yourself
in week 0, right now and here.
So far as grades go, so
far as progress goes,
the course really does very deliberately
and very manually consider that delta,
from now until the end of
the semester, independent
of any knowledge or experience or
lack thereof that you might have.
But toward that end, and to
put our toes in these waters,
let's consider what computer
science is really about.
Odds are, if you're
like me, you probably
had this perception in high
school that it's programming.
And in fact, I still remember
kind of looking through the glass
door of our computer science
classroom in high school,
seeing all of my
friends with their heads
down, typing away at the keyboard.
And it seemed completely asocial.
It seemed completely uninspiring.
The door was literally closed,
fluorescent lights, desktop computers
back in the day.
It just didn't seem at
all appealing to me.
But if you take a step
back from that and consider
it's really computer science,
a field about problem
solving-- and yes, we have tools,
both in our pockets, and on our laps,
and on our desk these days that make
it easier to solve problems quickly.
At the end of the day, it's all about
cleaning up your thought process
and trying to think a
little more precisely
so that you can express
yourself not only correctly
but efficiently when it comes to
making a computer do something,
or even writing more
persuasive arguments in English
or any other native language.
And to give you a sense of the kinds
of problems we used in the class
last year as the backbone via which to
explore some constructs, some of which
we'll dive in today, last
year we started the semester
with Scratch, a graphical
programming language.
And we'll see a little
bit of that today.
That allows you to drag and drop
puzzle pieces, not unlike the adverts
you might have in your hands here
for CS50's tradition of Puzzle Day
this weekend, that lets you program
by interlocking these puzzle pieces.
We then introduced C, a fairly
old language, but a small language
that's pretty Greek-like,
so to speak, for those
who don't actually speak Greek.
And you have the ability in C to go
even closer to the computer's hardware
and make things move around in
memory very, very digitally,
as we'll soon see.
And then we introduced
the world of cryptography,
the art of scrambling or
enciphering information
to keep messages secure or safe.
Game of 15, that little up, down,
left, right puzzle piece thing
that you might have
gotten in a party favor
as a kid, where you try to
order the numbers-- that
lends itself to a
discussion of algorithms,
procedures for solving problems.
Forensics-- we often take photos, either
from online or from a digital camera,
and accidentally delete them, and then
hand you a forensic image, so to speak,
of the memory card and have
you write software in C
to recover those images, something that
you yourself might have had occasion
to need, if you've ever had corrupted
or deleted files accidentally.
Misspellings-- deliberately
misspelled there,
because we give you a dictionary
of 150,000 English words
and challenge you to write code to
load all of those words from a big file
into your computer's memory and somehow
spell-check really big files quickly,
much like Microsoft Word and
Google Docs does for you,
but thinking about how you can
actually determine if something
is spelled rightly or wrongly.
And then we transition
to web programming,
sort of a more modern
paradigm, certainly what
you and I all interact with
pretty much daily these days,
anything in a web browser.
And we introduce you to Python,
and JavaScript, and SQL,
and a few other languages too.
And we have you implement, for instance,
your own stock-trading web site,
talking to Yahoo Finance,
getting real-time stock quotes
and actually simulating the process
of buying and selling stocks
and then mashing up, ultimately,
Google News and Google Maps
and creating visualizations
of information.
So all of this, especially those
68% of you with no prior background,
will have been completed by
you in just three months' time.
And we'll have a scaffolding process
and a step-wise approach to this.
But ultimately you'll
find, hopefully, as I
did long ago, that this
process of problem solving
accelerates once you
learn these basics here,
and then assume those from the
prior week and build on top of them,
build on top of them,
build on top of them.
And you'll be struck by just how far
you've come by the end of one semester.
So let's consider what we mean
by problem solving itself.
We could, perhaps, distill it pretty
simply as just this, like a black box.
So we don't know what's inside of it.
We don't know how problems
are going to be solved.
But at the end of the
day, what's a problem?
It's something that's got input,
and the goal is to get output.
You want to solve that
problem-- a very generic way,
but a very simple way of describing
what it means to solve a problem.
Now, the secret sauce is going
to be what's inside that box.
But we'll come back to
that in just a moment.
First, we have to consider how to
represent inputs and outputs, right?
At the end of the day, you have
a laptop on your lap or desk.
You've got a phone in your pocket,
maybe some kind of smart watch
and other devices.
And you probably know, even if
you're not a computer person,
that these computer devices only
speak one language, so to speak,
at the end of the day.
What is that-- yeah?
AUDIENCE: Binary.
DAVID MALAN: Binary, so binary--
bi, meaning two, and
that alludes to the fact
that computers only understand two
digits, 0's and 1's, though you
could call them anything you want.
But humans decided years ago
to think of it as 0 and 1.
Now, why might that be the case?
Well, it's kind of handy that
the physical input to computers,
whether it's from a plug
in the wall or if you've
pre-charged a battery-- you
have some form of electrons,
the ability for electrons to flow.
That too is kind of a physical input
that you could either visualize or just
proceed with some kind of measure.
And if we visualize this with
something like this, my phone
right now, with the flashlight
off, might be representing a 0.
And if I, instead, just
turn the flashlight on,
now I might be said to
be representing a 1.
And so long as I have a physical
resource like electricity,
I can turn something on or off,
and therefore represent a 1 or a 0.
So already, even though I have no
idea really how my computer works,
or my phone, or any other
such electronic device,
I know I have to plug
it in once in a while.
And I know that gives me electrons
or electricity from the wall.
That is the physical resource
that we can somehow now map,
so to speak, to just
0's and 1's, off and on.
But what can we now do with
this kind of information?
How do computers represent numbers,
and letters, and graphics, and videos,
and all these fancier
things we now have?
Well, let's consider what we
already know, which might be this--
computers, of course, speak binary.
We humans speak, as you probably
recall, decimal-- dec meaning 10,
so we have 0 through
9 in our vocabulary.
But what does it mean to
actually represent numbers?
So this number 123--
why do all of us have a very
intuitive notion of what that is,
upon seeing these symbols on the board?
1, 2, 3-- it's just
a pattern of symbols,
glyphs that I've drawn
artistically on the board.
But why do they have meaning?
Well, if you're like me,
back in grade school,
you probably learned that the 3 is
in the what's place, so to speak?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so it's in the
ones place or the ones column.
And then this is the tens place,
and this is the hundreds place.
And then the reason
that this is 123 and not
just some artistic pattern
of symbols anymore--
it has a mathematical meaning-- is
because if this 1 is in the 100s place,
this is like 1 times 100.
And this is now 2 times 10,
and this is now 3 times 1.
This, of course, is 100 plus 20 plus 3.
And of course, at the end of the
day, we still write it the same way.
But now you think of
it as an aggregate--
123.
Well, if you're on the same page as
me with this, if everyone in the room
is already comfortable,
certainly, with these fundamentals
that we've long taken for granted, let's
just change the paradigm a little bit.
We had powers of 10 a moment ago--
ones, tens, hundreds, thousands, ten
thousands, hundred
thousands if we kept going.
Those are all powers of 10.
Specifically, it's 10 to the 0, 10
to the 1, 10 to the 2, 10 to the 3,
and so forth.
And that's because we have 10
digits in the decimal system
that we humans tend to use.
But of course, in the
binary system, we have two.
So if we have powers of 2,
what should these values be?
2 to the 0, 2 to the 1, 2 to the 2--
so what should this
rightmost column represent?
2 to the 0 in this case, so
that's just the ones place still.
2 to the 1 is the twos
place, and 2 to the 2
is now the fours place, and so forth--
8, 16, 32, 64, 128, 256.
You can go on forever, but
it's just the same thing.
So what then, in binary,
does this represent?
What decimal number does a pattern
of three 0's in binary represent?
It's just 0, because it's 0 times
4 plus 0 times 2 plus 0 times 1.
All right, that's surely quite easy.
What about this?
What's this number in binary,
if you convert it to decimal?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah,
it's just the number 1.
And then, of course, if we just
change this, it's the number--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, good,
it's 3, all right?
You might be inclined
initially to say 2,
because it's like hash
marks on the board.
But that's not quite the same thing,
because we have a 0 in the fours,
1 in the twos, 1 in the ones.
And so this means we now have
the ability to count to 3.
And if we want to
change this to 2, we're
going to have to change
this back to a 0.
And if we really quickly
erase all of this,
and just do this, what's the highest
we can count with just three places?
Not eight per se, but--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: 7, and it's not
8, because we're starting at 0.
So it's eight total values, but 7 is
the highest one that we can actually go.
And so after this, just to be clear,
we might have the eights place,
the sixteens place, the
thirty-twos place, and the--
damn it.
We've run out of room for a
byte, so we'll do this again.
And we have the
hundred-and-twenty-eights place, 64,
32, 16, 8, 4, 2, 1.
And just to take, maybe, the
pressure off me for a second,
could a brave volunteer come
on up and answer one problem--
not only in front of everyone,
but on the internet as well?
And we can sweeten it with
a little CS50 stress ball.
Oh, there we go, OK, come on up.
What's your name?
AUDIENCE: [? Mikhail. ?]
DAVID MALAN: [? Mikhail, ?] come on up.
All right, so this shall be yours if--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Nice to meet you.
Go ahead and represent
for us in binary--
so 0's and 1's-- the number 50, using
a piece of chalk and putting a number
in each of those columns, the number 50.
And now as he does this,
it's no coincidence
that I deliberately made room
for 8 bits on the screen.
If you've ever heard of a byte,
B-Y-T-E, a byte is just 8 bits.
It's a collection of eight
0's and 1's together.
Why is it a convention?
It's just a nicer number to
deal with than individual bits.
Eights is a nice unit of measure.
And [? Mikhail ?] here, indeed, gave
us 32 plus 16, which gives us 48.
Toss in another 2, and you get
a stress ball-- congratulations,
thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
So what's the take-away here?
So if you've ever known that computers
speak binary, 0's and 1's, you
probably vaguely knew
something like that.
But it's actually not
all that inaccessible.
If you didn't even
know this before, it's
just a step away from
what we all grew up with.
And binary and decimal
aren't even the only two.
We'll see hexadecimal down the road.
There's base-64, and there's
base- any number you want--
it's just some of these conventions
tend to be more popular than others.
So it suffices to say now that
computers can clearly count from 0 to 1
or even much higher, just
by using multiple bits.
In fact, if you wanted to
count even higher than this,
we just need a 256 place,
a 512 place, and so forth.
So we can just keep doing
what we do in the human world,
just keep adding more and
more numbers to the left.
But numbers are just one thing.
Computers, of course, let
me send emails these days,
and I can see pictures
and movies on the screen.
So how do we get from 0's and 1's--
or, really, electricity-- to 0's
and 1's, to numbers, and now sort
of a higher-level notion of a letter?
Well, humans some time
ago essentially decided
to standardize things, whereby the
world decided that, you know what?
If you're writing a
program, and you want
to show the user the capital letter
A, you simply want to use 8 bits--
technically 7, but generally
8 bits these days--
arranged in a pattern that
represents the decimal number 65.
And so if the user is using a
program like Microsoft Word instead
of a calculator, he or she will see
the letter A instead of the number 65,
for instance.
So it's just context sensitive,
depending on the type of software
the human is actually using.
If you want a B, number 66.
If you want an H, 72,
73 for I, and so forth.
And the dot, dot, dot just suggests
that someone thought it all through,
so we've got lowercase-- we've got
punctuation and a few other symbols.
But they didn't really
leave them that much room.
In fact, if you're using 8 bits,
how many total possible values
can you represent with 8 bits,
each of which can be a 0 or 1?
It turns out it's like 2 times 2.
It's 256 total possible values.
If you've got 1 byte or 8 bits,
it's only 256 possible values.
And if that's not immediately
obvious, totally fine-- just
take on faith that it's 256.
There's a lot more than that many
characters in other languages
than, say, English or romance languages.
In a lot of Asian languages,
you need many more symbols
or glyphs than that allows.
And so now the world has not
just ASCII, but something
called Unicode, which uses not 8, but
maybe 16 or even more bits, as needed.
So we've solved at least that
problem, but it doesn't just
have to be letters that we encode.
Consider this as well--
here's a pattern of 3 bytes, I claim.
It's not that much fun
to see things in binary
all the time, because it would
take me a while to figure out
what the pattern represents.
So we're just going to
use decimal for now.
And if you see 3 bytes, which
represent 72, 73, 33, what message
might be embedded on the screen here?
These are three ASCII
or Unicode characters.
What message is encoded
if it's 72, 73, 33?
You can get at least 2/3 of the answer.
What have we said?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Hi.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so it's
hi, H-I, and then something.
And you wouldn't know unless you
looked this up or knew it in advance.
33 happens to be the
exclamation point, so
what we've represented here in,
say, Microsoft Word or an email,
or a text message, or whatever
is the message "HI!"--
simply by storing 24 bits, 8 bits, 8
bits, 8 bits, each of which represents
those values.
But suppose you don't want to
send an email or write a message.
You actually want to use Photoshop
or something or a graphics program
more generally.
Well, it turns out if,
at the end of the day,
your computer only
understands 0's and 1's,
you have to decide on a mapping sort
of a translation between 0's and 1's
and things like colors.
And so humans decided some
years ago that very often--
certainly for very colorful images--
we will use 24 bits for
colors instead, 8 of which
represent how much red you
want on the screen, 8 of which
represent how much green, 8 of which
represent how much blue you want.
Thus was born RGB, for red, green, blue.
And so together, if you have 0
red, it would just be all 0 bits.
All the light bulbs are off,
so to speak, in the computer.
If you want a lot of
red, it'd be 8 1's--
all the light bulbs
go on in the computer,
and that means give me a lot of red.
Then you say give me some amount
of green, some amount of blue,
and then you mix them
together like waves of light.
And you get, ultimately, one color.
And it turns out, if you actually
combine 72 out of 256 or 255 of red
and 73, which are medium amounts,
and then just a little bit of blue,
because 33 isn't that
big of a number, you
get this very hard to see, on this
projector, shade of yellow or brown.
And so it's using the same pattern of
0's and 1's, the same pattern of bits.
But in a different context,
these bits, barely,
are representing a big square of yellow.
And if you've ever looked on
your computer screen really close
or your phone, you might see these
tiny, tiny little squares or dots called
pixels.
And those are, indeed, each
generally using 24 bits--
some red, some green, some blue--
to give you some color of the rainbow.
So these sort of baby
steps that we've taken,
starting with electricity and
then 0's and 1's and then letters
of the alphabet-- or in another
context, images, or rather colors--
is all about abstraction--
taking pretty simple, if
not uninteresting ideas,
and then using them as ingredients
to build up more interesting notions.
So electricity is just
flowing from the wall.
What could I possibly do with that?
Well, if I let it flow, I claim
I'm going to represent a 1.
If I turn it off, I'm
going to represent a 0.
That now gives me a vocabulary,
the binary alphabet.
Once I have 0's and
1's, we've seen, just
like [? Mikhail, ?] we can put
patterns of them together--
8 different light bulbs.
And turning them on and off
in different permutations
lets me represent much bigger
numbers than 1, like the number 50.
And of course, if we now just decide
as humans that, hmm, some of those bits
represent red, some of them
represent green, some represent blue,
we can all decide that, oh.
Well, I'm looking at, really, a
pattern of 1's that's a color.
And I never again--
after today, frankly--
never again need to know or care what
binary is or how electricity works.
But I know that it exists, and
I know that I've abstracted away
on top of that to come up with
higher-level ideas that are actually
interesting to me.
If I'm an artist dealing with colors,
I don't care how you represent it.
I want them to exist, but what
we'll do in this kind of class
is peel back those layers, look
underneath the hood, so to speak,
so that you at least understand
these building blocks.
And so even though today you might
look at software on your computer
or projects that your
friends are working
on as well beyond your
own familiarity, that's
just because they've been layering,
maybe for more weeks or more semesters
than you.
And it just takes some
step-wise approach
to building up that
same knowledge yourself.
So that's how we might
represent inputs and outputs.
But what's inside the
black box, the secret sauce
to which I alluded earlier?
This is the so-called algorithm.
And an algorithm, in
someone's own words, is what?
What's an algorithm, if
you're familiar-- yeah?
AUDIENCE: A step-by-step
process for solving something?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, a step-by-step
process for solving something--
so it's like step-by-step instructions.
Step 1, do this; step 2, do that;
step 3, do this; and so forth.
It's just-- that's an algorithm.
It's a process for solving problems,
albeit under the guise of some fancier
word.
So how do we go about using
algorithms in interesting ways?
Well, at the risk of being a little
overboard, let me move this over here.
And we have come prepared
with some supplies here.
We've got some paper towel, we've
got some white Wonder Bread,
we've got some creamy
Skippy peanut butter.
And we've got some Smucker's
grape jelly and a knife--
and, I discovered too late, no plate.
So we're going to use some paper
towel here and see if we can't
craft an algorithm together, all right?
I learned this in fifth grade, when my
homeroom teacher, back in fifth grade,
used this as an example to teach us
how to follow instructions correctly.
But the reality is, it's actually
wonderfully demonstrative too
of how precise and how correct you
need to be when feeding instructions
to a computer, because
computers, at the end of the day,
as fancy as they might seem,
are pretty dumb devices.
After all, they were
designed by and programmed
by us humans and our own
limitations, and so they can only
do exactly what we tell them to do.
So suppose that what I
want a computer to do
is make a peanut butter
and jelly sandwich.
I'll take on that role,
for the sake of discussion.
Consider me, for the moment, a computer
or a robot if having some kind of form
helps.
And you guys will be the
programmers, verbally.
So if we were to make a peanut
butter and jelly sandwich here,
step 1 in this process might be what?
You want to begin for us?
What's your name?
RACHEL: Rachel.
DAVID MALAN: Rachel, what
might step 1 be for--
RACHEL: Open the bag
with the bread in it.
DAVID MALAN: Open the
bag with the bread in it.
So I, taking this completely literally,
simply do what Rachel has said.
It's correct, but probably
not the program you intended.
So it's OK-- we're now one
step closer to something.
But let's see if we can't now make
step 2 ever-more precise-- step
2, someone else, yeah?
AUDIENCE: Manipulate plastic--
DAVID MALAN: Manipulate plastic, OK.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: And take out what?
AUDIENCE: A whole slice.
DAVID MALAN: Take out a whole slice of
bread, after manipulating the plastic,
OK.
OK, good, we've got the
bread out-- step 3, yeah?
AUDIENCE: Get a knife,
but not by the sharp end.
DAVID MALAN: OK, get a knife--
thank you-- but not from the sharp end--
step 4?
Step 4-- yeah?
AUDIENCE: Put the bread
on the paper towel.
DAVID MALAN: Put the bread on
the paper towel, OK-- step 5?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, over here?
AUDIENCE: Pick up the
jar of peanut butter.
DAVID MALAN: Pick up the jar
of peanut butter, and then--
AUDIENCE: Yeah, unscrew the
lid from the peanut butter.
DAVID MALAN: Thank you, unscrew
the lid from the peanut butter--
OK, next step?
AUDIENCE: Remove film from the jar.
DAVID MALAN: Thank you,
remove film from the jar--
all right, next, yeah?
AUDIENCE: Plunge your knife into it.
[LAUGHTER]
DAVID MALAN: Thank you, next step?
We're not that much
closer to a sandwich yet--
next step, yeah?
AUDIENCE: Remove [INAUDIBLE]
[LAUGHTER]
DAVID MALAN: OK, 100
grams, here you are--
what's next?
AUDIENCE: Put down the jar.
DAVID MALAN: Put down
the jar [INAUDIBLE]..
OK, literally correct.
AUDIENCE: Place the peanut
butter on the knife onto bread.
DAVID MALAN: Place the peanut
butter on the knife onto the bread.
AUDIENCE: Evenly.
AUDIENCE: Gently.
DAVID MALAN: Evenly and gently,
lovely, OK, that's pretty good--
nice, now what?
AUDIENCE: Place knife down.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, sorry, wait--
thank you, place knife down.
AUDIENCE: Open the [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Open the jar of jelly.
AUDIENCE: Repeat the exact same
thing as you just did [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: OK, so we
manipulated the plastic, OK.
[LAUGHTER]
We put this down.
We plunged the knife--
100 grams of jelly.
We gently and evenly
spread the jelly, nice--
and?
AUDIENCE: Put the bread together.
DAVID MALAN: Put the bread together--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: In the peanut
butter and jelly side, yeah.
OK, [INAUDIBLE] pretty good.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you, so for the first time-- we
did this once before, a few months ago,
and someone was one step
ahead of me and, I think,
added, "Smear peanut
butter on your face."
Thank you, all right, so
anyhow, this was a little--
this was certainly
organic, and it wasn't
necessarily as precise as could be.
And even though I was
being a bit histrionic,
I was really taking the
instructions literally,
which suggests even in
something as trivial
as this, that we humans take
for granted in real life,
there are certainly opportunities to
be ambiguous, which probably isn't
a good thing, and to be imprecise, which
probably yields unexpected results.
And frankly, in our human world,
when you're using a Mac, or a PC,
or your iPhone, or your
Android, and maybe you
see a spinning beach-ball
or an hourglass,
or the thing just freezes or crashes,
those are unforeseen circumstances.
Odds are there was a human who wrote
some code at Apple, or Microsoft,
or Google, or wherever, and he or she
did not anticipate some situation,
did not anticipate you
clicking over there,
doing this so quickly,
or some other unforeseen circumstance,
because they weren't thinking
through all of the
possible scenarios, just
as we weren't necessarily a moment ago.
So it's ever-more
important to be precise
and to express yourself in
some kind of standard way.
We were just using English
pretty organically.
But of course, computers,
as you may know,
have some kinds of
programming languages.
But there's a generic one that
we might call simply pseudocode.
Pseudocode is not a formal language.
There's no book about it.
It's just a very general sort of casual
way, but precise way when possible,
of expressing yourself using
as few words in English
or your native language as possible.
So let's consider an actual problem
that isn't quite as messy as that.
Here is an old-school
technology called a phone book.
It's increasingly dated,
of course, and most of us--
these are hard to find, physically.
But we'll use it as
demonstrative of, frankly,
a technology we're still using.
All of us in this room probably
have an iPhone or an Android
or whatever that has a
contacts application.
And in your contacts are probably
all of your friends and family
and so forth alphabetically-- maybe
by first name, maybe by last name.
And all of those folks have
phone numbers and maybe
email addresses and more these days.
So that's really the same thing, right?
This is a physical form
of that app these days,
but I have a whole bunch of
names, a whole bunch of numbers
that are somehow alphabetized.
So even though this problem is
solved by computers more digitally,
we can see it in the human world a
little more graphically with this older
format.
So here is a phone book, and suppose
I want to find an old friend of mine,
like Mike Smith.
I could certainly simply open
the beginning of the book,
look down at the page,
and look for Mike Smith--
not there, obviously, because
this is probably the A section.
And so I might turn the page and
look, turn the page and look.
I'm still not seeing Mike.
Maybe I eventually hit
the Bs, but I'm not
going to see Mike really until I
get to the S section, for Smith,
way back when.
So this is correct or incorrect,
this process for finding Mike Smith--
starting at the beginning and
looking one page at a time?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's correct.
It's kind of stupid, but it's correct.
It's just very inefficient,
because it's going
to take me forever, especially when
I know a little something about S
in the alphabet.
So at least I learned in grade school
too, if I can do something faster,
I could do it by twos--
so 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12.
Still going to take me a while,
but it's literally twice as fast.
Is it correct?
AUDIENCE: No.
DAVID MALAN: No, why
not, or kind of why?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Right,
so it's a bit faster,
but it's not fast enough, because
if I counted this high by twos,
we're still going to be here forever.
AUDIENCE: You might
[? skip Mike ?] [? Smith. ?]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, and it's
also buggy, so to speak.
A bug in a computer
program is a mistake,
something you didn't anticipate.
And what if Mike, when
I'm going by twos,
just happens to be in between those
two pages, such that I fly by him
and never notice him?
So at least I've got to have
a little bit of a check here.
If I hit the T section,
definitely gone too far.
So maybe I should backpedal at least
one page to check if Mike is there.
So it's incorrect if
I'm just going by twos,
but we can fix it by just going
back a little bit in the phone book.
But this, too, is naive and
silly, even though it's correct.
What would be the more intuitive
approach that most of us use,
if we ever do this anymore-- yeah?
AUDIENCE: Flip it open to where
you know [INAUDIBLE] probably be,
and then go back [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, flip it
open to roughly the section,
and maybe I didn't go far enough.
I landed in the M section,
so roughly halfway through.
What do I know about the problem
in front of me right now?
Where is Mike?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: He's to your left
side, or he's my right side.
And so I know the M through Zs are
here, and the As through Ms are here.
But what's nice about this
technology is we can literally
tear the problem in half, which is very
easy when you do it down the spine.
You can tear the problem in
half, throw half of-- if I may--
the problem-- sorry--
half of the problem away.
But I'm left with now, fundamentally,
the same problem, right?
I might have had 1,000 pages a moment
ago, but now I have the same problem.
It's just half as big, 500 pages.
And if I do it again, now
I went a little too far.
Now I'm in the T section, and so
I can tear the problem in half
again, find myself with a
quarter of the problem--
250 pages.
And I can repeat, and I can repeat
and repeat, until finally I'm
probably left with just one page.
So how much faster is this algorithm?
Before, by twos, it
didn't feel much faster.
But can we quantify or describe how
much faster this third algorithm was?
What's happening every time I
tear the phone book in half?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Say again?
AUDIENCE: You split the problem in half.
DAVID MALAN: I split
the problem in half.
And so that invites the
question, how many times can you
split the problem in half?
I went from 1,000 pages, to 500,
to 250, to 125, and so forth,
as opposed to our first
two algorithms, which was--
I went from 1,000 to 999,
to 998, to 997, or even
the second approach from 1,000,
to 998, 996, 994, and so forth.
It's still much, much slower.
And we can visualize this as follows--
we don't need to get too formal here,
but let me go ahead and pull it up as
follows.
Here might be a depiction--
let me dim the lights a little bit.
Here might be a depiction of just
an x, y graph where on the x-axis,
the horizontal is the
size of the problem.
So the farther right you
get, the bigger the problem,
so the more phone book pages there are.
On the y-axis or vertical
I call it "time to solve."
So that might be the
number of seconds it takes
you to find someone in the phone book.
So the higher you go on the y-axis,
the more time it's going to take.
The relationship between size and time
in the first algorithm is just linear.
It's a straight line.
And you can think of it
as follows-- if Verizon
or whoever the phone
company is, tomorrow,
adds one more page to the phone
book because more people moved
into New Haven, well, it's
going to take you maybe one more
step to find Mike Smith, because
the phone book's one page longer.
So there's this linear
slope, a straight line.
The second algorithm is still
linear, because if Verizon
adds two pages tomorrow, it's
going to take you one more second.
Or if they add one page, it's
going to take you a half second.
But it's this constant difference,
so we still have this straight line.
But notice the yellow
line is below the red,
because for a given size
problem, which should be faster--
the first algorithm or
the second algorithm?
AUDIENCE: The second [? algorithm. ?]
DAVID MALAN: The second, and
the speed of the algorithm,
again, is based on the y-axis.
So because the yellow line
is below the red line,
that just implies that it's faster.
There's less time required
for the second algorithm.
But what's amazing about that
third algorithm-- which, frankly,
all of us probably intuitively
would have done in the first place,
had I not coaxed us through
the more naive approaches--
looks like this.
This green line, among the
three, is the best objectively,
in so far as it's a
fundamentally different shape.
Notice it's not even a straight line.
It's curved, and though it looks
like it's kind of flattening out,
it never actually flattens out.
It just grows ever, ever more
slowly the bigger the problem gets.
But it requires massively less time.
Why is that?
Well, in this third algorithm,
Verizon, for instance,
tomorrow could double the
size of the phone book.
Instead of 1,000 pages, they
may be merged the town over,
and so it's 2,000 pages
in the phone book.
That's huge, but how many more steps
is it going to take if you're dividing
and conquering the problem by
tearing the phone book in half?
It's going to take just one more step.
And if Verizon quadruples the size
of the phone book, no big deal--
two more steps.
Put another way, let's consider
a ridiculously large phone book.
If you've got a phone book with,
like, 4 billion pages, which is huge,
how many times might I have to tear
a 4-billion-page phone book in half
before I'm left with one page, on
which Mike Smith is or simply isn't?
Well, how many times can
you divide 4 billion in 2?
4 billion, to 2 billion, to 1
billion, to 500 million, to 250--
we could keep going, but I'm pretty
quickly going to get to one page,
because you can only divide 4 billion
roughly 32 times before you're
left with just one page.
And that's where computer
science, and that's
where algorithms start to get
interesting and powerful, but also
accessible.
This intuition you've
long had is already
something you have a grasp
over for solving problems.
It's just a matter now of deploying
these ideas in the context of computers
and deploying them in
the context of a computer
that you can be ever so precise
with, per this mention of pseudocode.
What would it mean for me to
solve that problem a moment ago?
Well, let's not just talk about it.
Let's actually apply
a couple of steps more
methodically in an English-like
syntax, pseudocode.
My first step, otherwise known
as 0-- and computer scientists
tend to number things at 0, just
because that's the lowest you can count,
instead of our more
human convention of 1.
Pick up the phone book--
just do this.
It's an action or a verb.
Step 1, open to middle of phone book.
That's what I did for
that third algorithm too.
Step 2, look at names--
that's a third action I did.
If Smith is among names--
now, this phrase is fundamentally
different from the first three.
It starts with the key word if, so
this is kind of a decision point.
If Smith is among names, maybe do
this, and if he's not, maybe do this.
So it's like this proverbial fork in
the road, or a condition, or a branch.
And so we're going to call Mike if
he is among the names on the page.
And I've indented it here,
as is common in programming,
to imply that you should
only do step 4 if step 3 is
applicable-- is true, so to speak.
Otherwise, step 5, if Smith is
earlier in the book-- to the left,
so to speak--
what should I instead do, if
Mike is to the left of the book?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Say again?
If Mike is to the left--
AUDIENCE: Rip the book
in half [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Yes, rip, right,
so before I do the ripping,
jump to the middle of
the left half, open
to the middle of the left half of
the book, and then go back to step 2.
Rip, because I've already done that in
the past, so if I go back to step 2,
that's look at names.
So I've jumped to the
middle of the left half,
and now I'm looking for Smith again.
So that's when I said earlier,
it's the same problem.
It's just gotten a little smaller.
You can still use the same algorithm,
the same process, or the same code.
Else, if Smith is later
in the book, to the right,
what do you want to do instead?
You can open to the middle
of the right half of the book
and then go back to step
2 again, look for Mike.
You've divided the problem in half.
Else, what's this final
branch in the road?
If he's not among the names,
and if he's not to the left,
and he's not to the right,
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: He's not there,
and so we might as well just
give up or quit the program
altogether, so four possible scenarios.
And again, if you've ever seen
your phone or your computer
just have a spinning beach-ball or it
freezes or does something unexpected,
maybe it's simply because that
program, or a Google, or Facebook,
or wherever just forgot that
there's four possible scenarios.
Maybe he or she only thought of
three of them or two of them,
and so when you don't think about
all the possible cases or scenarios,
undefined behavior might happen.
Computer might crash, computer might
hang, or something else all together.
Now, in reality, this pseudocode could
be written in any number of ways.
But what I've highlighted here in yellow
is a few of the fundamental constructs
that you'll see in pseudocode, in C, in
Python, in Scratch and other languages
still--
pick up, open to, look at,
call, open, open, quit.
These are verbs.
These are actions.
Henceforth, we're going
to call them functions.
These are built-in capabilities
of a computer that allow
you to just do something actionable.
In yellow now are different
keywords if, else if, else if, else,
and these are the keywords
in many programming
languages via which you make decisions.
You go left or right, or you
choose some other fork in the road.
Now in yellow here is
what we're going to call
a little more fancifully
Boolean expressions, named
after, literally, a person named Boole.
And Boolean expressions
are simply questions
that have yes or no answers or,
more geekily, true or false answers.
So for instance, Smith
among names, question mark--
true or false, he either is
or isn't, yes or no, true
or false, 1 or 0, if you will.
If Smith is earlier
in the book, that too
is a yes/no or a true or false question.
It's a Boolean expression, and same
for the other things in yellow.
And then lastly, we have this.
Go back to step 2.
There's different ways, as we'll
see, of expressing things that
happen again, and again, and again.
But this is perhaps the most literal--
go back to step 2,
where you already were.
And just conceptually,
that suggests you're
going to do something again,
because you're going back
in your sets of instructions.
So with that said, let's
transition now to actually using
this programmatically,
writing a program.
Now, in just a few
days' time, our programs
are going to pretty quickly
look like this, which is
the Greek to which I alluded earlier.
This is a programming language called C.
And C is a fairly arcane or traditional
language.
It's purely textual, uses
a lot of funky punctuation
like curly braces, and
parentheses, and semi-colons,
things that you might
not type super commonly.
But they've probably been on
your keyboard all this time.
But even though this might
not look familiar to you,
if you've never programmed
before, just take a guess.
If you've never programmed, what does
this program, once run on a Mac or PC,
probably do--
yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Oh, sorry, go ahead.
AUDIENCE: It says, "Hello, world."
DAVID MALAN: It says, "Hello, world."
I don't quite know what printf
means, but it sounds like print.
And so printf hello world
probably does exactly that.
It shows the phrase "Hello,
world" on the screen.
And indeed, that's exactly what it does.
But for now, let's actually do
things a little more graphically,
not to make things
unnecessarily childlike,
but because it allows us to now
not worry about the parentheses,
not worry about the curly
braces, the semi-colons,
all of these frankly stupid
syntactic details that get easier
and more familiar after some time.
But the ideas needn't be--
they needn't be a distraction
in the face of ideas.
This is, in a programming language
called Scratch, the equivalent program.
So our friends down the road
in Cambridge at MIT's Media Lab
have a group called the
Lifelong Kindergarten group.
And this is a research
group that some years ago
created this graphical programming
language called Scratch.
And it is assembled
via these puzzle pieces
that have puzzle-piece-like shapes
to them that you can drag and drop
and interconnect in order to
make the computer do something.
And specifically, if I go ahead
and open this up, you'll see here--
the program itself, Scratch, it
turns out it exists in two forms.
There's a downloadable version, which
I tend to use on my computer in class,
just so that we don't have Wi-Fi issues.
But you can also go to
scratch.mit.edu, which
you will for the course's first
homework assignment, problem set 0.
And you'll see this user interface,
whether you're online or offline.
In the top left-hand corner here--
let me just dim it for a moment--
you'll see the so-called
stage for Scratch.
This is his little
two-dimensional world,
and cat is the character by
default that we can manipulate.
It's a sprite, so to speak, a
character in a computer program.
And he can move up, down, left,
right and do other things too.
In the middle is a palette
of all of our puzzle pieces.
And if I zoom in here,
you'll see a few things.
This puzzle piece says
move some number of steps.
This puzzle piece says turn
some number of degrees.
If I zoom out and go to Control, which
is just a different category and color
of blocks, notice some other blocks--
Forever, and Repeat, and Wait, and If.
And even though these might
not be wholly familiar,
you can probably just
kind of use your intuition
to understand what
these things are doing.
And even though they're
a fixed size, we'll
see that they can grow to fill shapes.
So I'm going to do this,
and it's quick for me
just because I've done this before.
But if I go to the Events
category and drag this piece--
when green flag clicked--
this is a special puzzle
piece that starts the program,
because as you can see, at
top left there's a green flag,
and there's a stop sign.
Green flag means go.
Stop sign means stop, and that's how
you can start and stop a program written
in this language called Scratch.
So literally, when the
green flag is clicked,
I want the program to do something.
I want it to do something pretty
simple, so I'm going to do this.
I know from having tinkered before
that the Looks category has things like
this-- "say hello"--
and I'm going to double-click on the
white box there and say "hello world."
And let me go ahead and zoom out,
and now if I click the green flag,
I've written my first computer program.
It's not all that
interesting, but I didn't have
to type anything out on the keyboard.
All I had to do was drag and
drop these puzzle pieces,
and it actually did something for me.
Well, let's go ahead and do
something a little more interesting.
But first, we need a
few more constructs.
So let's just introduce some
of the fundamental pieces
that we have at our disposal.
I said earlier, we have
functions or actions, like verbs.
We have conditions,
like forks in the road--
Boolean expressions, which,
just to be sure, are what?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, just
true/false statements--
it's a question that has a true
or false, or yes or no, answer.
Loops, things that
happen again and again--
there's even more features to languages
like this-- variables like in algebra,
x, and y, and z.
You can actually store values,
so you can count up and down
and do other things with them.
Things called threads-- turns
out programs and computers can
kind of sort of do multiple things at
once in any number of different ways.
And that's great because,
frankly, it's nice to be
able to check your email while something
is printing or someone is sending you
a Facebook message in another window.
Computers can give the
illusion at least or actually
do multiple things at a time.
And threads are generally the feature
of computers that make that possible.
And then there's events,
like sometimes you
get a little notification in your
browser or on your Mac or PC,
saying you've got new mail,
or you've got a message,
or any other kind of reminder.
And those events can get triggered too.
So these are all things
you've seen on your computer,
but we can now express them
in a language like Scratch.
So let's take a look at a few samples.
This purple puzzle piece
here is like printf
a moment ago, in that language called
C, which we'll come back to next week.
But "say hello world" shall
be, henceforth, a function.
And functions, it turns out,
can themselves take input.
It's like a mini program.
The input here is whatever's
in that white box.
And as we guessed earlier, when you
print something or say something,
the output is something
visual on the screen.
Maybe it's in a window on your computer
or on Scratch's stage, so to speak.
So a function does some action,
but we can do this conditionally.
Here I've taken two puzzle pieces, one
of which is kind of wrapping the other.
And I'm saying if x is less than y--
I have no idea in this context what x
and y is, because it's just an example.
But suppose x is a
number and y is a number,
and I ask the Boolean
expression, is x less than y?
That's true or false.
And if it's true, go
ahead and do what's,
effectively, indented inside of it.
Previously, I used the space-bar
for the black-and-white code
for finding Mike Smith.
Here you just physically
have a yellow block,
and then you have the purple block here,
indented a little bit to the right.
You're only going to say x is less than
y if, indeed, it is mathematically.
You can do fancier things.
You can nest these things.
And earlier I said you can
actually grow these blocks,
so they don't have to be this big.
They'll grow to fit
whatever you put into them.
So you can take multiple
if/else blocks, and an if/else
is like a two-way fork in the road.
But if you put a two-way fork in
the road inside of a two-way fork
in the road, you can effectively
make it a three-way fork,
just as I've done here.
If x is less than y--
say x is less than y--
else, if x is greater than
y, say x is greater than y.
Else, it must be the case
logically that they're equal,
and so that's the third
and final case there.
What else can we do?
This is the Boolean expression
on its own, out of that context.
You can do specific numbers, like is
i some other variable less than 50?
You can forever say
hello, just keep saying
hello, world; hello, world;
ad nauseum, never stopping.
Or you can do it just 50
times or any number of times.
The Repeat block lets you
type in a number there.
Set i to 0--
this is an orange block that lets
you define a variable. x or y or z
or i is very common, because
it's an integer or a number.
And you might start counting
at 0, and then 1, and then 2.
You might have two of these things.
If you want your program, as we'll
see, to do multiple things at once
in parallel, so to speak, we'll
just attach some of the blocks
to the left, some of
the blocks to the right,
and let the computer do
both at the same time.
Meanwhile, there's this,
a fancier feature still--
one sprite, one character can actually
broadcast a message sort of inaudibly
in some sense, and the other can
receive it or hear it, as though they're
whispering to one another.
So one program or one cat could
communicate with another on the screen
too.
So there's a way to make
even fancier programs still.
So if we take these all together,
we get some pretty cute results.
For instance, if I go ahead
and make a new program here--
File, New-- I'm going to go ahead
and grab a "When green flag clicked."
This time I'm going to go
to sound and drag this--
"play sound meow."
And notice how it works.
They're sort of magnetic.
As soon as you get close enough,
a little white bar appears.
And if you let go, they snap together.
And if I now click the green flag--
[COMPUTER MEOWING]
-- you get a very sickly
cat on these speakers.
[COMPUTER MEOWING]
OK, this is not really a good program
if every time I want the cat to emote,
I have to start the program again.
I could instead do something like this,
Control, and just do this forever.
[LAUGHTER]
No, not good?
OK, well, here, if you
don't like that one--
meow-- OK, that's what meow
looks like on a wave form--
my meow.
So now I can change it.
Sometimes the blocks
have little drop downs,
so you can change their inputs
or their parameter, so to speak.
[RECORDING OF DAVID'S MEOW PLAYS]
OK, that's no better.
OK, but it's a better
program written that way
than it would be if I instead did this.
A sort of a lazy
approach might have been
to do this if I wanted it to
keep playing the same sound.
But this, of course, kind of
looks stupid, and indeed it is.
There comes a point, and
it's not necessarily always
a well-defined point, but where a smart
person is going to look at your program
and say, hmm, it's correct.
It does meow, what, five times.
But it's not well designed--
we can do better than that.
And to do better, I could do it
forever, if that's really my goal.
Or I can go repeat, say, five
times, grab just one of these.
And notice, it grows to fill.
And this now would be a
better-designed program.
But now, we can very quickly escalate
things and go to a fancier program.
In fact, just for old time's sake, let
me go ahead and open up one program
that I, myself, wrote the very
first time I saw Scratch years ago,
which is this one here.
Could we get a quick volunteer?
You don't need to say too much.
You just need to be really good at
picking up trash with an adorable song.
Come on up.
What's your name?
TUCKER: Tucker.
DAVID MALAN: Tucker, come on up, Tucker.
All right, so you'll see here a
game that, frankly, took me all day.
So it didn't just come
out-- nice to meet you--
like meowing a few times did.
But you'll see that it's made
up of a whole bunch of pieces.
I'm going go ahead and
full-screen it here,
just so we can see it a little better.
[COMPUTER PROGRAM - MUSIC PLAYING]
And your goal is to drag
and drop the falling trash.
And let's consider, as Tucker plays
this game, what it is that's happening.
So there's probably some kind of loop
that's making the trash fall, right?
How does trash fall?
That's just a picture,
in this case, of a shoe.
And it's really just moving
maybe one pixel at a time,
one dot on the screen at a time.
But if you do it again, and
again, and again, just like
one of those old-school flip books, you
can create the illusion of animation,
having a picture move,
and move, and move.
Meanwhile, Tucker is using my
track-pad and the mouse, really,
and he's clicking.
So the computer is listening.
If clicked on trash,
do something different.
Follow the mouse to the trash can.
Meanwhile, Oscar is clearly counting.
How is he counting?
He's probably got a variable--
x, or y, or z, or i, or whatever.
And indeed, I had a puzzle piece that's
a variable that's counting up, and up,
and up.
And of course, finally,
there's probably a condition--
any time Tucker is dragging the
trash over to Oscar's trash can,
the lid is popping up.
So what is that?
That's a branch in the road.
If trash touching trash
can, change the picture
to look like the trash can is
actually above the trash can.
OK, the song goes on forever, so maybe
a round of applause for Tucker here.
[APPLAUSE]
Very nicely done, here you go, here.
TUCKER: [? Thanks. ?]
DAVID MALAN: As you'll soon learn, one
of the inherent aspects of programming,
whether you've been doing
it briefly or forever,
is debugging-- finding
mistakes in your program.
And I swear to god,
all these years later,
I still remember playing that
song for like 12 hours on loop,
trying to get all of the timing right.
Thankfully, most of the programs we
write won't have quite as much sound.
But we can do things now incrementally.
And indeed, I didn't just sit
down and write Oscar Time.
It took me hours.
But what I started with was, how
do I make a piece of trash fall?
I just had a big, white,
empty window, and I
downloaded a piece of a
trash icon or something,
or maybe it came with Scratch.
And I just had it start
at the top of the screen,
and it turns out there's puzzle pieces
that let you position things at an xy
coordinate, like up here and over here.
And then I just had it move one
pixel, move one pixel, move one pixel.
And I put it in a Forever block, so
it just did it on its own for me.
And I had a condition that
said if the trash is touching
the bottom of the screen,
stop falling, because it
would be kind of an annoying game
if the trash just kept falling,
and you could never pick it up.
So at some point, you have
to stop the animation too.
So that was one step in that
process, or one building block.
And once I figured that
out, I added something else.
I probably added Oscar at that
point, because it was just adorable.
And I figured out, how do I make his
trash can go up and down, up and down?
It looks like animation,
but really that's
just two or three different pictures.
And when Tucker was moving
his mouse over the trash can,
I changed the picture from the default
one, where the trash can is closed,
to one where the lid is open, to a third
one where Oscar is popping out of it.
And that's all animation
is, is a sequence of images.
It's a sort of a simple
video, if you will.
So what are these kinds of building
blocks that we can actually do?
Well, let's open just
a few of these here.
We have on the course's
web site a few examples
that you can play with later,
beyond the ones I just made.
But if I go ahead, for instance, and
open up this one, Counting Sheep,
you'll see that you didn't
have just cats in your world.
You can have this adorable guy here.
And it's a pretty
simple program, and it's
kind of a re-take on the
notion of counting sheep.
This time, it's a sheep counting.
And what is he doing?
Well, let's just zoom in
on his program, and that's,
indeed, what these puzzle pieces are.
When green flag clicked,
set counter to 0.
Counter is apparently
a variable, and it's
a better name, frankly,
than x or y or z,
which has no meaning to really anyone.
But Counter is more descriptive
word, so that's better design.
Forever just means keep
doing the following--
do what?
Say Counter for one second.
So I don't have to hard
code a word like "hello."
I can drag the Counter variable
block so that it prints out a number.
I can wait one second, change the
counter by one, by incrementing it
by one, and then just let it repeat.
And so now I have a sheep
that's counting in perpetuity.
We can add this example, a little bit
of interactivity now, with Pet the Cat.
So this is an unnaturally
sounding cat at the moment,
but notice nothing's happening here.
But if I zoom in, what should
be happening, or how can
I make something happen on my screen--
yeah?
AUDIENCE: If you move the
mouse to the [INAUDIBLE]
then the cat might start meowing.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, if I move the mouse
to the cat, it seems to start to meow.
So let's try.
Here we go.
[COMPUTER PROGRAM MEOWING]
Yeah, so it's Pet the Cat, in the
sense that as soon as the mouse touches
the cat, he's meowing.
So what about Don't Pet the Cat,
which is another take on things?
This one looks like
this, similar appearance.
[COMPUTER PROGRAM MEOWING]
But there's a forever loop
that, by default, is meowing.
And I realize this is annoying,
so let's quickly not pet the cat
by moving closer, and
closer, and closer.
[COMPUTER PROGRAM GROWLS]
OK, so don't pet the cat.
Well, how did that happen?
Well, this time there's a
two-way fork in the road.
If touching cat, play the lion sound--
else, just play the cuter meow sound.
So it's an interactive
program this time,
because I'm actually detecting
the presence of that mouse.
I can take things one step further.
In threads here-- which,
a thread is just--
a computer can use multiple
threads, so to speak,
to do multiple things at a time.
Here we have a bird and a
different cat, and you can kind of
infer that the cat is using
AI, artificial intelligence,
to figure out the bird.
And that's kind of an overstatement,
because it's really just pointing
himself perpetually at the bird.
[COMPUTER PROGRAM GROWLS]
OK, but he honed in on
the cat as follows--
notice, down here I
now have two sprites.
In the past examples,
we've just had one,
but you can have two,
just like Oscar Time did.
And the bird, notice, is just going
in some specific direction at first.
I just tinkered with this--
negative 150, positive 150.
That's just the xy
coordinate on the grid.
Point in a 45-degree
direction, and then forever,
if you're not touching
the cat, move three steps.
And then if you're on the edge, bounce.
So this is just the bird kind of
futzing around, and if he hits the edge,
he bounces.
But he's completely not aware of the
cat until he's actually touching it.
But I can change this.
What if I make the bird
go 10 steps at a time?
You'd think he kind of has
the advantage, but not really,
because the cat's program--
if we zoom in on this--
is to do what?
He starts off in a random direction.
This computer program, like
many, can use random number,
sort of guess a number, so to
speak-- more on that down the road.
If touching bird, play the
lion sound and then stop.
Else, he's kind of cheating
with that blue puzzle piece--
point toward the bird,
and then move one step.
It's one step, though.
That's pretty slow.
What if I give him a
bit of an advantage?
What if I stop the program?
Let's give him 20 steps at a time.
[COMPUTER PROGRAM GROWLS]
And the program executes
much more quickly.
And we can do one final
example here involving
what are called events, whereby
one script can signal, somehow,
to another as follows.
If you've ever played the game
Marco Polo, you might have had this.
If I hit the space-bar, the
little purple Muppet says Marco.
And then the blue one says Polo,
without me hitting the space-bar again.
What's going on?
It's a simple idea, but let's see
the orange Muppet's scripts first.
Forever do the following--
if the key space
is pressed-- so a weird way of
saying, if the space-bar is pressed,
then say Marco for two seconds.
And then broadcast an event.
And I could have called
the event anything,
but it's like this whisper, so to speak,
that you can't hear, we can't hear,
but the computer sprites can hear.
And it's broadcasting it, waiting for
another sprite or character to hear it.
And indeed, if I go to the blue Muppet
here, when he receives that event,
that whisper, go ahead and say Polo.
So it's not the same program.
They're fundamentally
independent, but these processes
are somehow intercommunicating.
And that's ever-important too
with software today, where
you want one program to interact with
another so that your software can
do fancier and fancier things still.
Now, let's look at one final
idea that comes full circle, back
to the notion of
functions, because it's not
enough to just implement a function.
There's good ways and bad
ways to do it, and we'll
see that this is demonstrative
of the kind of sophistication
we'll soon have in
another language like C.
Here is a program that
simply has the character
on the screen cough three times--
cough, cough, cough.
This is correct, if my goal is
to have him cough three times.
But I would argue it's
not well-designed-- why?
Why is it not well designed-- yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] use a loop.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I
can use a loop, right?
Why use six blocks when I, instead,
could use two or three if I just use
a looping construct?
So let me open a different example.
That was cough 0.
Let me open cough 1, which looks a
little different, but is much tighter,
so to speak-- it's better-designed
code that still does the same thing.
If I click the green flag, it's cough,
cough, cough, but I'm using less code.
It's, therefore, easier to read
and it's easier to maintain.
If I want to repeat this
now, not 3 times, but 10,
I don't have to copy and paste a
lot of blocks or code, so to speak.
I can just change that number.
But you know what?
There's an opportunity to
kind of factor code out,
and we'll see this more and
more in the weeks to come.
There's an opportunity to
now do this-- a custom block.
Now, notice this.
Let me drag this off the
screen for the moment
and claim that this is the program.
When green flag is clicked,
repeat the following three times--
cough.
That's interesting, but the purple
block there did not come with Scratch.
I invented it myself by using
the More Blocks category here.
And what I did was dragged and dropped
the requisite pieces to give me
this construct, this design--
define cough.
That's the name of my new verb,
the name of my new function.
And its purpose in life
is to do two things--
say cough for one second and
then wait for one second.
Henceforth, I can
abstract that idea away.
I don't know how cough is implemented.
I wrote this like a year ago, no
recollection, and that's fine.
I can literally hide it off
the screen, because the name
is descriptive enough
and abstract enough
that I don't care how this thing coughs.
I just want it to cough.
And so again, to this point of
layering, and layering, and layering--
we started with electrons
and 0's and 1's today,
and we're already now, in some
sense, at the level of coughing,
which has a very well-defined meaning.
If we really dug into it, we
could really define it formally.
But we don't care, because it's a useful
abstraction, a generalization that
communicates a shared idea
that all of us here understand.
So I thought we should
do one thing here.
That last game wasn't quite as
interactive as would be ideal,
and one of our favorite games was
written in the very first year
of this offering.
One of your predecessors
thought it would
be fun to make something
a little competitive.
And for this, we have an opportunity
for one final volunteer today before we
conclude with a summary and a teaser.
Yeah, what's your name?
[? ABEERAH: ?] [? Abeerah. ?]
DAVID MALAN: Ameerah?
DAVID MALAN: [? Abeerah, ?] come on up.
Come on up, [? Abeerah. ?] So
here we have "Ivy's Hardest Game"
remixed by one of your predecessors--
and [? Abeerah, ?] did you say?
[? ABEERAH: ?] Yeah.
DAVID MALAN: OK, come
on up, nice to meet you.
[? ABEERAH: ?] Nice to meet you.
DAVID MALAN: The goal
here is to navigate
your way through a maze of sorts, per
the instructions we're about to see.
[COMPUTER PROGRAM - MUSIC PLAYING]
[AUDIO OUT]
So the goal is to get
Yale through the maze.
And again, consider-- we want
to make this a little academic--
what's happening.
She's hitting the mouse
key, so there's probably
a loop listening for the
mouse key or the arrow key,
instead of the space-bar.
And it's moving the
character for as long
as the [? Abeerah ?] is holding down
the right arrow or the left arrow--
nice.
[COMPUTER PROGRAM - MUSIC PLAYING]
Nice, and presumably,
the Yale icon is moving
more steps, more pixels at a time.
And that's why it's faster
than that Harvard shield.
[COMPUTER PROGRAM - MUSIC PLAYING]
[AUDIENCE GASPS]
Very nice, notice we
have two variables--
Level, at top left, and
Death, currently at 0.
Oh!
[AUDIENCE GASPS]
We don't care about 0.
[APPLAUSE]
Very nice-- there's
some randomness there.
He's just kind of moving around.
[LAUGHTER]
He seems to have a condition that
says if near Yale, move away.
[LAUGHTER]
Nice.
[? ABEERAH: ?] I don't like this game.
[LAUGHTER]
DAVID MALAN: Princeton seems
to be picking a direction.
[AUDIENCE GASPS]
Notice her variable of
Death got incremented.
Nice, two Princetons, so the sprite has
cloned itself or duplicated itself--
second-to-last level-- nice.
[AUDIENCE GASPS]
[? ABEERAH: ?] [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Oh!
DAVID MALAN: All right, a big round
of applause for [? Abeerah. ?]
[APPLAUSE]
Very nicely done, here you go.
Here you go.
We'll post a link online so that
you can take a look at that as well.
Before I turn things back over
to Benedict, just a couple
of final remarks--
one, for 10 years we've
had a tradition of ending class with
cake, which is a nice opportunity
to get to know some of the
TAs and CAs, all of whom
will greet you outside if you have
a few minutes in just a moment.
But we also wanted to paint a picture in
words that the syllabus elaborates on,
that you have in your hands, of the
support structure in this class.
It's undoubtedly a lot of work
and challenging for many students,
but you'll have at your
disposal innumerable
resources, among which we see here.
And then there's also,
finally, this cultural aspect
to the class, more than just
a typical class, we hope.
We hope that you find this, ultimately,
to be a shared experience and really
a community of students, 68% of whom
are in the exact same boat as you.
And by way of a number
of events and traditions
that we've carried on for some time in
both Cambridge and now New Haven alike,
will you experience some of
these opportunities ahead.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK -- MUSIC PLAYING]
BENEDICT BROWN: Meow, meow, meow--
so thank you all for coming.
Those of you who came in a few
minutes late, I'm Benedict.
I am the instructor lead
here at Yale, and, again,
I encourage you all to come on
Thursdays during this time slot.
I'll be talking about things
related to the material we're doing,
but not specifically how
to go over your homework.
We will have times in
office hours for that.
But I also wanted to tell you,
just quickly, a couple of things.
Next Thursday what I'll be talking
about is how to be successful in CS50.
If you've heard from your friends,
oh, this is an impossible class--
it's 20 hours a week--
there are ways that this gets much
better, understanding the best ways
to use the resources of
office hours, of the website,
of all the different
aspects of the course.
So especially if you're
one of the 68% of students
who have no previous programming
or computer science experience,
and also for all of
you who are freshmen,
I really, really strongly
urge you to come to this.
You will find it helpful.
It will save you a lot of time and
learn more to navigate the course.
Also, we have not posted the regular
office hours for Natalie and me yet,
and we won't start the office hours in
the library before homework 0 is due.
Now, this is in Scratch.
It's a lot of having fun and exploring.
But Natalie will be holding
office hours tomorrow.
And if it's busy, I will join
her from 11 o'clock to 2:00.
That's tomorrow in the computer
science building, which
is called AK Watson hall, and it's right
around the corner on Prospect Street,
51 Prospect Street, in room 201.
So if you have any questions about
the class, any questions about P
set 0, feel free to stop by.
We'll look forward to meeting
you and talking with you.
And now it's time for cake.
[APPLAUSE]