[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50 and this is lecture five.
And you'll recall perhaps that
in this most current week,
you've probably been tackling
a little something like this.
And if you don't actually have
this experience from childhood,
what we're referring
to in this problem set
is these kind of glasses that aren't
3-D glasses because it's both red eyes
or sometimes it's just
a big piece of plastic.
But with this can you
actually look up and see
what the answer is supposed to be.
And so this is the allusion
to which we're referring
and the goal ultimately in
problem set five's who done
it is to actually figure out how to
implement that kind of red filter.
But to do that, you
first have to understand
this thing, which at first glance,
admittedly, looks pretty complicated.
But if you dived into
the problem already,
you'll probably have wrapped
your mind around at least
a few of these fields like the size
of the image or the width of the image
and the height of the image, which
should be a little more reasonably
straightforward.
But to implement this, you've
had to deal with something
called a struct or a structure.
And so in C, we have
this feature, recall.
And we didn't really play
with this that much last time.
But you've seen it now in
forensics, or you soon will.
And here we have the
definition of a student.
So when C was invented decades
ago, they didn't foresee
the need for a student data type.
They had int and char
and float and double.
But we can invent our own data
types much like in Scratch.
We can make our own
puzzle pieces as follows.
Typedef to define a type, struct
to say here comes a structure.
And what is the structure
known as student?
Well in this case, I arbitrarily
decided that a student would just
have a name and a dorm and
both of those would be strains.
And you can imagine putting
other things in there
like ID numbers, phone numbers,
email addresses, or whatnot
so that you can actually combine
all of this information together.
So let's just take a quick look at
how you might use code like this.
Here is a file called struct.h.
It's common, but not necessary
to declare your structures inside
of a file that also starts with .h so
that we can share it across multiple
programs just like with other
libraries' header files.
And here I've taken
those training wheels
off as before where, string is actually
just a white lie for char star.
But this is really the
same data structure
and it's in a file called struct.h.
So let's take a quick look now
at a program that actually uses
this in struct0.C. So let's take
a look at what we've done here.
In struct0.C we have
some header files up top.
But we also include this header
file so that we have access
to this new custom data type.
And then in main we do a few things.
We first go ahead and ask the user
for an integer called enrollment.
So hopefully they'll give
us a positive number.
If we then do get back a
number as expected in line 13,
what do we do in English here?
How would you just describe what line
13 is doing at this point in the term?
Anyone, yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, give us an array
of students of size enrollment.
So even though on line
11 and prior we didn't
know how many students we
needed, we did get on line 12
that answer, the enrollment.
And so on line 13 we declare an
array using a variable saying,
give me this many elements, this many
students in my array to store things.
And then we proceed, in the
lines below, as follows.
We start iterating over the enrollment
from zero on up to enrollment.
And we prompt the user on each
iteration for a student's name and dorm.
And the right hand side of those two
lines of code is pretty familiar.
You're just calling, get string.
But on the left hand side, we do
have a slightly new piece of syntax.
We have students bracket I, which gives
you the i-th students in the array.
But what piece of syntax
perhaps jumps out at you?
Especially if you've
never programmed before?
And we've not used this symbol
just yet in this context.
What looks different?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so the .name.
So you can probably infer that
.name and .dorm is somehow accessing
the student's name and
the student's dorm.
And that's literally
all that's happening.
This dot operator tells the computer,
go inside of the student's structure
at that i-th location and
store the string that's coming
back from get string in that variable.
And similarly, do the same for dorm.
So it's like taking a struct
and then looking inside of it
and going very specifically to
one of the elements therein.
We've never needed this .operator
before because in the past, any array,
any variable we've had has just
been a string or an int or float.
We haven't had anything
to dive deeper into.
So that's all that's going on there.
We've encapsulated, so to speak, inside
of a student structure, name and dorm.
And then this last part is
actually just a printing out
of that same information.
We're just printing out, so-and-so
is in such-and-such a dorm
by passing in those two strings
using our familiar percent S.
Now this program at the end of
the day is kind of pointless
because you prompt the user for some
number of students' names and dorms,
you print them out, and then
you throw them away forever.
And that's not all that
useful of a program long term.
And so we have in our second version of
this program, struct 1.C a new trick,
too.
That's a teaser as
well for the direction
we're going in this problem
set, next problem set,
and beyond, where we're actually
using files where files on a computer
are just a whole bunch
of bits, zeros and ones.
Those zeroes and ones
follow some pattern.
But we have yet to see a mechanism
for actually saving files.
But here's how we can do it.
So above this line here,
21 and above, same program.
Just get a bunch of students from
the user, per their name and dorm.
Then here line 24 we
see something that's
a little new, though you have seen
this in the forensics problem so far.
We call a function called
F open, meaning file open.
That takes two arguments,
according to its documentation.
The name of the file you want
open and then the second argument
is how you want to open the file.
And even if you've
never seen this before,
what might the W there represent?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, right.
So it's read and write are two of the
most common operations for a computer.
R would be read, W would be write.
And this kind of makes sense if the goal
now is to save these students to a file
so that the program is actually
useful if you run it again and again.
So here we have a new
data type on the left.
It's all caps, which is a
bit of an anomaly, even in C.
But file, star, file just says,
hey, give me a variable of type file
that can store the address
of a file, so to speak.
And technically, that's not the
address of the file on disk.
That's the address in RAM
once you've opened the file.
But for now, just assume that this
is an abstraction for the file.
And it's just called literally file.
So what is line 25's purpose in life?
Even though we've never
written this code before now.
Yeah, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: If the file exists.
DAVID MALAN: If the file exists, or more
generally, if the file was successfully
opened.
Because there could be bunches
of things that go wrong.
One, as you've implied,
the file might not exist.
Two, maybe you don't have permission
so it exists but you can't open it.
Three, maybe there's not
enough memory in the computer
to open yet one more file.
So any number of things could go wrong.
And recall, what is the special sentinel
value that typically represents errors
now that we're in the world of pointers?
Null, so N-U-L-L in all caps is sort of
the opposite of having a valid address.
It means no such address.
So we use it to check for errors.
So that's all line 25 is doing.
And then the rest of this is almost
identical to the previous program,
except we're not using print F.
What are we apparently using?
F print F and take a guess as to
what the F in print F stands for?
Yeah, so file print F. So
it works almost the same
except it takes one more argument.
The very first argument
now is not a format string
like it's been for ages now.
It's instead a variable that references
an open file and then the rest of this
is all the same.
So what's really cool about F
print F is that you don't just
print to the screen.
You actually print to
whatever file you've
opened so that then,
on the very last line
here, when I call F close, that's
equivalent to saving the file.
And then the program just quits.
And so what's neat
about this in the end is
if I go ahead and
scroll up here, and let
me go into my source five directory.
Let me go ahead and make struct one.
Structs.h not found.
What did I do?
Well, I just screwed up before
class and misnamed this file
so that didn't just happen.
So now I've compiled the program.
All right, so now let me go ahead and
run this ./struct1 enrollment will be
three.
And we'll say that it'll be Maria
who is in Cabot House and Brian who
is in Winthrop.
And say David was, say, in Mather.
Enter and nothing seems to happen.
But if I type LS now and
look inside this directory,
notice that I have a file called
students.csv deliberately named
because if you've ever
used Excel or Numbers,
a very common file format is what's
called the CSV, comma separated values
format.
And this is sort of like a
very simplistic database.
If I open this you'll see that
indeed, the contents of this file
are separated by commas.
And if I were to actually open this
file up in Excel, each of these columns
would open up visually in exactly that.
So what I did with my printdef,
if I go back to structs1.c,
notice as I consciously
included that comma there,
to create this sort of
faux database format.
And just for good
measure, let me see if I
go to download from
the IDE's file manager
and I go ahead and open up students.csv.
And then if the program cooperates
here, we have Microsoft Excel.
And now I've made myself
a tiny little spreadsheet.
Now using c-code.
Now we're going to find pretty
quickly that this is not
all that useful to make CSV files.
Because the more and more rows we add
to these files, the slower and slower
it's going to get to search them.
And so before long, as we transition
next week and be onto web programming,
we're actually going to replace
spreadsheets or CSVs like this
and actually replace them with something
more powerful, namely databases.
So that's a teaser
then of what's to come.
But where did we begin
this conversation?
It all kind of keeps
coming back to what's
inside of our computer, which we
can continue abstracting away.
You don't have to understand
how this hardware works.
But we previously had said
that you can at least think
about chopping up your
computer's memory into a grid
so that you can just
number of the bytes.
So that you have specific
locations otherwise
known as addresses or pointers.
Last time we clarified
that not all memory is
treated equal inside of the computer.
Rather, different chunks of
memory are used differently.
So the top portion, so to speak, but
there is no notion of top in reality.
This is just an artist's rendition.
So the top of your
computer's memory might
be the heap, whereby you
store certain types of values
and then down here is
the so-called stack where
you store other types of values.
And if we zoom out there's actually
different layers still of memory.
So let's actually tease
apart what's going on here.
If, when you run a
program, you have access
to a gigabyte of RAM or two
gigabytes, and indeed, that's
what your Mac or PC does.
No matter how much RAM
you have, the computer
typically gives you the illusion
of having access to all of it.
And so this might be two
gigabytes, then, of memory.
Well, one of the first
things that happens
is that the zeros and ones that
compose your program, whether it's
called A.out or Caesar or Vigenere
or Structs One, those zeros and ones
are loaded way up top here
in your computer's memory.
So the text segment in
memory is a weird name
for the zeros and ones
of your actual program.
It's not ASCII text.
It's like literally zeros and
ones of your compiled program.
Below that are what are generally called
initialized data or uninitialized data.
And this essentially just
means any global variables
you have in your program
are stored here or here.
If you gave them values at
the top of your program,
they're initialized by definition.
And if you didn't,
they're uninitialized.
So the compiler just kind of lays
those out a little bit differently.
At the very bottom are something
called environment variables,
which we don't use too
much but you use them
in a few weeks for web programming.
You'll often store things like user
names and passwords or other values
that you don't want
to save in your code.
But you want the Mac or PC or
server to have somehow access to.
But these are the ones we'll talk
about the most, stack and heap.
And we saw a couple of examples
of each of these, though, briefly.
What did we use the stack for or
claim it's used for last time?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Say again?
DAVID MALAN: Int min
void, and more generally,
functions when they are called.
Main is, of course, the go to
one for all programs' beginnings.
But it might call another
function like swap.
And swap itself might call something
else, maybe printdef gets called.
So every time you call a function, it
gets a slice of or a frame of memory.
And they go up and up and up
as those functions get called.
And this was ultimately
illuminating, at least theoretically,
as to why this program was broken.
The program we looked at last time,
the swap and no swap programs,
we claim that this
implementation was wrong.
And yet I think when Kate came up
and we did the example with switching
the Gatorade flavors,
this is pretty much
an interpretation of that into code.
And it's correct in one sense
and it's incorrect in another.
In what sense was this
code actually correct?
In the no swap program.
Because we did walk through
it briefly with the debugger.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, we needed temporary
container or variable in which
to store one of the values or
one of the Gatorade flavors.
And by the time we got to
this third and final line
in this function, what
could you say about A and B?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, they
had in fact been swapped.
And I saw that, I think, by plugging in,
I think I struggled with the debugger
so I used E print def
at the last minute just
to see what had happened
after that very third line.
So it works.
This function does swap A and
B. But it did not swap what?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: X and Y, which
were the variables in main.
And so recall the story
we told last time,
was that if we focus only
on your computer stack,
that sort of bottom portion of
memory, when main is called,
it gets a chunk of memory
down here at the bottom
because it's the very first
function to be called.
And it had variables, recall, called
X and Y whose values were one and two.
When main called swap, the
other function we just saw,
it had values called A, B, and also
temp that initially were one and two.
And eventually became two and one.
But that picture kind of
answers the whole question.
The reason X and Y didn't
change is because you literally
change in that red
version, just A and B.
So we solved this problem, recall,
last time with what new feature of C?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Pointers, so addresses.
Rather than just hand the function,
the values you want to swap,
give the function a road map,
so to speak, to those values
so that the function can go to
the values you actually care about
and move them wherever they are.
And it's a strange
looking syntax at first.
It looks like multiplication
all over the place.
But it had two different uses.
If you have the star or asterisk up here
and a data type like int next to it,
this is saying, hey computer.
Give me a variable called A. But
that's not going to store an int.
It's going to store what?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, the memory
address of an int and just as B
is going to store the
address of another integer.
So those are kind of
placeholders for the addresses.
So down the road is the Science Center.
So if the address of the Science
Center is 1 Oxford Street, Cambridge,
Mass 02138, that is it's postal
address and it uniquely identifies that
building.
Similarly inside of a computer
do values have unique addresses.
They're just much simpler.
They're numbers, they don't have
streets and zip codes and all of that.
But it's the same exact idea.
So here we still have a
variable temp of type int.
So give me a temporary
variable just like Kate had
the extra cup that was initially empty.
*A, though, without a data type to
the left of it, was like saying what?
*A in this context is a sort of
different English sentence than this
one.
This means give me a pointer to an
int or declare for me a variable
that will store the address of an int.
But this says, go to that address.
So it means A is in address, *A means
go to that address so you can get
at the value, which probably
in the story, is one.
*A means the same thing.
Again, go to that address.
And then, by the way,
go to that address B.
Whatever that value is, put it where
this finger is already pointing.
And then *B means go to that address and
put whatever was in the temporary cup
of Gatorade, or in this
case, the value one.
So pointers, though kind
of a very convoluted way
of fixing this solve the problem
fundamentally, because now
rather than passing one and two, we
instead passed in here the address of X
and the address of Y
that allowed the computer
to then go to those locations
in memory and actually
do what it is we wanted it to do.
So long story short, this is
how the computer stack is used.
When you call a function, it
gets a new slice of memory on top
of whatever function called it.
As soon as that function
is done executing,
this memory effectively goes away.
It's technically still
there, because it's hardware.
It's not going to physically disappear.
But now whatever next function main
calls, maybe printdef, maybe something
else, it will reuse this
memory in any number of ways
that it wants for its own
local values and parameters.
So given that definition,
the fact that the stack, kind
of like trays in the
cafeteria grow up and down
and up and down as a program calls
functions and those functions
return, where do garbage
values actually come from?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Old things
that were in that memory.
So I kind of made this
sweeping claim in the past
that you shouldn't trust
variables if you yourself
haven't put values in them, because
they have so-called garbage values.
But that actually has
a very precise meaning.
That means if you have
called a function and it
needs a variable that just happens
to be here, and this is like a minute
into your program's running, a
whole bunch of different functions
might have used and unused, used
and unused that portion of memory.
So they're just going to have zeros and
ones lingering there in some pattern.
The computer could be really
defensive and it could just change
these all to zeros bits all the time.
And that could have been a
reasonable design decision,
but long story short,
C does not do that.
It would have just been time
consuming, especially years ago
when computers were slower.
The language was younger.
And it just wasn't
compelling to do that.
So you just get garbage
values, which I have typically
just written as question marks.
But that's why.
There are garbage values there because
they're your own previous values,
or those of some functions.
So the heap, meanwhile, was
fundamentally different.
So the heap is this
upper portion of memory
that is in some sense
conceptually above the stack.
And it's up here.
And that's different in the sense
that it's more for long term storage.
The stack is for short
term storage, just
to use locally when a
function is executing.
But suppose your program
is to run for a while,
or suppose you want a function to
allocate memory that does stick around
and does not just immediately
become garbage values.
In fact, think about GetString.
GetString is a function we
wrote and its purpose in life
is to get a string from the user,
which is a whole bunch of characters.
And consider this.
If GetString is called and therefore
gets a slice of memory on the stack,
and I type in Maria's name, M-A-R-I-A
and then that gets a secret /0.
Where is the M-A-R-I-A and /0 stored?
Can it be, by this definition,
stored on the stack?
Why?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So if we allocated space on the stack,
which we could do with an array,
and then return the
address of that string,
that would be valid in
some sense, because you
would have allocated the memory.
And I'll go ahead and draw it like this.
If we had a function, GetString
being called and GetString's
being called by main, that might mean
that GetString has this chunk of memory
here.
And if Maria or I go ahead
and type in her name,
that's like allocating
space for M-A-R-I-A /0.
And you can think of this as just being
a whole bunch of bytes in that frame.
So they do exist and they
literally are stored in memory.
And I could return the address of
this first byte, whatever this is.
Maybe this is byte 10 or 100 or whatnot.
And I could return that address to
main as GetString's return value.
But as soon as I do that, yeah, exactly.
The memory doesn't
technically go anywhere.
But it's no longer trustworthy.
All of that is now garbage value.
So you might get lucky.
And if you try to print GetString's
return value you might see Maria
but maybe briefly, because the
next time you call a line of code
or somehow that memory's
reused, Maria's name
might get overwritten
with some other values
because her name becomes, by
definition, a garbage value.
And you don't know when it's
actually going to get reused.
So that's not safe.
So this is why the heap exists.
If you need to keep your memory around
for a while, like GetString is supposed
to do, turns out you can allocate it
just elsewhere that won't disappear
until you yourself free it.
And so that's when we introduced
last time a couple of new functions,
malloc for memory
allocation and it turns out
there's an opposite of
it, free, which you'll
need to use for future problem
sets dealing with memory management
in order to undo the allocation here.
Otherwise you end up having
what's called a memory leak.
And the computer might slow
down, run out of memory,
because you're not giving it back.
And as an aside, it turns out
there's a couple of cousins
of malloc, calloc and realloc.
Calloc is kind of cool in
that the C means clear.
So calloc is identical to malloc, but
it zeros the entire chunk of memory
for you.
So if you just want to initialize to
have no garbage values whatsoever,
you can use calloc instead of doing it
yourself with a four loop or something
like that.
Realloc, we're going to see,
is a more powerful function
that allows you to take a chunk
of memory and somehow grow it.
But we'll see what that
actually means in a moment.
But with this power comes
great responsibility.
And we saw that things can
go horribly wrong for binkie
when you misuse memory addresses.
And recall that we looked briefly at
this program by way of Nick's video
from Stanford.
And let's see what these lines
of code actually represent here.
So here and here I'm declaring
two variables, X and Y,
that are going to store
what, generally speaking?
Addresses of integers.
So that's all that's happening there.
This now, was a new
line of code last time.
Where it's saying, call malloc,
so allocate some amount of memory.
How much memory do you want?
Whatever the size of an int is.
Odds are it's going to be four,
maybe eight, some power of two
or some multiple of two
here, or a multiple of four.
So here we get back what?
A chunk of memory or
specifically, its address and we
store that in X. Meanwhile this
line says, go to that address
and put the special number 42 there.
This next line blindly
says, go to the address in Y
and put the unlucky number 13 there.
But that's where binkie had
an accident because what
was inside of Y at that moment in time?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Memory it
wasn't allowed to touch.
And why?
Be more precise.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So close.
That's going explain the
symptom ultimately but?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
I didn't ask for any memory whatsoever.
So by default, even
though this looks funky,
int*y just means give
me space for an address.
So that means, give me four or eight
bytes of memory in the computer's RAM.
But what is inside of a variable
by default, have we claimed?
Just garbage values.
So there's going to be a number
there, and numbers are our addresses.
So it's going to look like
there's an address there.
So it is technically
correct to say, go there.
But it's like following a map where
you have no idea where you're going.
You might sort of walk off
the edge of wherever you are.
And that's when bad things happen.
And so the visualization that Nick
put together with claymation was this.
If you have this and
it turns out it doesn't
matter if the star is on the
left or on the right here.
But we have conventionally put
it over onto the right side,
next to the variable.
When you do int*X and
int*Y, that's like saying,
give me a chunk of memory or
clay for each of these variables.
And he just kind of circled the
little arrowhead there on the string
because there's memory for it.
It's just not pointing
anywhere specific.
It's a garbage value
at this moment in time.
The next chapter in this story was this.
Allocate space for an int,
drawn in white clay here.
And Nick, because of the assignment,
said X, which is again is a pointer,
is now going to point
to that chunk of memory.
So it's no longer a garbage value.
It points somewhere specific.
That is why Nick was then
able to say, go there.
Follow the arrow, and
put the number 42 there.
But the next line of code,
this one went horribly wrong
because Y was not pointing anywhere.
Nick tried to say, go there and
put 13 but there is nowhere so
the computer crashes.
A segmentation fault, meaning that
you touch the segment of memory
that you should not have because
you tried to go somewhere
where it was just some garbage value.
And the fix, recall, might
be this, or a solution.
If we instead kind of
rewind and fix binkie.
And say Y equals X, that's
not allocating extra space.
That's just saying, have Y point
at the same chunk of memory as X.
Because again, X and
Y are just addresses.
So if the address is 100 in
memory, now X is 100, Y is 100.
They're both pointing at the
same chunk of white clay.
So if he then did *Y, gets
13, that says, go there.
Update the number.
And now 42 became 13.
Very similar in spirit, in fact,
to our capitalization example,
when we pointed to strings last
time, at the same chunk of memory.
So any questions on the stack or as
depicted here, by binkie, the heap?
Malloc allocates memory from the heap.
But anytime you declare
local variables or arrays
inside of a function,
that ends up on the stack.
And thus far malloc is the only
tool, or calloc or realloc,
that gives us access to this new
portion of memory depicted in white clay
here and sort of depicted
in our diagram up above.
Any questions?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
So keep in mind that X and Y
are both the same data types.
They're both pointers to addresses.
So as such, if you're going
to set one equal to the other,
you have to just store the value
that's in one inside of the other.
Otherwise it would be
trying to put an integer
inside of a pointer, which isn't
quite correct even though they're
technically both numbers.
So this is just saying,
whatever address is in X,
put that same address in Y it says
nothing about going to that address.
It's like making a photocopy of
a map but not actually following
that map yet.
Until this line, which then says,
go follow the copy of the map.
And it turns out it leads
you to the same location.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So if you return, in
C you can only return one value.
So you're kind of in a bad spot because
you ideally want to return two values,
right?
Both A and B you want
to return B and A. There
are ways you can work around that
and kind of sort of return two values
and see.
But in short, it's much
easier said than done.
Python will actually
make that much easier.
But the short of it in C is you
can't return multiple values.
And that ties our hands in this case.
OK, so odds are, related
to all of this, you've
heard about this website, which
is enormously useful when you're
trying to learn some new language,
when you're out in the real world
trying to solve some
problem because this
is this wonderful community of
people who post questions and answers
and ideally link to canonical
references so you can kind of understand
why some answer is the way it is.
But this actually has a very
technical meaning, Stack Overflow.
And stack, of course, is
now a familiar concept.
And you can imagine something
like this picture eventually
going very wrong if you call so many
functions that you just kind of run out
of memory.
Or not even run out per se.
What are you going to hit eventually
if you keep calling function
after function after function?
The heap.
And then bad things are going to happen.
If your stack frames
and your local variables
are so numerous that you start
overwriting the heap memory,
now values that you allocated with
malloc might themselves get clobbered.
So this is not the best design
decision but it is the reality.
And it's mitigated only
by using a compiler that
might help you notice
this or by actually using
more memory than you actually need.
Now, Stack Overflow actually has
a very technical meaning here,
as does heap overflow.
Stack Overflow means
you overflow the stack.
You just call so many darn functions
that you just touch memory you
shouldn't.
Heap overflow would be the opposite.
You keep calling malloc
and malloc and malloc
and the heap overflows the stack.
Because for better or for worse,
the stack is growing this way
and the heap is growing this way.
And eventually they're
going to strike each other.
So this is a more general way
of saying buffer overflows.
A buffer it's just a chunk of
memory that stores data or values.
We people in the real
world might have heard
of this in the context of video,
YouTube, or various video players.
If you've ever seen the
expression buffering, dot dot dot.
It's the most infuriating thing.
Something's about to happen in
the movie or show you're watching.
And the damn thing start
buffering, buffering, buffering.
What does that mean?
Well, the video player,
YouTube or something else,
has a chunk of memory, which
you can think of as an array.
And loaded into that array
are the zeros and ones
that compose the movie or
TV show you're watching.
And those were downloaded
over the internet.
And what happens is, hopefully
your internet speed is faster
than the movie's own playback.
So that even though you might be
at the minute 10 in the video,
hopefully your computer has
downloaded minute 10 through 11
so that you have this
built up buffer of bytes
that you have a whole
minute where you can watch,
even if your internet
connection goes out.
But when your video is buffering, it
means you have this array of memory
and you've kind of looked at or
watched all of the bytes in it.
And the buffer is now empty.
But the opposite can happen, too.
If you try downloading more
bytes then you have memory for,
you might try putting minutes
of the video someplace they
don't belong in your computer.
Or if you call too many functions or
if you call malloc too many times,
you might overflow the chunk of
memory that's been allocated.
So buffers are all over the place.
And indeed, a string as we
know it is just a buffer.
It's an array of memory
and hopefully you
will only put as many
characters in that string
as can fit in that chunk of memory.
So what kinds of things can go wrong?
This is a bit of a
contrived example, but it
comes with a couple of
visuals just to paint
a picture of how adversaries
can hack into systems
that are written in languages
like C. So here's a quick program.
We're going to include string.h.
And down here we have int main
that takes command line arguments.
Notice this function does not
do any error checking at all.
It's pretty stupid.
It just calls a function
foo and passes an argv[1].
So the idea here is
that this is a program
that if you take a command line
argument, a word after the program's
name, just gets blindly
passed into the foo program.
OK.
So next, what does foo do?
It accepts as input a string, a.k.a.
char* and we're just calling it bar.
And then it allocates an array
on the stack called C of size 12.
And then even if you've never
seen this function before,
you can maybe kind of infer from its
name, mem copy, like memory copy.
So it turns out this is going to
copy into this memory whatever is
in this memory up to this many bytes.
So if I type in Maria as the command
line argument, M-A-R-I-A is five.
So that means the length I
typed in is going to be five.
And this is going to copy five
bytes from bar into C that's it.
Now it's meant to be just a monster.
This program is pretty
useless at the end of the day.
But it's kind of distilled a thread
into the fewest lines of code.
What does this actually look
like or what's happening?
We've called the function.
We've allocated 12 bytes.
We've copied those five
bytes into those 12 bytes.
So all is well in this story.
But what actually happens in memory?
So here's a picture of the stack kind
of zoomed in and nicely colorized.
So stack is going this way.
Heap is growing this way.
And this is just showing you technically
how things are laid out on the stack.
I keep kind of simplifying the
world by just drawing things
as X and Y and A and B. But they
actually follow a precise order.
So specifically, if we
have a local variable
called bar, which we
did for this function,
it goes right there at the bottom.
If you then declare an array called
C, it goes right up there on top.
And these are sized proportional.
This is four bytes.
This is going to be 12 bytes.
So it all is kind of proportional size.
And then it turns out, and we
won't go into too much detail,
but if you like this stuff, CS 61
and other classes will explore it,
it turns out another thing that has
always been tucked away on the stack
secretly is what's
called a return address.
So when main calls swap, it's
like handing the keys to the car
off to someone else.
Like swap, go do your thing.
But main kind of has to tell
swap or any function it calls,
how to get back to its chunk of memory
so that execution can resume with main
as soon as swap is done executing.
And it's not its stack memory, per se.
Recall that top portion of memory
that I described as the text segment?
All the zeros and ones
that compose your program?
It turns out that main, when it
calls swap or some other function,
it tucks its own return address,
the address of the appropriate zeros
and ones in that text segment, into
four bytes here, or maybe eight bytes,
the address to which swap should hand
the keys back to you, so to speak.
Otherwise it's like main handing
the keys off to another function
and then it never hears from it
again so main's other lines of code
never get executed.
So long story short, there needs to
be an address or a map tucked away
on the stack so that swap can
hand control back to main.
But what happens here when
you actually use this memory?
Well, it turns out that if we just
number the bytes on the stack, and that
was a size 12, the first one is
zero, and the last one is 11.
So zero through 11 gives us 12 total.
So if we type in something like Maria or
maybe more generally, hello, H-E-L-L-O,
which is the same length, that's
using six bytes technically,
because the /0 and all is well.
Fits comfortably in C and
we've got room to breathe.
But what if we don't
type in Maria or hello?
What if we type in a very long sentence
that's more than 12 characters?
Where are they going to end up?
If you type in a longer string
at the command line in argv[1],
notice the code is flawed.
You're going to check the length
of the word that the user typed in,
copy all of its bytes
from bar into C. But what
if the length of the
string you typed in is 13?
What are you going to do?
You're going to copy 13
bytes from bar into C,
thereby filling all of
these 12 bytes plus one
more that you shouldn't be touching.
And if the string is
even longer than 13,
if the adversary really typed a long
sentence or phrase or word or whatnot,
you're going to really
exceed the boundaries
of that buffer or that array.
So what does this look Like Well,
if you type in a much longer word,
like A-A-A-A-A-A-A, you could end
up overwriting these 12 bytes,
also these four bytes, also these
green bytes, whatever they are,
and most importantly, even the red bytes
that I described as the return address.
Now A-A-A-A-A really isn't going
to cause anyone any trouble
because it's just a sequence
of random ASCII characters.
But characters at the end
of the day are just numbers,
and numbers are just bits,
and programs are just bits.
So the threat here is that if you're a
pretty sophisticated adversary, someone
who really knows programming,
you could technically
write a program that does
something really bad like delete
all the files on a hard drive.
Or send spam to everyone
in your contacts.
Or anything like that
because at the end of the day
the program that he or she has just
written is just zeros and ones.
If you then convert that program
zeros and ones to the corresponding,
even if weird-looking ASCII values,
you could technically type a program
at the command line in argv[1] just
by typing out the funky characters
on the keys that are not going to
make sense to a human reading it.
But those ASCII characters
in the context of a program
are going to be interpreted as code.
And if you're really
good, and frankly, it's
not so much that you're really good.
If by a lot of trial
and error, you happen
to overwrite the return
address in a program,
you can trick the computer
into not returning
back to main, but to jumping to the
very input you passed into the program.
So A here implies
attack, like attack code.
So if you're really clever, you can
pass in an appropriate pattern of zeros
and ones, convert it to ASCII so the
human can type them in at the prompt,
overwrite this return address,
and trick the computer program
to return from this function not to
main, but to like, this byte up here.
And maybe this byte coupled
with all of these others
means delete all the files
on this user's hard drive,
send spam to everyone in their contacts.
This is called a buffer
overflow exploit,
and it's incredibly shockingly
common even these days.
C is not commonly used for a lot of
programs but it still is everywhere.
And there's other languages, too,
like C++ that lend itself to this.
And even though this is
still a little arcane
and you don't need to worry too much
about the addresses on the screen,
the fundamental threat
here is that if you do not
check the boundaries of your arrays and
the amount of memory you've allocated
and you touch memory you should
not, very bad things can happen.
You're effectively
giving control to anyone
on the internet who can use your program
because he or she can be clever enough
to inject their own zeros and ones
into your program for execution.
OK.
So dear God, this is scary
in a computer science sense.
So what can we do to defend against
this beyond just not writing bugs,
which is never going to happen, right?
Even the most advanced,
best programmers still
make bugs, especially as the software
gets more and more complicated.
We have eprintf and we have
help50 and we have debug50
but there's other tools,
too, like Valgrind
which happens to be a tool for
detecting memory leaks in a program
and other memory-related issues.
So let me actually go ahead and
open this program, memory.c.
And it looks like this.
And let's see if we can't tease apart
what is buggy about this program.
So here's the program here.
So, include standard lib.h, function
f, function main, main calls f
and returns 0.
Nothing really interesting
going on there.
So what's in f?
F on the right hand side allocates
space for 10 integers, I think.
Malloc returns the address of that
chunk of memory and stores it in X
and then line 8 is the bug, I think.
What's wrong with line 8?
Let me go here first.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly, because
we start counting at zero
and because we're asking the
computer for space for 10 ints,
we get them back.
But that's going to be accessible
via [0] through, as you say, [9].
So [10] is like writing one
int past the buffer, a.k.a.
A buffer overflow.
Now it might be hard to see this,
especially when the program isn't
as relatively short as this but
is buried in a dozen lines, 100
lines, thousands of lines of code.
But tools can help.
So if I go ahead and make
this program with make memory.
And then I go ahead and execute
Valgrind ./memory enter,
the one downside of this program is
that its output is just completely
overwhelming.
But let's see if we can't tease
apart some recognizable terms.
So all of this on the left
is a bit of a distraction.
This is just copyright information.
So the interesting stuff
seems to happen here.
I see invalid right of size 4.
Not quite sure what all
of this means, but I
do see that it's somehow related
to uh-oh, line 8 of memory.c line
13, line eight, line 13, a lot of
bugs in the same places, it seems.
And then here, address such and such
as zero bytes after a block of sys
40 alloc, it's a little hard
to wrap my mind around this.
So as always, let's at least
initially just run this through help50
and see if it can help tease this apart.
So we see the same output.
It recognizes something
familiar in yellow here.
Invalid right of size four
and it highlights the lines.
And our TF-like feedback
is, looks like you're
trying to modify four bytes of memory
that isn't yours, question mark?
Did you try to store something
beyond the bounds of an array?
Take a closer look at
line 8 of memory.c.
So that's kind of a
mouthful but it's just
because we have practiced reading
stuff that's pretty arcane like this.
So we've extracted all of the salient
details like line eight of memory.c.
So line eight of memory.c, as we
noted, is already the dangerous line.
So what might it mean to have
an invalid right of size four?
Well, it turns out an int in
the IEDE is how many bytes?
Four, or 32 bits.
So invalid right of size four just means
that this int here, zero, is an int,
it's four bytes, it's just
invalidly being written, as you say,
to the wrong location.
So this is Valgrind's pretty terse
way of communicating that idea.
So here we have then an explanation.
So how do I fix this?
Well, if my intent was just
to update the last area there,
let me go ahead and do make memory
enter, ./valgrind ./memory enter.
And now this is a good thing
except we've made some progress.
Let me scroll up to
fit more on the screen.
So I got rid of that message,
invalid right of size four,
but this does not sound good either.
40 bytes in one block are definitely
lost in lost record one of one,
all right?
So I need a little help with that.
So let me do help50 again until
I get familiar with the syntax.
And it's highlighted
that chunk of output.
Looks like your program
leaked 40 bytes of memory.
Did you forget to free memory
that you allocated via malloc?
Take a closer look at
line seven of memory.c.
So let's do exactly that.
So line 7 of memory.c, OK,
here's where I malloc the memory.
And per help50's own feedback,
what have I apparently not done?
Freed it.
And it turns out freeing is
actually pretty straightforward
so long as you remember it do it.
You just call free, passing
in the same pointer.
You don't have to
remember how long it is.
It's up to the operating system
to remember how long it is.
But now if I do make memory.
And now I do again Valgrind./memory
enter, heap summary,
all heap blocks were freed.
No leaks are possible.
I see nothing particularly worrisome.
And the program is bug free now.
So Valgrind is another
tool in your toolkit
that doesn't help you
find logical bugs per se.
It helps you find memory-related
errors, which might be logical bugs.
But it helps you hone in on them and
see them in a way that you as a human
might not otherwise, especially if it's
buried in many, many lines of code.
Now you'll notice, too, real
briefly, in Valgrin's output
in these several examples, there
are all of these funky numbers.
So if I go back to the original
version here just a moment ago,
where it was in fact
buggy in a couple of ways.
And I rerun make and I
rerun Valgrind, you'll
see a whole bunch of things like this.
At OX such and such, at OX such and
such, OX, what did OX denote last time?
So hexadecimal, so
this is just a succinct
if weird-looking way of representing
numbers, generally memory addresses.
And so this very specifically is
saying that line 13 of memory.c
happens to be using
memory at this location.
It's not particularly useful
to us the programmers.
But that's why you see it.
And Valgrind is arguably
a more advanced tool,
which is to say that memory addresses
in tools like this and even in debuggers
tends to be written using
hexadecimal notation like that.
Of course, you've seen
hexadecimal converted.
Like these are the first
three bytes in a JPEG,
which are typically thought of
using hexadecimal like this.
But even though this looks
new, it's the exact same idea.
And I thought I'd tease
perhaps with a joke
that only a computer
scientist can understand.
OK, so that's a good one
that goes around each year.
So that of course is alluding
to just these addresses.
And now let me propose one other
debugging technique and explain like,
what the hell is going on
here on stage today, too.
So you have of course debug50, which
is a tool for debugging and walking
through code.
And silly though this
is, there is actually
this thing in the world of
programming, rubber duck debugging.
This is, in the absence of having a
TF or a CA to bounce ideas off of,
this is in the absence of having a
roommate around or roommate around
who wants to talk to
you about your code.
It's recommended that if you
have some bug in your program,
that you keep something
like this on your desk.
And in the absence of
roommates and friends
and hopefully doors closed,
you talk to the rubber duck.
And I feel silly even saying this
but there's a Wikipedia article
on this it's a real thing.
The idea here is that if you've
ever been in office hours
or you've been chatting
with a TFer friend
and just like talking about
your code and talking about what
it is you think your code is
doing, just very often that act
of saying something and hearing
yourself say it can help reinforce one,
what your code is in fact doing.
Or if you realize
verbally, wait a minute.
What I just said does not
seem to line up with the code,
finally that light bulb goes off.
And it doesn't have to be a duck.
I mean, you can talk to the wall
but that's a little stranger.
So at least this is a personification
of having someone like a colleague
to talk to.
So at the end of today or
during break by all means,
grab yourself a rubber duck the
debugger and keep it on your shelf.
It doesn't have to quite be this large.
But this is a genuine
debugging technique.
Like, in the absence of
understanding something,
don't necessarily turn only to
CS50 discourse or to office hours
or to sections or the like.
Literally try talking
yourself through it,
even if it feels a little bit silly.
And if it does really feel
silly, just look at him
and talk to yourself
in your head perhaps.
But that kind of enunciation of what
your code is doing or should be doing
will hopefully help all the
more light bulbs go off.
And eventually you can just
keep them on your shelf
and take off that
training wheel as well.
Let's go ahead and take
our five minute break here.
Grab a duck if you'd like and
we'll come back with more.
All right.
So we're back and we keep
thinking about memory.
Is this generally laid
out as having addresses,
but of course we've clarified
that a little bit in that we have
more of a canvas at our disposal now.
But even then we keep talking
about having things back
to back to back in memory.
But that simply needn't be the case.
Like, what we have now with
pointers and with malloc
and these kinds of functions is the
ability to get memory from anywhere
we want and somehow stitch it
together or connect these things.
But how do we actually do that
with the ingredients we now have?
And why might we want to?
So here is how we keep representing
something like an array.
An array, again, is just a
contiguous chunk of memory
where you store things
literally back to back to back.
But suppose that I've put six things
into this array, six numbers, one, two,
three, four, five, six.
What happens if I try to
put seven into this array?
What do I have to think
about or worry about?
Touching memory that I'm
not allowed to touch.
So I'd better not put it over here.
But what if seven must go in this array?
Well, I don't have too many options.
Like, if I fill the space I have to
either overwrite some value or put it
somewhere it shouldn't
be, and that should never
be an option because the
program could or will crash.
And so I could alternatively
just allocate more memory.
So how do I do that?
Well, if I've allocated this
array initially to be a size six,
I could encode, just allocate a new
array of size seven and then do what?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, add
all the numbers and seven.
So I can take this array, I can give
myself another one elsewhere in memory,
copy the values from old to
new, then maybe free the old.
And then move on with my life
because now I have enough memory.
Now, that fixes the problem.
And if we implemented
it in code correctly,
it would be by nature correct, assuming
there's enough memory in the computer.
But why is that arguably bad design?
AUDIENCE: It's a waste of space.
DAVID MALAN: It's a waste of space how?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, even though I
don't keep both around in the story
I'm telling, it's temporarily
pretty inefficient in that I'm
using twice as much memory as I actually
need only to then kind of downscale.
What else?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, if I want to
change the size of the array again,
whether bigger or even smaller perhaps,
if I remove items from the list, then
I just have to keep allocating
new memory, which is wasteful
and more importantly, it's
not just space inefficient.
In what other sense is inefficient?
Time, why?
Where is the time coming from?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So that's
an asymptotic notation.
This is copying something from one array
to another would be in big O of what?
They go of side, yeah.
So if we just genericize size
as n it's like big O of N.
It's a linear time operation,
which isn't horrible, right?
N squared is bad.
Linear has never really been bad but
we already know that log n is better,
constant time is best.
And so just wasting any amount of
time doesn't feel like optimal design.
And that all is a
function of arrays being
a fixed size and contiguous in
memory, back to back to back.
In fact, arguably there's one
other issue that could occur.
It's not so much if you
have a very small array.
But what if you have a huge
amount of memory available
but it's only in size
five or six increments?
Like, for whatever
reasons your computer's
been using some of this memory, this
memory, this memory, this memory,
and if you add up all the available
memory there's a lot of free space
but they're always separated
by memory that's in use.
So maybe this memory is free,
then there's a bite that's in use.
This memory is free,
there's a bite in use.
So your memory is quote
unquote very fragmented.
So you have lots of available
memory but it's not contiguous.
You cannot, in this model, allocate an
array of size seven if you don't have
that memory available contiguously.
So not as big of a concern
given enough memory,
but at least something that could arise.
So let's introduce the solution.
Something here called a linked list.
And the name kind of
describes what it is.
It's still a list of numbers but
it's linked by way of these arrows.
And we've used arrows before.
What have we used arrows to
represent in pictures past?
Yeah, so pointers.
So now that we have the expressiveness
of pointers, you can kind of digitally
stitch your data structures together
if you spend a little bit more memory.
So we've not really solved
the problem you identified,
which was the space use.
But if you're tolerant
of that and if you've
got enough memory at
your disposal and can
afford to spend it, why don't
we store for every number
not just the number but
also space for a pointer?
So each of the boxes I've
drawn here now doesn't just
have a box for the number itself n.
It's got really two boxes together,
one for n and one for something
we'll call next, which is
going to be a pointer to
or equivalently the address of
the next node, as we'll call it,
the next box in this list.
Now even though we've drawn it here
very prettily from left to right,
technically these boxes
could be anywhere in memory,
specifically in the
heap, we're going to see.
But they don't have to be back to back.
And so the fact that there are
these gaps in between the nodes
deliberately paints a picture
that these things don't have
to be back to back to back any more.
They can be anywhere.
And now suppose I've got these
five numbers, nine through 34.
Suppose I want to add another number.
Where do I put it?
I don't seem to have room.
But based on this picture, how much
you infer we're going to engineer this.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so why don't
we just allocate space for another
and it's not going to fit on
the board here but who cares?
We can put it here.
Put the new number in it and then just
add a line, an arrow from it to that.
And so this then is going to
be what we call a linked list
and it gives us dynamism.
It gives us the ability to grow or
shrink our data structure, addressing
your concern, not necessarily yours.
It's still a little space wasteful,
but we gain benefits for both of you,
your concerns time is a lot
better now because we don't
have to waste time copying the values.
We just add to the values.
And if we want to grow or subtract
it we only do as much work
as we're trying to add or subtract.
We don't have to worry
about fixing everything.
But there is some complexity here.
And given that we have
a whole bunch of these,
which would make problems
at five a little easier,
if you haven't quite
finished who done it.
Could we get for just one
demo today six volunteers?
Six volunteers?
All right.
Come on down, right in front here.
Well actually, come on up.
Come on up and have a two
and three over there, four.
No one over here today.
OK, OK, five.
OK, six.
OK, six, six.
Come on up.
All right.
We'll save this till the very end.
But let me give you guys in
the meantime, these numbers.
And if you don't mind
holding the numbers
out I want you to go
over to the left there
and just order yourselves just as the
picture on the screen OK, you'll be 17.
Let's see, let's see, nine.
I might have given out too many numbers.
OK, let me free that and give
you nine instead, if I may.
And give you, let's see.
You have 17?
OK, so 17.
And yeah, I'll have you go ahead and
flip yourselves if you don't mind.
22, and then 26.
And what do we got?
20, 34.
34.
OK, and you guys will
be slightly special.
So who wants to be literally first?
OK, so here first.
And who wants to be temporary?
OK, you'll be temporary, all right.
Come on over here.
OK, come on over here and if you
guys could step a little closer.
So we have 9, 17, 22, 26, 34, and give
yourselves like a foot in between.
And if you guys could use your left arms
to represent the pointers to visualize
who is linked to whom.
OK, and why don't you just point,
yes, very deliberately down.
So what's your name?
NAZLI: Nazli.
DAVID MALAN: Nazli.
So Nazli's left hand
will be a null pointer.
It's not pointing at anyone.
So literally just pointed down to
the ground, like ground electrically.
OK.
So now we just have to
have some first node.
So what's your name?
OLIVIA: Olivia.
DAVID MALAN: Olivia is a little special
here in that her paper has a word
and it's not just a number.
She represents a distinct
variable called first.
Because that one catch
with the linked list
is that you don't remember it by
way of the address of a contiguous
chunk of memory.
You remember a linked list by way of the
address of the first node in the linked
list.
And what's your name?
ACHMED: Achmed.
DAVID MALAN: Achmed.
So Achmed here happens to be the very
first node in the list right now.
So Olivia's left arm
is going to be pointing
to Achmed to represent that he
is the first node in the list.
OK, and what's your name?
JESS: Jess.
DAVID MALAN: Jess.
We're going to use Jess in just a
moment to complete some operations.
So suppose that we actually want to
insert some value into this list,
like the number 55.
All right, so the number 55 is going
to require a little bit of cleverness
here.
And so I need some place to store this.
I need to malloc.
So OK, you've been volunteered.
What's your name?
STELLA: Stella.
DAVID MALAN: Stella, come on up.
So malloc Stella.
And we will store the
number 55 in Stella's node.
And right now if you could just kind
of point your left hand anywhere.
It's kind of a garbage value.
OK, thank you.
And now what's your name again?
JESS: Jess.
DAVID MALAN: Jess.
OK, so Jess is going to help
us find the right space here.
So we can obviously see where 55
belongs if we're keeping this sorted.
But again, computers
don't have that luxury.
Moreover, we no longer
have random access.
We can't just jump to [0], [1], [2]
because there are these gaps between
them.
And just to make this more
clear, can every other of you
step forward or back so that
it just looks a little weird?
So you can no longer index
into this data structure
because again, it's not an array.
It's not back to back.
These things could be anywhere in
memory and it's only the pointers
that are linking everything together.
So Jess now is going to initially
point at the very same thing
that Olivia is pointing at,
the same address or Achmed.
All right, so now we
have a bit of redundancy.
But suppose we want to insert 55.
What kind of logic, what's
the pseudocode here for Jess
to find the location for Stella?
What should Jess do?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, keeps going
until she finds the null pointer,
or more specifically, till she finds
the null pointer or the right location
for this number if we
want to keep it sorted.
So let's do that.
So you're pointing at Achmed.
The number nine is not greater than 55.
So Stella belongs after Achmed.
So what are you going to do?
Good, you're going to point at Maria.
So you know to point at Maria why?
JESS: Because nine is less than 55.
DAVID MALAN: Nine is less than 55 but
also, Achmed isn't just story nine.
Right, he has this next
pointer that's telling
Jess where the next value is to look.
So his left hand is the substitute for
what would have been just ++ the world
of an array.
So you go ahead and physically walk
and let's just walk through this.
So now we're pointing here at 17.
It's not greater than.
We point next at Arunev.
OK, that's a 22.
Still not the right value.
We keep going.
What's your name?
Jeung Wan?
OK, that's not the right
number because he's holding 26.
And now we catch you again?
Nazli.
Still no good and now go ahead
and follow her left hand.
OK, so now we know that this has got to
be the right space because we haven't
found numerically the right space.
So if we could borrow you,
Stella, all the way over here.
Well, you're not technically
physically moving in memory
but this will just
make the story better.
OK, so yes, we're re-alloc-ing sort of.
So what are you going
to do now with Stella
now that you found the right location?
Leave her here, OK.
But she's just kind of orphaned now.
She's pointing at nowhere
and no one's pointing at her.
It's kind of sad.
And this is actually perfect.
Memory leak.
OK, so let's fix.
Who has the point at whom?
OK, good.
And now what should Stella point at?
Since now she is the end
of the list and she's just
pointing to some garbage value.
And she's pointing, to be clear, at
some garbage value because when you call
malloc you just get garbage values.
We overrode one of those
garbage values with 55 for n,
but the pointer has not
yet been overwritten.
So what you want to do, Jess?
To whom?
That's OK.
It's close.
What should her value be if
there's no one to her left?
Should be null.
OK, and how did we
represent null before?
Yeah, exactly.
Null, so now we have a list and now
just to fix things, your pointer,
so Jess is kind of temporary.
We don't really care what her value is.
But who's important over here?
What's your name again?
Olivia was first and now do we
have a list that is still linked?
We do.
And now, it of course took a
little while to walk through this.
And frankly I kind of told a lie.
I haven't really made
this faster because what
was the running time of this algorithm?
It was still a log of n.
But that's because what?
I was trying to maintain what property?
Sorted.
So suppose I relax that constraint.
Suppose that I didn't care
about being sorted order.
Can I do better than 0 of n in
order to have inserted Stella?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, Constan time,
where can I put her then?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So if we don't care
about sorted order, I
could have saved myself
a huge amount of time
and we could have inserted Stella here,
updated Olivia's hands, and updated
Stella's hands to point at Achmed.
And then we're done.
Constant time.
And here's an example of why big
0 of one doesn't mean one step.
That's constant time because it's like
moving Olivia's hand and Stella's hand
but not Achmed.
So that's at least two steps
but it's still always two steps.
So if we could get a round of
applause for our volunteers here?
[CHEERING] You can keep both your
numbers and these if you'd like.
Thank you so much.
May let this help you P set five.
Oh, sorry.
All right, thank you.
So that's of course just one operation.
There could have been other numbers.
Like, if we were trying to
insert five in sorted order,
we would have gotten our constant
time or maybe our omega of one
because in the best case, the number
might end up at the beginning.
20, had we inserted it
with our humans, might
have been a little more involved
because we kind of have to walk the list
as we did with Jess.
But then she's kind of got to
point at the person behind her
and the person in front of her
because she has to update more hands.
Which is to say, that doing
insertions or even deletions
requires a bit of re-stitching.
It's like kind of fixing
clothes here if you're
trying to maintain a contiguous thread
through all of these data structures.
But at the end of the day,
even though it uses pointers,
it really just boils down
to getting this logic right.
And in fact, let me do an example here
of some code of how we might do this.
I'm going to go ahead
and open up list 0.c
and take a look at how this here works.
So in list 0.c we have
the following code.
We first, in main, get a
positive number from the user.
So I'm going to wave my hands at this
because this is kind of old school now.
We've been using a do while loop to
get a positive number from the user.
And I'm calling it capacity.
So this is an example of getting it
in from the user, calling it capacity.
Capacity meaning the maximum
possible size for a data structure.
That would be a term of art there.
Here now is where, per
week two the class,
I allocate an array for ints
this many ints capacity.
So that, too, is hopefully familiar.
There's no pointers yet.
There's nothing too fancy.
I'm just allocating an array of size
based on what the human just typed in.
But here's where it gets
a little interesting.
The purpose of this program is to just
prompt the user for that many numbers
again and again and again.
So I can type in 1, 2, 3 or
5, 17, 20, 22, and so forth.
And just build up an array
of numbers and memory,
but I'm going to trip over the problem
we identified a little bit ago.
So here we go.
I initialize size to zero
because initially there's
nothing in the structure.
While size is less than my
capacity, so while the current size
is less than the max, so
to speak, do the following.
First I'm going to get
a number from the user.
And the goal is to now insert
this number into this list.
But now I'm going to do
a quick sanity check.
Let me check and make sure this number
is or isn't in the list already,
because I don't want to have duplicates.
Why?
Just because.
I want this to be a very
clean list, no duplicates.
And so this loop of code here, maybe
from week one, week two, week three,
is just an example of iterating through
an array, looking for the number,
and if so, remembering that
I found it with a Boolean
so that I have an answer found or
not found in a Boolean variable.
OK.
So that's all that code is doing.
Still no magic.
So now is where the interesting
part of the story happens.
So if the number was not found in the
list already, here is how per week two,
we add a number to the end of an array.
Because if the size is
initially zero, numbers [0]
is where the first number should go.
If size's initial is one
at this point, numbers [1]
is where the new number should go.
And then I should increment size.
But there's a problem here in that
once I print out these numbers
and the program ends, I can only
have inputted as many numbers
as are available, as
I have capacity for.
So it's kind of constrained.
So what if I want to do a
little better than this?
Enlist 1.c which does now introduce new
material, or at least an application
of the topics this week and last?
Here in line nine is
technically how I can allocate
an array before I know the size of it.
So an array, recall, is
just a chunk of memory
identified by some word, like
numbers or students or whatnot.
But technically we've seen that
there's kind of this equivalence, where
if an array is just the chunk of memory,
you can technically refer to an array
by an address, the address of its
first byte just like a string.
So this on line nine is a little new.
But it's kind of that idea.
Give me a pointer called numbers
but initialize it to null.
There's no space for the number.
But this pointer therefore doesn't
point to any chunk of memory.
It would be like Olivia standing
up here awkwardly with no one
to point at because we've only
allocated space for the first pointer,
not for everyone else on the stage.
So capacity is by default zero.
So here the rest of the
program is pretty similar.
I go ahead and infinitely
prompt the user for a number.
I check for errors.
It turns out if you
read the documentation
for get int it will return a
special constant called int
max if the user stops for writing input.
Here I'm just checking
with a loop in a Boolean,
whether or not this number is
in the list, same as before.
But here's where I start to
use some new functionality.
If the number was not found already
in the list, and the size of the list
already equals its capacity,
that is if it is filled,
what do I have to do conceptually now?
If I've got an array whose purpose
in life, as we proposed earlier,
is just to grow it?
I need to add space for it.
So I need to add space,
as we were proposing.
Even though this is kind of lame
in that it's a little inefficient,
here's how we do it.
I can simply call real alloc, passing
in the array that whose memory
I want to reallocate.
And I just tell realloc
how much space I now want.
So here, this is the size
of the int, four bytes.
And this is how many bytes I want.
So whatever the current size is,
realloc give me one more byte.
And then realloc gets
assigned to numbers
and I check if it's null or not null.
And I'm keeping it a little simple.
We could add some additional error
checking here, but what does realloc
do?
Realloc is pretty cool because
if you pass to realloc,
a pointer to a chunk of memory
that's like of this size, realloc
will look in your
computer's memory and if it
sees a bigger chunk of
memory over here, it
will handle the copying of
everything over to it for you.
And then return to the address
of the new chunk of memory
and free the old for you.
So does the switcheroo.
It's still linear time but
this is how you would use it
without having to alloc and free and use
a four loop like we described before.
And then you can go ahead and put
the number in the list as before.
So the only new thing here, even
though we're going through it quickly,
is that this is how you call realloc.
You pass in a pointer
that's previously pointing
to a chunk of memory or even null.
That's OK.
If you pass it in a pointer
that's pointing null,
it will give you back the address of
just one byte and then the next time
two bytes, three bytes, and four bytes.
But with linked lists things
get a little more interesting.
And the syntax is going to be
a little funky but let's see.
Here it turns out is how we can
implement each of our human volunteers
in code.
Each of them I called a node
and node is a term of art in CS.
It refers to some data structure
that contains some information.
Each of them was holding a
number, which we called an int.
And then each of them,
this is kind of funky,
had a left hand called next that
was meant to point to someone
who looked just like them structurally.
So the idea here is that we don't
want to just have another structure
inside of a structure,
otherwise you would
get this sort of infinite Russian
doll kind of thing going on.
You instead want to say,
each of these structures
has a pointer to someone else who
looks like them structurally, too.
And that's how we get the left
arm metaphor implemented in code.
So that just defines a
node, one of our volunteers.
Meanwhile though, here's how we would
implement Olivia in one line of code.
So Olivia was herself
a pointer to a node.
She didn't have a number, right?
Her sign just said first.
She was not holding a number.
So we don't need a whole
structure for Olivia.
We just need a pointer to
one such node structure.
But initially she was just kind
of standing here so we'll just
say she was null initially.
So the rest of this code is presumably
about malloc-ing someone like Stella
from the audience, updating Olivia,
using Jess to actually update pointers
temporarily.
So let's see what this
looks like in code.
So while true, I'm just going to prompt
the user for numbers like before.
As before, I'm going to check
for errors in the same way.
Here's a little different.
Here's the block of code wherein I just
check if my current linked list already
has the number I'm trying to insert.
But remember, we took away the
expressiveness of square brackets.
Can't do that anymore.
I have to now do this with pointers.
So here we go.
I, with my four loop,
initialize a pointer, Jess,
to point at the same thing
Olivia was pointing at, numbers.
So again, Jess was also just a pointer.
She was not holding a number.
She was holding PTR, so
she was just one pointer
pointing at the same thing as Olivia.
Here we're saying, so long
as Jess is not equal to null,
so as long as Jess doesn't
walk off the edge of the stage,
go ahead and do the following.
What do I want to do?
And this syntax is new.
We saw at the beginning
of today the dot operator,
which says take a data
structure like students
and go into it with the dot operator.
Get their name and their dorm.
That was because the first demo
today did not use pointers.
It just used structures.
Now we're using structures and pointers.
And so the syntax
changes just a tiny bit.
When you have a pointer that
is a pointer to a structure
and you want to follow that
pointer and go to that structure,
the one piece of syntax in C that maybe
actually maps to reality or concept
is this arrow operator, which
means follow the left hand,
look at the structure,
and get at that number.
And so if the volunteer's number equals
the number that Jess was looking for,
go ahead and say found is true.
Otherwise update Jess
or pointer to equal
whatever her left hand is pointing at.
So if Jess was
temporarily pointing here,
she would then update
herself by pointing there.
And so that's all this code is doing.
Jess starts to point at whatever
her left hand was pointing at.
She moves physically on the stage.
All right, so now is where
things get a little ugly.
And we'll do this with a hand-wave
because I think this one is better
done at a slower pace on one's own.
And we'll come over these kinds
of things in section and beyond.
Here's how I allocate
space for a new node.
When I said malloc Stella, it's
this line of code here, 45.
Malloc space for the size of a
node and store it in the person
that Stella embodied.
Otherwise, if there is not enough
memory, if something goes wrong,
return one.
Meanwhile, here's how we
add the number to the list.
So this is exactly what
Jess ended up acting out.
First we handed Stella her
number, which is line 52 here.
We technically told her to
point at a garbage value,
so I've improved the code since.
So line 53 would be like telling
Stella, point here, not here.
So that's just cleaning up
that omission last time.
And then here we have
the same kind of code
again, a four loop that
looks kind of funky
but it's just like updating the
hand as you walk through the list.
And here's where the
interesting part happens.
At the very end of our story, Jess kind
of manipulated our volunteer's arms.
So if not pointer next, which
is a cryptic way of saying,
if pointer next equals equals null.
So if Jess has found
the end of the list,
go ahead and update whoever
she is pointing at's
left hand to point to
Stella, the new node.
Then break out because we're done.
So syntactically, this
is hard and problem
set five will afford us opportunities
to walk through very similar code.
But for now, just realize
that all we're doing
is instead of just using super simple
arithmetic, plus one, plus one,
plus one, we're just kind of following
these arrows, following these arrows.
And the kind of syntax
we'll use for that
is just this, which is not
very readable at first glance.
But that's why I grasp onto, if
you are a more visual person,
the kinds of hand
manipulation and arm changes
that we were doing here
physically with our volunteers.
And then we, again,
print up [INAUDIBLE]..
The last thing here
I'll note, and you'll
do this in problem set five,
is here's how you might
free a whole length list of numbers.
I just kind of congratulated
our volunteers and everyone
left the stage, thereby being freed.
But if we wanted to do this more
methodically, we could use a four loop
but here I chose to do a
while loop, because it's
a little more succinct design wise.
Here was our pointer, temporary
pointer pointing at numbers.
And here I can say while pointer
is not null because if it's null
my work is done.
Here I go ahead and say,
update this value next to equal
whoever's next in the list.
Free whoever's currently in the list.
And then update the next pointer.
So again, don't worry too much
about the lower level details here.
But just take away for today that we
do now have a way of implementing,
in code, the higher level
intuition that derived
from this kind of data structure.
But don't fret yet
about the code itself.
But we now have the ability to stitch
data structures together like this.
Upside of which is now
we get dynamism, right?
We're no longer stuck
painting our ourselves
into the proverbial corner with arrays
by not allocating enough memory.
Or conversely, wasting memory by
allocating way too much just so we
don't have to deal with the problem.
But we pay a price with the linked list.
We get dynamism and can more
efficiently add a node, subtract a node,
and we just have to in constant
time, update those pointers.
But we spend more memory
for all these darn pointers.
And frankly, the code is more complex.
So recall from our first or second
week, human time, programmer time
is a valuable resource.
And making something harder and
more time consuming to implement
might not be a price you want to pay.
And so even I was just
chatting with a colleague
yesterday about how in graduate
school I used to cut corners,
especially late at
night when writing code.
And I would write sometimes
deliberately really bad code
that might take like
eight hours to analyze
some data set for some research project
I was working on because you know what?
I realized it was faster for me to
write bad code, poorly designed, that
takes eight hours because
in those eight hours
I could just go to sleep, frankly.
Now I would say that was only
because my advisor was not grading me
on correctness and design and style.
But it is a manifestation
of a very actual resource
that I don't recommend you cut
that particular corner for now,
since one of the goals of being in
a class is to get better at design.
But at the end of the day
and in the real world,
even CS50 staff and I are
constantly making decisions.
Well, yeah, we could improve
this feature of help50
but it's going to take a week to do it.
Or we can just throw in some extra
line of code and get it done now.
And it's a trade off.
And this is what makes
code good and bad.
And when you start to cut these
corners in the real world,
you start to accumulate what the
world would call technical debt.
And debt tends not to
be such a good thing.
And that speaks to the price
you're paying in the long term
because it might take me and
the staff longer this summer
now to go back in and clean all that up.
And God forbid, overnight
frankly, and this
happened more often than I should
admit, my code was buggy and bailed out
at like 2:00 AM I wake up eight hours
later thinking, my data's ready.
No.
I should have done it
right the first time so
I could rerun the code again and again.
So what else do we get
now from this ability
to have pointers in data structures?
So there's this picture here
from Mather's Dining Hall.
The cap represent the
notion of actual trays.
And we've been using the
stack in a very low level
arcane way to talk about
memory management, which
isn't all that useful to
us for solving problems.
But the data structure is.
It turns out there is a data structure
in computer science called a stack.
And your computer, Mac
or PC, are constantly
using it to manage functions and
memory, but we can use it, too,
for various applications.
We can implement a data structure
within I have two operations.
They're conventionally
called push and pop.
Though it's like add and subtract.
You can call it anything you
want but most programmers would
call it push and pop.
Push is like adding a tray to the
stack and pop is like taking one off.
But just as the name
implies with the stack,
what's this characteristic of a stack
is that it is an example of a LIFO data
structure, last in first out, L-I-F-O.
Now what does that mean?
Well, if one of the staff from the
dining hall comes by with a new tray
that's just been cleaned and he or
she puts it on the top of the stack,
which one is a normal human
being going to grab first?
The last one in, right?
It'd be strange and kind of
difficult to get down on your knees
and pull out the bottom one, even
though that would be more fair, right?
Like that little tray down there has
been waiting the longest to be used.
But it's under the weight of
the whole stack, literally.
But that, nonetheless, is
how a stack would work.
And you can implement the
stack now in a couple of ways.
And here's where the world gets
interesting in programming,
in that there is this
distinction between design
of data structures and low
level implementation details.
A stack is as I've described
it, a LIFO data structure.
Push and pop, last in, first out.
That's it.
How you implement that
could be any number of ways.
For instance, I could implement a
stack as a C data type, custom one,
that has an array of numbers
for this capacity where capacity
is some big constant like 100,
1,000, however many trays I want
to store so long as I
keep track of the size
of how many trays are in it so that I
can always make sure its size less than
or equal to the capacity.
Just to make sure I don't try
to cram too many trays in there.
But what's a downside
of this implementation
of Mather House's stack of trays?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Limited space, exactly.
I have consciously hard coded
capacity to be some fixed value.
So if we buy a new tray or
a whole box of trays arrive,
might not fit there, right?
Once I exhaust this remaining
space, I need to make a new pile
or I need to store them elsewhere.
I'm just out of space.
So maybe this is a good design
decision in that it reflects reality.
Or maybe it's stupid because now
I can't store even more trays
when they come in via shipment.
So I could solve that.
We know from our brief
example a moment ago,
you could just make your array dynamic.
Don't preallocate it
to be of size capacity.
Just declare it to be a
pointer that will eventually
point to maybe space for
one tray or 100 trays
or 1,000 trays or maybe 1,001 trays if
we realloc the space again and again.
And when you start writing code that
involves other people, whether it's
for some school project or a personal
project or just in the real world,
this is where life
gets more interesting,
too, because so long as you and I,
if my colleague kind of decide, OK.
I'm going to expose push
and pop as the operations.
I will implement push and pop.
You don't have to worry about
the low level implementation
details in my own design decisions.
You just have to read
my documentation and not
care how I've implemented it because
I have abstracted that away for you
and given you just an API.
Push and pop would be an API,
application programming interface.
All you need to know
is that you can trust
that I will implement push and pop.
And you might dislike it
ultimately, if I limit your space,
but to understand that you
need to read the documentation
to know what features my
implementation are providing.
Now this of course is the ridiculousness
that ensues every year or so, whereby
people line up to buy an iPhone.
Now, why would it be a bad thing
if Apple used a stack when people
arrive at 3:00 AM for their iPhones?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
The person who came last
would get their phone first,
which is fantastic for that person.
But it's really unfair to everyone else.
So Apple of course, like most stores,
if they even have this problem,
have queues or lines whereby it's a FIFO
data structure, first in, first out.
Were the first person in line
hopefully gets his or her iPhone first.
So how can you implement
those operations or that API?
Might call it nq and dq,
but add, subtract, whatever.
But these are the terms of art.
And we might implement it as follows.
A queue might just need a little bit
more information than capacity and size
alone.
You have to remember who's
in front, potentially,
just so that when that
person gets out of line,
you don't have to move all
of your data in the array
just like the humans would walk forward.
That's a waste of time.
Every time someone's
ready to buy their phone,
why does n-1 people have
to take a step forward?
Why not just bring the phone to them
and save that inefficient use of time?
Or we could do it like this,
more of a dynamic data structure.
And we won't do the code here.
But we've seen, for instance, the
example in our list zero, one,
and two code, how you could
start with a fixed size array,
make it dynamic with malloc and
realloc, and how you might further
make it dynamic with a linked list,
albeit with trade offs of time
and space.
There's this great short video I
thought I'd share here, wherein in Jack
learns the facts about queues and stacks
which distinguishes these two data
structures in a way that actually
paints an even more clear picture of how
they're distinct.
If we can dim the lights
for 60 seconds or so.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Once upon a time there
was a guy named Jack.
When it came to making friends,
Jack did not have the knack.
So Jack went to talk to the
most popular guy he knew.
He went up to Lu and
asked, what do I do?
Lu saw that his friend
was really distressed.
Well, Lu began, just
look how you're dressed.
Don't you have any clothes
with a different look?
Yes, said Jack.
I sure do.
Come to my house and
I'll show them to you.
So they went off to Jack's
and Jack showed Lu the box
where he kept all his shirts
and his pants and his socks.
Lu said, I see you have
all your clothes in a pile.
Why don't you wear some
others once in awhile?
Jack said, well, when I
remove clothes and socks,
I wash them and put
them away in the box.
Then comes the next
morning and up I hop.
I go to the box and get
my clothes off the top.
Lu quickly realized
the problem with Jack.
He kept clothes, CDs,
and books in a stack.
When he reached for
something to read or to wear,
he chose the top book or underwear.
Then when he was done he
would put it right back.
Back it would go, on top of the stack.
I know the solution,
said a triumphant Lu.
You need to learn to
start using a queue.
Lu took Jack's clothes
and hung them in a closet.
And when he had emptied
the box, he just tossed it.
Then he said, now Jack, at the end
of day, put your clothes on the left
when you put them away.
Then tomorrow morning
when you see the sun
shine, get your clothes from the
right, from the end of the line.
Don't you see, said
Lu, it will be so nice.
You'll wear everything once
before you wear something twice.
And with everything in queues
in his closet and shelf,
Jack started to feel quite
sure of himself all thanks
to Lou and his wonderful queue.
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: So that isn't to
say that queues are all that
and stacks are a bad data structure.
They actually each have
their own applications.
And in fact, one common use for
stacks beyond memory management,
as we discuss in a couple of weeks
when we start exploring HTML and web
programming, you'll see
that HTML itself, this
is the language in which
web pages are written.
That you'll soon be able
to write if not already.
This is a language that actually
has a nested hierarchy to it.
Who, where by a browser, might actually
use a stack to analyze the HTML
that composes a web page to determine,
for instance, if it is correct or not.
But there's so many other tools
that we can now add to your toolkit.
And even though we'll look at each
of these just briefly, each of them
derives from these very two
simple principles, the ability
to come up with custom data structures
inside of which are pointers,
or the ability to stitch
one thing to another.
So here's an example of what a
computer scientist would call a tree.
The node here we've drawn
as circles just because.
But the nodes in a tree are
much like a family tree, where
each node has zero or more
children or descendants, maybe
a parent or other ancestors.
And so we'll call things
like the first node
at the very top in a data structure
called the tree, the root of the tree,
albeit growing downward like
this like a family tree.
Anything at the very bottom of the
tree that only has arrows going into it
will be called children
or leaves of the tree.
And so this might be a way to
lay out data in a useful way.
In fact, if you think back to
when we had things like numbers
like this, thus far any time we dealt
with numbers or words or Mike Smiths,
we would just order them from
left to right in an array
and then search the array either in
big O of end time linearly from left
to right.
But we did better using what?
Binary search, but for binary
search it needed to be an array
and it needed to be sorted.
And the problem I never
dealt with was we never
actually added another
page to the phone book.
We never actually tried to
add more numbers to our array.
And yet today, we've kind of identify
these very glaring issues with arrays,
which is that you're kind
of painted into a corner.
If you allocate only so much space,
you use it all up and then darn it,
you want to add more to the array.
So how can we maybe still lay
out data in sorted order, still
leverage something like
logarithmic time and divide
and conquer, but get today's
benefit of the dynamism whereby
we can grow the data structure
and shrink it very incrementally,
without having to all of a sudden
reallocate the whole structure?
Well, instead of laying out these
numbers, which are conveniently
numbered as multiples
of 11 here, 22, 33, 55,
what if we laid them
out like this in memory?
We won't look at the code for this,
but think of each of these circles
as a structure, a data structure,
inside of which there's
an int n, how many pointers apparently?
Seven total on the screen.
But how about within each
node, like this one here?
There's a number n, 55.
And what else?
How many pointers?
Just two.
Two maximally, in fact, because
the leaves, it would seem,
have zero by definition.
And technically, if I hadn't added 22,
maybe there could just be one child.
This is what we call a binary
tree because every node has
at most two children, 0, 1, or 2.
And it's technically a binary search
tree because of a special property.
It's very searchable because if you look
at any node, its left child is smaller.
And if you look at any node,
its right child is bigger.
And that's a recursive
definition, so to speak.
You can look at any node in the
tree and that definition is true.
Even the leaves, because it's
sort of a vacuous statement
to say it's greater than its left
child if there is no left child.
It's sort of trivially true.
So what's nice about
this data structure?
Well, suppose I want to
search for the number 22.
Like our linked list, and like Olivia
being the special first pointer,
a binary tree in a
computer's memory would just
have one special pointer, called root or
first or whatever you want to call it.
And if you want to look for 22
just like Olivia and Jess were,
you might look here.
And say, hmm, 55 is greater than 22.
So which way do I go?
Left obviously.
And here, you know, if we
were doing this visually
we could snip off that whole subtree.
And you would see half of the problem
be torn away like the phone book.
22 versus 33, of
course, this is greater.
So we go here and we find it.
And long story short,
that was not linear
because we weren't
searching all of the nodes.
And if conceptually we were
chopping the tree in half,
in half, in half every
time we went left or right,
what should be the running time
of search on a binary search tree?
Log base 2 of n, or just
logarithmic as we've seen.
Now it's not necessarily
always as prettily balanced.
This is very deliberately chosen.
You can get perverse situations
where it just kind of devolves
into a long linked list.
But it still is a binary search tree.
It was just poorly built. But at
least if we keep a balance like this,
we can gain some benefits.
And here's how we would implement
your proposed integer and two nodes.
Instead of just calling
it next, I'm going
to call it more semantically
usefully left and right.
And notice that struct node
is just a pointer called left.
Struct node is a pointer called right.
And that's how we implement these.
And what do you think the leaves have
as their values for left and right?
The leaves of the tree had no
children, by definition, so what's
the value of left and right?
Null.
So they're just sort of pointing down
at the floor as zero, null, values.
So we're not going to write
the code for this now,
but we can leverage weak zero's ideas.
Divide and conquer, binary search.
We can leverage last week and
this week's ideas of structures
and dynamic memory and
technically the heap in order
to start to build up data structures
like this, that now give us dynamism
that can grow and shrink as needed.
And just so you've seen
the code, here might
be an implementation of a
function for binary search tree
that, given the roots of the
tree, finds for you true or false,
whether or not something is in it.
So I want to search for
a number n in this tree.
So this here is, again,
a pointer to the root
just like Olivia was a pointer to
the first node in the linked list.
So if the tree is null,
return false because it's
kind of a stupid question to ask.
If there's no tree being passed
in, it's clearly not there.
So return false.
That's our special case to ensure
that we don't dive too deeply.
But here's a very cool
application of a past idea.
If n is less than the n at
the current node in the tree,
and remember the arrow just
says, go there and look at n,
we know we want to look at the
left hand side of the tree.
So do we have an algorithm to
search a tree for a specific value?
Just so happens that tree
is now smaller because it's
this half of the tree on the left.
We do.
We have a function called search
that takes a number as input
and takes a tree as a pointer.
That doesn't have to be the whole tree.
It can be a sub-tree because again, a
tree is kind of recursively defined,
because every left child and right
child itself might have children.
So it's a smaller tree
but it's still a tree.
So I can answer this question.
If n is less than the
current node's own n value,
I can just return the answer to
calling search on the same number,
but passing in just the
left half of the tree.
So this is like the tree version
of tearing the phone book in half
and searching only the left half.
And you can perhaps guess, if you're
following along at this point,
if n is greater than
the current node, we're
just going to search to the right.
And that's three cases.
What's the fourth possible case?
Yeah, if n equals the current node.
And so in that case I'm just
going to trivially return true.
And this is kind of beautiful.
It's not from one perspective.
It's not obvious at first
glance, how this works.
And it's not comfortable necessarily
if you're not used recursion that much.
But what's beautiful
about this, especially
if we get rid of the stupid
curly braces and a lot of stuff
it's not really
intellectually interesting,
you are reducing this problem to
really just these lines of code.
Check for null, return false.
Check if it's less than,
just recurse on the left.
Check if it's greater
than, recurse on the right.
Otherwise you found it.
It's literally the same idea or
spirit as our divide and conquer
approach for the phone
book, just implemented now
using trees or nodes
linked together in a tree.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Tree arrow n, so tree,
recall, is a pointer to a node.
So that, just like Olivia was a
pointer to a node in a linked list,
this would be like Olivia
standing here and instead
of pointing at a line of students,
sort of pointing at a tree of students
that fans out this way.
So tree, we could call
it anything we want.
I just called it tree, represents that.
And meanwhile, tree left would be like
if Olivia was pointing at a node here.
Actually, if Olivia is pointing
at the root of the tree here,
tree left would be go look
at the left half of the tree
or the right half of the tree.
If again, our volunteers were
laid out on stage like a fan,
like a tree instead of a list.
So we've seen a whole bunch
of algorithms that might
have any number of these running times.
And up until now kind
of the best running time
really has been this for
the fanciest of algorithms.
But we have seen constant
time here and there.
And even today if we want
to insert into a linked list
and we don't really
care about the order,
we can just plug the new value right
there after Olivia and before Achmed
and get our constant time.
But wouldn't it be nice if more
operations were constant timed?
One step, two step, three
stepped or some finite number?
And it turns out we can achieve
this with a bit of thought.
And we can leverage another sort
of familiar idea as follows.
So like here, for instance, is
some unusually large playing cards,
which actually do exist if you
just Google jumbo playing cards
and look for them on Amazon.
Suppose I wanted to
sort this deck of cards.
I could go through
the deck one at a time
and order them both by their
suite, like clubs and hearts
and so forth, and also by their numbers.
But odds are if you're like me,
you're going to probably try
to make the problem a little simpler.
And if you see the king of
spades here, I put him over here.
Nine of spades, I'm
going to put that there.
10 of spades coincidentally.
I'm going to put that over here.
Then I'm going to do what
with the hearts, probably?
You know, probably I'm not going
to go through one at a time.
I'm going to kind of
bucketize each of the cards.
So here's the ace of clubs, so
I'm going to make a third pile.
Here's a couple of diamonds.
So that's my fourth pile.
And then I'm just going to repeat this,
because it's a nice simple algorithm.
It's going to make my life a
little easier in just a moment
once everything is in the right pile.
But this is a general notion
of what we'll call hashing.
And I'm not going to finish
it because surprise, surprise,
we're going to get 13
cards in each pile.
But this is a more
fundamental notion of hashing.
You take as input something
from your list of inputs.
You look at it and you make
a decision based on it.
And in this case, my hash value is
going to be zero, one, two, three,
two because it's going to
go into the hearts pile.
And what is a hash function?
It's just going to be a function
in code or in my brain that
just makes a decision based on output
and outputs a hash value, which
in this case is going to be that
pile, that pile, that pile, that pile,
or if we want to be more precise,
zero, one, two, or three.
If those four piles are
implemented it's like four arrays
or some kind of stacks, really.
I seem to be making a stack of cards.
Now it's not done.
If I want to sort
these things later, I'm
still going to have to sort
each of the piles of 13.
But I've kind of made the problem
a little easier for myself
in that I've spread it out
over four equivalent problems.
But the key ingredient here
is that notion of hashing.
And honestly, if you've ever watched a
TA or professor deal with these things
at the end of some class that has blue
books, if a whole bunch of students
at the end of the hour come down and
start handing in their blue books
it's a complete mess.
And if the TFs or professor
wants to organize these,
you might make a whole bunch of piles.
All the L last names will go there.
E will go there.
F will go there.
And maybe in this case you'll
alphabetize as you go, thereby
making this problem easier, too.
That is a hash function.
You take as input a
student's name, you look
at the first letter of
his or her last name,
and you decide whether it
goes in bucket zero, one,
or maybe 25 if you're indeed hashing
based on the English alphabet.
So hashing is something we've
all done, even if we've never
slapped that name on it before.
So how might we leverage
this kind of ingredient
and get ourselves closer to the
holy grail of data structures, which
would be constant time for everything?
Like none of this linear,
none of this logarithmic time.
So suppose we have an array or a
table, we'll call it, like this.
I'm going to call this a hash
table because I want to leverage
the idea of this hash function.
And suppose that what I want to store
in here are just things like names.
And I want to go ahead
and store the name
Alice, because she
turned in her exam first.
So here I might have [0]
through [25] or in general, n-1.
So there's 26 buckets total.
Where might I be inclined to put Alice?
I might just hash her
to zero because Alice,
we'll use her first name,
not last, because she never
seems to have a last name.
So first name, Alice,
brackets zero, she goes there.
Then Bob comes up, turns in his exam.
Where does he go?
[1] and then maybe Brendan comes over.
Damn it.
No room for Brendan's exam.
Why?
Because he hashes to the same value.
And this can happen.
Like, you might hash to the same value.
And here it was not a big deal.
I kept getting diamond,
diamond, diamond.
That's fine because this
data structure grows.
But this is an array, it would seem.
And I could write Alice
here, I could write Bob here,
but Brendan should be written there too.
But I don't want to give Bob his
exam back just to accept Brendan's.
So where could I put Brendan?
Maybe I'll kind of cheat and just put
him here because there's room, right?
This is all free in this story so far.
But then Charlie comes forward.
What do we do with Charlie?
Now Brendan is where Charlie should be.
So now I've just kind of made a
mess but I have so much free space
and odds are I'm not going to have a
student, no offense, whose name starts
with a Z or an X or and some of
the statistically less likely ones.
So why don't we use those spaces?
And we could, but this is
an example algorithmically
of linear probing, where you linearly
top to bottom just kind of probe
the data structure looking
for space and just drop
the values in the first available.
And initially it's nice and
clean and nice and efficient
because if I want to look
for Alice's exam later, boom,
she's on the top of the pile.
Bob, boom, second in the pile.
But then Charlie, not
quite where he should be.
So eventually with this
approach of linear probing
it's space efficient in that you pack
everyone into your data structure.
But it eventually devolves
into something linear.
If Alice came and given her
exam last, by nature of space,
she might end up at
the bottom of the pile
and that does not make
her easy to find later.
So what if we instead
change the data structure
and use elements from today and past?
Let's use an array here of pointers
drawn vertically just because.
And then why don't we string
students' names off the right of this?
So this is an excerpt from a text that
explores exactly this data structure.
It's called a hash table,
not with linear probing,
but with separate chaining, whereby
your data structure, your hash table,
is technically an array.
This time it's upsized 31,
because the book's example was
about day of the month for birthdays.
And so the data structure has not just
an array, though, but what other data
structure combined with it?
It's a kind of linked list.
So what's nice here is that S Adams,
so Adams, starting with A in our story.
Now they're using birthdays if
you read this in the context.
But suppose that Adams is
the only one with birthday
on the second of some month.
Well, he or she might end up here.
And that's no big deal if someone else
has the same birthday in this example,
because we can either walk
the list as we did with Jess
and just string him or her at
the end of this data structure.
Or we can just kind of insert
them at the very beginning
and just use some constant time changes
to peoples' left hand to fit them in.
The point is though, the data
structure no longer is an array only.
It's an array of 31 buckets,
four piles, 26 piles, 31 piles.
But each of those piles
can grow vertically,
so to speak, or in this
case laterally because we're
implementing the idea
of these data structures
now by using an actual linked list.
So why is this actually better or worse?
Well one, is there any limit now on how
many students can turn in their exams
or have birthdays?
No because we just keep growing
it wider and wider and wider.
Why is this then a good thing?
Well now if I want to look someone
up, if I know their name starts
with A or in the
birthday example, I know
their birthday is on
the second of the month,
I know deterministically,
no matter what,
what bucket they will
be in in the array.
Now, they might be in a long string of
people with similar names or birthdays.
But they're going to be there,
deterministically, predictably,
again and again.
And the beautiful thing is if my hash
function is well-implemented, uniform
so to speak statistically, then it would
be nice if almost all of these chains
are roughly the same length.
It would be pretty lame if
this chain were really huge
and then every other chain were
shorter because that's just
an opportunity for better design.
So in real terms, a hash table,
when implemented like this,
should decrease in this concrete
case, by a factor of like 31,
how long it takes to find someone.
So the time is one divided by 31
because if all the chains are roughly
the same length, you have chopped
up your data set into four piles, 26
piles, 31 piles, each of
which is one fourth or 126th
or 131st the size of the whole data set.
Now asymptotically, per
couple of weeks ago,
that is algorithmically irrelevant.
That's big O of the
same thing, so to speak.
But in real terms, having it
taking a quarter of as much time,
126th the amount of
time, 131st the real time
is literally going to save
us times on our watches.
Like that in real human
times will save time.
And in fact, what you'll see in problem
set five, in which you implement
your first spell checker,
you'll see that that's
what we're trying to optimize for.
In fact, as a quick teaser before we
look at our final data structure here,
you'll be challenged as part
of this problem set optionally,
if you'd like to opt in, to
compete on the big board.
Once your code is
working per check 50, you
can actually run a separate command with
check 50 to post it to the leader board
here.
And right now, damn it, Brian
is beaning both Doug and me
because his implementation
of the spell checker
takes only 4.81 seconds and only
7.4 kilobytes versus my 82 megabytes
of memory implementing a spell
check over the whole lot of words.
But how do you decide how to
minimize space or minimize time
and how do you mitigate
some of the trade-offs?
Well, let's look at one final
data structure to consider.
This is perhaps the most sophisticated
and it takes up more space
and so it's hard to paint on the screen.
But suppose we did this.
Suppose we were trying to store in
our data structure people's names.
We could do this with an
array of a lot of strings.
And we could do linear
search and Brian or Doug
or I could just use linear search
big O of n and find any one you want.
That's not so great.
We could somehow use binary search
if we used a tree or an array
but kept the names sorted.
We know we can do better.
Just as we found Mike Smith
pretty quickly in week zero.
But what if we could find
names in constant time?
Whereby no matter how many
words are in the tree, no matter
how many words are in the
dictionary more generally,
still takes me the same
amount of time to find anyone?
And it doesn't get longer and
longer the more names we add?
So here is a type of tree
goofily called a trie, T-R-I-E,
which is an excerpt from retrieval,
which is weird because it's retrieval
and retrival but this
is a trie, T-R-I-E.
Each of the nodes in a trie,
essentially, are an array themselves.
Technically they're a structure
with a little more inside of them.
And you'll see this in the walk
through that Zamyla put together.
But each of the nodes in
the trie are an array.
Each of those arrays elements is
a pointer to another such array.
And the way you store words in
a trie is not with characters,
but implicitly with pointers.
So if we want to put someone's
name like Maxwell in here,
we hash into this trie using the
first letter of Maxwell's name, which
is of course m.
And that's going to be the 13th element
in the array in my 26-element array
here.
I'm going to change that
originally null pointer
to be a pointer to another node.
And then I'm going to hash on the second
letter of Maxwell's name, which is A,
and I'm going to allocate
a pointer to another array.
And then repeat that process
for every letter in his name.
So if I hash on his first letter,
second letter, third letter, every time
I do that it leads me to a new array.
What's not shown here is that
each of these arrays is size 26.
It would just be atrocious
to see on the screen.
So it does use a bunch of memory.
But the end of this, there's a special
symbol drawn here is a delta symbol,
but it can be anything, that
just means Maxwell stops here.
There's a word here.
So how many steps does it take
to find any name in the tree?
Well, to find Maxwell it's
M-A-X-W-E-L-L. So that's seven steps.
For Maria it'd be M-A-R-I-A.
That would be five steps.
So it's still dependent on the
number of letters in the name.
But if there is a billion
names in this dictionary,
per this definition, how many more
steps does it take to find Maxwell?
M-A-X-W-E-L-L.
How about if there's four
billion names in the dictionary?
How long does it take to find Maxwell?
M-A-X-W-E-L-L. it's invariant.
And if we assume that no human
name is going to be super long,
it's effectively constant whether it's
10 characters, maybe 30 characters
or whatnot.
That's effectively constant, which means
a trie gives you constant time look up
or big O of one, which means it's in
theory the fastest of data structures.
But of course you pay a
price with more memory.
And I know we're one minute over but
let me tease you with this final look.
And you'll see this data structure's
implementation with Zamyla.
But we begin to do transitionally
now, especially if you're
a little worried, especially as we're
coming on the midpoint of the semester,
like oh my god.
Things are getting more
and more sophisticated.
We're kind of at the peak of a
hill here because after problem set
five do we transition to HTML and
CSS and Python and JavaScript and web
programming more generally.
And next week, how the internet works.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
- He came with a message,
with a protocol all his own.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
He came to a world of cruel firewalls,
uncuring routers, and dangers
from worse than death.
He's fast.
He's strong.
He's TCPIP.
And he's got your address.
Warriors of the net.
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
All that and more next week.
We'll see you then.